<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Choice Accounts of the Types of Physicians</title>
        <author ref="https://usaybia.net/person/1">Ibn Abī Uṣaybiʿa</author>
        <sponsor ref="https://www.uni-muenchen.de">
          <orgName>Ludwig Maximilian University of Munich</orgName>
          (<orgName xml:lang="de">Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München</orgName>)
        </sponsor>
        <sponsor ref="http://www.naher-osten.uni-muenchen.de">
          <orgName>Institute of Near and Middle Eastern Studies</orgName>
          (<orgName xml:lang="de">Institut für den Nahen und Mittleren Osten</orgName>)
        </sponsor>
        <funder ref="https://www.bmbf.de/">
          <orgName>German Federal Ministry of Education and Research</orgName>
          (<orgName xml:lang="de">Bundesministerium für Bildung und Forschung</orgName>)
        </funder>
        <principal ref="#ngibson">Nathan P. Gibson</principal>
        <editor xml:id="ngibson" role="editor" ref="https://usaybia.net/documentation/editors.xml#ngibson 
          http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.html#ngibson 
          https://www.naher-osten.uni-muenchen.de/personen/wiss_ma/gibson/index.html
          http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0786-8075
          http://viaf.org/viaf/59147905242279092527">Nathan P. Gibson</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Conversion to TEI and initial correction of name transcription by </resp>
          <name type="person" ref="https://usaybia.net/editors.xml#ngibson">Nathan P. Gibson</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Additional name correction and page number alignment by </resp>
          <name type="person" ref="https://usaybia.net/editors.xml#vbirkhahn">Vanessa Birkhahn</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.1"/>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>based upon</resp>
          <name><ptr target="#sourceDesc1"/></name>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor><placeName>Ludwig Maximilian University of Munich, Institute of Near and Middle Eastern Studies</placeName></distributor>
        <authority>
          <orgName ref="https://usaybia.net">Communities of Knowledge: Interreligious Networks of Scholars in Ibn Abi Usaybiʿa’s History of the Physicians</orgName>
          (<orgName xml:lang="de"  ref="https://usaybia.net">Wissensgemeinschaften: Interreligiöse Gelehrtennetzwerke in Ibn Abi Usaybiʿa’s Geschichte der Ärzte</orgName>)
        </authority>
        <idno type="URI">https://usaybia.net/text/2</idno>
        <availability>
          <p/>
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
            <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p></licence>
          <ab><note>This electronic edition is designed for open access reuse. The base
            text is in the public domain, since the translation was conducted on behalf of 
            the United States government for the National Library of Medicine. 
            The TEI XML edition is copyrighted the Wissensgemeinschaften team and is released under a 
            Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
            Public License (CC BY 4.0).</note></ab>
          <ab>
            <!-- Is the HTML copyright notice here accurate? -->
            <note>The HTML code is copyrighted by Vanderbilt University and released under a
              under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Public License (CC-BY
              4.0, https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). Attribution for reuse
              should follow the suggested citation and also credit the copyright holder of
              the TEI XML edition.</note>
          </ab>
        </availability>
        <date calendar="Gregorian">2019-10-22</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc xml:id="sourceDesc1">
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Ibn Abi Usaibia</author>
            <editor role="translator">Lothar Kopf</editor>
            <editor role="annotator">M. Plessner</editor>
            <editor role="html-encoder">Roger Pearse</editor>
            <title>History of physicians</title>
            <ptr target="http://www.tertullian.org/fathers/ibn_abi_usaibia_03.htm"/>
            <respStmt>
              <resp when="2011">This text was transcribed by </resp>
              <name type="person" ref="https://www.roger-pearse.com">Roger Pearse (Ipswich,
                UK)</name>
            </respStmt>
            <availability>
              <licence>public domain</licence>
            </availability>
            <imprint>
              <date>1971</date>
            </imprint>
            <biblScope unit="page" from="929" to="946">929–946</biblScope>
            <funder>Translated for the National Library of Medicine, Bethesda, Maryland, under the
              Special Foreign Currency Program, carried out under a National Science Foundation
              Contract with the Israel Program for Scientific Translations, Jerusalem,
              Israel</funder>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-24">CREATED: Pasted HTML into TEI body, created
        teiHeader</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-24">replaced
        '&lt;p>&lt;u>(.+?)&lt;/p>[\n\s\t]*&lt;p> &lt;/p>' with '&lt;div>&lt;u>\1&lt;/div>'</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-24">replaced '&lt;div>&lt;u>(.+?)&lt;/u>' with
        '&lt;div>&lt;head>\1&lt;/head>'</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-24">replaced '&lt;head>(.+?)&lt;/head>' with
        '&lt;head>&lt;persName>\1&lt;/persName>&lt;/head>'</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-24">replaced '&lt;/div>' with '&lt;/p>&lt;/div>'</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-24">replaced '&lt;a name="p(\d+)">.+?&lt;/a>' with '&lt;pb
        n="\1" ed="kopf"/>'</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-24">replaced '&lt;p>&lt;a
        name="(\d+)".+?(FN\d+).+?&lt;/b>\s*(.+?)&lt;/p>' with '&lt;note n="\1"
        xml:id="\2">\3&lt;/note>'</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-24">replaced '&lt;a name="(FN\d+)"/>&lt;a
        href="#\d+">&lt;sup>(\d+)&lt;/sup>&lt;/a>' with '&lt;ref target="#\1"
        type="noteAnchor">\2&lt;/ref>'</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-24">replaced '&lt;blockquote>[\s\n\t]*&lt;p>(.+?)&lt;br/>'
        with '&lt;blockquote>&lt;p>&lt;l>\1&lt;/l>'</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-25">added various missing end tags (esp. div before
        hr)</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-25">removed font and hr HTML tags</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-25">replaced &lt;/l>(.+?)&lt;/p> with
        &lt;/l>&lt;l>\1&lt;/l>&lt;/p> in xpath //p</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-25">replaced &lt;br/> with &lt;/l>&lt;l> in xpath
        //l</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-25">replaced
        (&lt;blockquote>[\s\n\t]*)+(.+?)([\s\n\t]*&lt;/blockquote>)+ with
        &lt;quote>\2&lt;/quote></change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-25">formatted manuscript volume 4 title page</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-25">replaced &lt;sup>(.+?)&lt;/sup> with \1</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-29">formatted footnote section (back/div) and
        respStmt</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-29">replaced &lt;p>(\d+)\)(.+?)&lt;/p> with &lt;item
        n="\1">\2&lt;/item></change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-29">replaced &lt;item(.+)&lt;/item> with
        &lt;list>&lt;item\1&lt;/item> in xpath //item[preceding-sibling::p][1]</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-29">replaced &lt;/item>([\s\t\n]*)&lt;p> with
        &lt;/item>&lt;/list>\1&lt;p> (required additional correction)</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-02-01">used find/replace to correct transcription of common
        names: Muḥammad, al-Ḥasan, Ḥusayn, Aḥmad, ʿAlī, Masīḥī, Isḥāq, Isḥaq, Raḥīm, Raḥmān, Raḥman,
        Ismāʿīl, Yaḥyā, Yuḥannā, Yūḥannā</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-02-01">corrected transcription by replacing (\W)ibn(\W) with
        \1b.\2</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-02-01">corrected transcription by replacing` with ʿ</change>
      <change who="vbirkhahn" when="2019-10-09">corrected transcriptions and added Mueller page numbers (2.239-274)</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-10-14">edited transcriptions and Mueller page numbers (2.239-274)</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en" style="direction: ltr">
    <body>
      <div n="15" type="chapter">
        <head>CHAPTER XV: On the Classes of Famous Syrian Physicians</head>
        <div>
          <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.256"/>
          <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.257"/>
          <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.258"/>
          <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.259"/>
          <p>My uncle Rashīd al-Dīn ʿAlī al-Khalīfa wrote the following books:</p>
          <list>
            <item n="1"> A useful abridgment of the science of mathematics; four treatises,
              dedicated to al-Malik al Amjad the ruler of Baʿalbekk, presented in Safar, 608/1211,
              while they were encamped on the mountain.</item>
            <item n="2"> "On Mensuration."</item>
            <item n="3"> "On Medicine"; a book dedicated to al-Malik al-Muʿayyad Najm al-Dīn Masʿūd
              b. al-Malik al-Nāsir Salāh al-Dīn Yūsuf b. Ayyūb; in it he summarizes the general
              rules of medicine and mentioned different maladies with their causes and
              remedies.</item>
            <item n="4"> "On Popular Medicine"; dedicated to one of his disciples, in which he
              mentions all the maladies which occur frequently and their treatment by remedies which
              are easily accessible and known to all.</item>
            <item n="5"> A treatise on the relationship and parallelism of the pulse to muscular
              rhythms.</item>
            <item n="6"> A treatise on the genesis of mountains; dedicated to al-Malik
              al-Amjad.</item>
            <item n="7"> "On the Elements."</item>
            <item n="8"> "Notes and Experiments in Medicine." <pb n="930" ed="kopf"/>
            </item>
          </list></div><div><head><persName>Badr al-Dīn,</persName></head>
          <p> the son of the Judge of Baʿalbekk. The illustrious physician and accomplished scholar
            Badr al-Dīn al-Muzaffar, the son of the judge and learned Imām Majd al-Dīn Abd
            al-Raḥmān b. Ibrāhīm was the son of the Judge of Baʿalbekk. He grew up in Damascus,
            where he studied medicine. An indescribable amount of precious knowledge, extreme
            intelligence and manly valor was. imbued into his soul by God the Omnipotent. He studied
            medicine under our master the physician Muhadhdhab al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Raḥīm b. ʿAlī, may he
            be blessed, and within the shortest possible time reached to perfection in both its
            theoretical and practical aspects. He was highly ambitious in his work and his soul
            contained all virtues I found him to study with a conscientiousness unmatched by any of
            the other students, for he never ceased to increase his knowledge, improve his
            scholarship and deepen his understanding. He knew many medical books and philosophical
            works by heart. The following story, to which I myself was a witness, may serve as proof
            of his high ambition and fine character. The shaykh Muhadhab al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Raḥīm ʿAlī
            had composed a treatise on vomiting. Each of his disciples studied it with him but Badr
            al-Dīn learnt it by heart and recited it from memory, without referring to the text,
            from beginning to end. For this the shaykh esteemed him highly. Our physician was
            attached to this shaykh, assiduously reading and studying under his guidance.</p>
          <p>In the year 622/1225, when Shaykh Muhadhdhab al-Dīn traveled to the East in order to
            join the service of al-Malik al-Ashraf Mūsā b. al-Malik al-ʿĀdil, he was accompanied by
            Badr al-Dīn, who continued to study with him. Later, Badr al-Dīn worked at the hospital
            of al-Raqqa and composed a fine treatise on the weather, conditions and predominant
            characteristics of this locality. He stayed in al-Raqqa for many years and studied
            philosophy under Zain al-Dīn the blind, may he be blessed, who was a master in the <pb
              n="931" ed="kopf"/> philosophical sciences. He then returned to Damascus, When
            al-Malik al-Gawād Muzaffar al-Dīn Yūnus b. Shams al-Dīn Mamdūd b. al-Malik al-ʿĀdil
            conquered Damascus in the year 635/1237, he called Badr al-Dīn to his service. The
            latter became a favorite, enjoying an important position in the government. The Sultan
            relied upon him in all medical matters and appointed him chief of all the physicians,
            oculists and surgeons, to which effect he gave him a written <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.260"/>
            certificate in the month of Safar 637/1239.</p>
          <p>Badr al-Dīn revived the long-forgotten virtues of medicine and instilled new life into
            its neglected merits by his continuous desire for doing good and his ceaseless concern
            for the general weal. The achievement which I now relate is the one I find the most
            beneficial, having the most long-lasting effect and gaining him the highest deserved
            reward: He expended all his efforts to buy many houses adjacent to the Great Hospital
            built and provided for [by mortmains] by al-Malik al-ʿAdil Nūr al-Dīn Mahmud b. Zenkī,
            may Allāh bless him; he worked hard for this and paid for it with his own money, until
            he annexed these houses to the hospital and incorporated them into it. He enlarged small
            rooms in order that they might serve as wards for the sick, reconstructed them in the
            best way, plastered them and installed running water in them, so that the hospital was
            improved by this most noble deed.</p>
          <p>Still he did not give up teaching medicine and also served as a physician in the fort
            of Damascus, at the "happy palace," treating the royal family of al-Malik al-Sālāh Najm
            al-Dīn Ayyūb b. al-Malik al-Kāmil and others who took refuge there, frequenting the
            hospital from time to time and practicing there as well. This ruler also gave him a
            written certificate, appointing him head physician, in the year 645/1247. Badr al-Dīn
            also attended several of his successors in Damascus, enjoying a permanent salary, a
            stable rank, an important position and the highest favors, while he went on visiting the
            fort and the hospital, increasing his knowledge in his leisure time. <pb n="932"
              ed="kopf"/>
          </p>
          <p>The following story may illustrate his high ambition and nobility of soul. He devoted
            himself to the science of religious law, spending much of his time in a room in the
            madrassa named Qiligiya, which was built by the Emir Saīf al-Dīn b. Qilij, may he be
            blessed, which was adjacent to his house. He studied books on jurisprudence and the
            literary arts, learnt the Qur'ān by heart to perfection and came to know its
            commentaries and modes of reading so well that he was considered an authority in the
            field. His master was the shaykh and Imām Shihāb al-Dīn Abū Shama, may Allāh bless him.
            Badr al-Dīn's sole interest lay in worship and religion and in being of assistance to
            other muslims.</p>
          <p>The fame of his nobility, generosity and kindness was continuously reaching my ears,
            until one of his works, a book entitled "The Soul-Cheerer" fell into my hands. I then
            wrote to him concerning the epistle "The Pious Bequest of a Mamluk," written by our
            master the physician and learned Imam Badr al-Dīn, may God strengthen his happiness and
            prolong his leadership, and contained in his unrivaled book in his concise style, called
            "The Soul-Cheerer, the originator of joy and happiness." In this book he surpassed
            former scholars, preceded all other physicians and philosophers, liberated anguished
            hearts and became the unquestionable leader in his lofty rank, with nobody to vie for
            his perfection and mastership. He is our lord, the shaykh of our times and the example
            of our generation. May God render his life full of happiness and fill the earth with his
            writings, so that many will be able to benefit by them!</p>
          <p>In the same epistle I included the following verses, addressed to him
            extemporaneously:</p>
          <quote><p><l>The rising sun was almost eclipsed by the radiance of Badr al-Dīn,</l><l> A
                virtuous physician, a noble scholar, both in heart and soul. <pb n="933" ed="kopf"/>
              </l><l> The most learned of men in the medical art, the science of feeling the
                pulse,</l><l> An expert in curing, not by guesswork, but by sound knowledge;</l><l>
                From Hippocrates and "the old master," from the Greeks and Persians [he got his
                art];</l><l> How many are those whom he has restored to health, saving them from the
                contrary!</l><pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.261"/>
                <l> His opinion is loftier than that of Qais and his style more perfect
                than that of Quss;</l><l> Indeed he presented my heart with his book "The
                Soul-Cheerer,"</l><l> A book which leads us into the world of holiness,</l><l> The
                light of its import shines in the darkness of my soul.</l><l> How beautiful is the
                flower of the handwriting in the paper-garden!</l><l> When the eye falls upon its
                first thoughts, it is refreshed;</l><l> How much comfort and delight I have received
                from it!</l><l> I have accepted its contents with kisses and learning,</l><l> And
                shall gather its fruit, sweeter than that of the sweetest fruit
            tree.</l></p></quote>
          <p>I included the following verses in another epistle . . . . . . . . . . </p>
          <p>May God prolong the life of his majesty the illustrious master, the learned scholar,
            the honorable leader, the standard of our generation and unique one of our times, the
            full moon of religion [Badr al-Dīn], the support of kings and sultans, an intimate
            friend of the Emir of the Faithful and the guardian of his virtues. May God accord him,
            in both this world and the next, the fulfillment of all his desires; may he cast down
            all his envious enemies; may happiness reside always in his home and may tongues never
            cease singing his praise in harmony. The mamluk [Ibn Abū Usaybiʿah uses this term here
            in reference to himself] ends [his <pb n="934" ed="kopf"/> epistle] by expressing his
            great longing to serve Badr al-Dīn. Had he the eloquence of the master shaykh together
            with Galen's prosy style, he still would have been unable to describe the depth of his
            yearnings and the magnitude of his suffering because of the separation. He prays to God
            the Omnipotent to facilitate their prompt meeting and make it good and beneficial. When
            your obedient servant heard of your appointment as chief of all the physicians, which
            was a sign of God's favor to them and their salvation from all pain, he rejoiced and
            reached the summit of his desires, realizing that God has indeed looked upon his people
            with a benevolent eye and gathered them under his generous protection. [By this
            appointment] the profession was raised in importance, its light spread, its fame grew
            together with its great favor, fortune and radiant splendor. Because of him, our
            generation is ennobled by medicine more than other generations and the status of science
            is the contrary to what was described by Ibn al-Hatīb in his book "Commentary on the
            Universals." Glory be to God for his all-embracing favors and perfect kindness! But our
            master is the first to be appointed chief of the profession and leader of the other
            masters and scholars. </p>
          <quote><p><l>And it could not be so good, were it not for him; </l><l> And he could not be
                so successful, were it not for it.</l></p></quote>
          <p>[Even after his appointment] the signs of glory continued to shine through all his
            deeds and the marks of superiority proved his virtues and nobility. May God the
            Omnipotent aid him in his new post and help him in everything he does now and in the
            future, if he so wishes!"</p>
            <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.262"/>
          <p>The following verses are part of a poem which I addressed to him in the year
            645/1247:</p>
          <quote><p><l>I wrote with unreined passion, with an extreme delight that grew constantly
                with the passing of time; <pb n="935" ed="kopf"/>
              </l><l> With unceasing longings for him who keeps attracting my thoughts and is the
                subject of all my good wishes:</l><l> He is the master Badr al-Dīn, the noble and
                praiseworthy, in the apogee of height, unique in his generation;</l><l> A physician
                who masters all that Hippocrates had said before, and knows all that Galen said
                later;</l><l> Who is versed in the discussions of the "old master" which sound, when
                read by him, like pearls;</l><l> Indeed when these pearls of speech come from the
                sea of his learning, it is no wonder, for pearls do come from the sea;</l><l> When
                he quotes others, his words are like magic, but all sweet things come from
                magic;</l><l> When he treats a sick man and aids the poor, both his nobility and
                virtues are shown in the recovery and benevolence.</l></p></quote>
          <p>The mamluk kisses the hand of the illustrious master and scholarly physician, the noble
            chief and unrivaled leader, the hand of Badr al-Dīn, may God prolong its strength and
            generosity, may he double its favors to the good folk who deserve them and prostrate its
            grudging enemies by the duration of its happiness. May it remain in grace and perpetual
            favor, as long as the days pass into years, as long as the heart pulsates in the
            arteries. May God accord the master our best wishes as long as he still feels the breath
            of life in him; may he well reward him as long as his noble roots still expand and
            branch out; may he make his praise a continuously fragrant perfume in the gardens of
            praise; may he adorn his countenance with the perpetually shining and brilliant fame of
            his benevolence; may he fulfill all our master's passions and desires, which cannot be
            fathomed by words or put down on paper.</p>
          <p>As to the mamlūk, he relies on the master's vast knowledge, sincere love and
            friendliness and his boundless devotion <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.263"/> to his followers and <pb n="936" ed="kopf"/>
            companions. The mamluk has received the epistle of the mamlūk's father with the good
            news, which filled his heart with joy and his soul with delight. Now he knows of the
            master's appointment as chief of all other physicians and of his protection over them by
            his good care and benevolent treatment. His father had described in his epistle the
            master's favors and generosity toward him, his kindness and nobility of spirit which are
            inherent in him and for which he is celebrated. Our master, who knows best the ways of
            honor and the fact that evil men consider the virtues as vices, should be helped by God
            to remain forever doing good, excelling in virtues, reaching the highest ranks, being
            happy and guarded against all misfortune.</p>
          <quote><p><l>This is my prayer, which I could have spared myself, for what I have asked
                God concerning you is already done.</l></p></quote>
          <p>Our master, may the high ranks be beautified by him and the elevated positions become
            even nobler by his fine opinions, has already surpassed by his virtues and nobility all
            those who are famous for their merits, has distinguished himself among all his
            contemporaries for his dignified conduct and good influence. He is the the perfect
            example to other physicians and to all his friends and loves ones.</p>
          <quote><p><l>When men divided happiness among themselves, I got the biggest share;</l><l>
                The mamluk again kisses the hand of his master for his favors, and offers his
                services and full obedience.</l></p></quote>
          <p>Badr al-Dīn the son of the Judge of Baʿalbekk wrote the following books:</p>
          <list>
            <item n="1"> An exhaustive treatise on the weather of al-Raqqa.</item>
            <item n="2"> "The Soul-Cheerer," in which he gives a full account of all the different
              kinds of heart ailments and their remedies; this is a very <pb n="937" ed="kopf"/>
              useful book, dedicated to the Emir Saiīf al-Dīn al-Mushid Abī al-Ḥasan ʿAlī b. ʿUmar
              b. Qizil, may Allāh have mercy upon him. </item>
            <item n="3"> "Medical Anecdotes," in which he includes many useful facts taken from the
              books by Galen and others.</item>
          </list>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head><persName>Shams al-Dīn Muḥammad "the Universal."</persName></head>
          <p> The illustrious physician and unique scholar Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad b. Ibrāhīm b. Abī
            al-Mahāsin was the son of a Spaniard who lived in North Africa and later settled in
            Damascus where he remained until his death, may he be blessed. The physician Shams
            al-Dīn Muḥammad grew up in Damascus and studied medicine under our master the physician
            Muhadhdhab al-Dīn ʿAbd al Raḥīm b. ʿAlī, may Allāh bless him. He devpted himself to his
            master assiduously and came to master all those things from the books of the ancients
            which one must know and which are studied by all medical students. The physician Shams
            al-Dīn was so far in his studies, that he memorized all of the first book of the Qānūn,
            which contains the universals. He acquired a perfect knowledge and understanding of
            them, and was therefore nicknamed "the Universal."</p>

          <p>In addition he studied many practical books and started exercising his profession,
            well-equipped with understanding and knowledge, but never failing to continue his
            studies during all his leisure time and ever increasing his knowledge under all
            circumstances. His appearance was pleasing and his conversation quite witty. He served
            as physician to al-Malik al-Ashraf Mūsā b. al-Malik al-ʿAdil in Damascus, until this
            ruler died, may he be blessed. He then practiced in the Great Hospital built by al-Malik
            al-ʿĀdil Nūr al-Dīn Zenkī, may he be blessed, for a long while, visiting it frequently
            and treating the inmates.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head><persName>Muwaffaq al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Salām</persName></head>
          <p> united in himself medical skill, the philosophical sciences, a praiseworthy character
            and sound <pb n="938" ed="kopf"/>opinion, perfect virtue and all-embracing kindness. He
            was a native of Hamāt, but moved to Damascus, where he studied under our master the
            physician Muhadhdhab al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Raḥīm b. ʿAlī and others. Having distinguished
            himself in medicine, he traveled to Aleppo, where he increased his knowledge. He served
            al-Malik al-Nāsir Yūsuf b. Muḥammad b. Ghāzī, <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.264"/>
            the ruler of Aleppo, until the latter
            conquered Damascus. Our physician accompanied him there, being greatly relied upon and
            receiving many favors. I have written the following poem to express my nostalgia for
            Damascus, in which I described the city and praise the physician Muwaffaq al-Dīn [. . .
            ]</p>
          <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.265"/>
          <p>When the Tatars turned in the direction of Damascus and its people heard of their
            movements, the physician Muwaffaq al-Dīn went to Egypt, where he lived for a long
            period. Later he served al-Malik al-Mansūr, the ruler of Hamāt, staying with him there.
            He was highly privileged, enjoyed an elevated position and received boundless favors and
            respect.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head><persName>Muwaffaq al-Dīn al-Minfāh.</persName></head>
          <p> The physician and unique scholar Abū al-Fadl Asʿad b. Hilwān was a native of
            al-Maʿarra. He studied medicine and became a distinguished practitioner. He served
            al-Malik al-Asraf Mūsā b. Abū Bakr b. Ayyūb in the East, staying in his service for many
            years until their separation. He died in Hamāt in the year 642/1244-5.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head><persName>Najm al-Dīn b. al-Minfākh.</persName></head>
          <p> The illustrious physician and noble scholar Abū al-Abbās Aḥmad b. Abū al-Fadl Asʿad b.
            Ḥilwān —known as the "daughter of Dahin al-Luz" [the one anointed with almond-oil] — was
            born in Damascus in the year 593/1196. He was swarthy and skinny; keen-witted, highly
            intelligent and eloquent, accomplished to the point where nobody could match him in
            research nor equal him in discussion. He studied under our master the <pb n="939"
              ed="kopf"/> physician Muhadhdhab al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Raḥīm b. ʿAlī, until he perfected
            himself in the medical science.</p>
          <p>He was also distinguished in the philosophical sciences and well-versed in logic. His
            writings are witty and well composed, as he was also a literary master. He wrote
            epistles and poetry as well, knew how to play the lute, and had a fine handwriting. He
            was physician to al-Malik al-Masʿūd, the ruler of ʿAamid and became his favorite and his
            vizier. [But] later this ruler was to avenge himself on him, expropriating him
            completely. The physician then went to Damascus and settled there. Many came to study
            medicine under him and he became a distinguished citizen. The governor Jamāl al-Dīn b.
            Matrūḥ wrote him the following poem in answer to his letter [on praising his
            handwriting] ....</p>
          <p>Najm al-Dīn, may he be blessed, was, because of his sharp temperament, an impatient man
            in his attitude and speech. A group of people envied him his superiority and devised
            ways to harm him. One day he recited the following allegorical poem to me [ . . . . . .
            ]</p>
          <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.266"/>
          <p>In his old age he served al-Malik al-Ashraf b. al-Malik al-Mansūr the ruler of Homs in
            Tell Bāshir. He remained in his service for a short period and died, may he be blessed,
            on the 13th of the Dhu al-Qaʿda, 652/1254. His half brother by his mother the judge
            Shihāb al-Dīn the son of a dancer, told me that he had died of poison.</p>

          <p>His books are:</p>
          <list>
            <item n="1"> "The Minute Analysis of the General and the Different," in which he
              mentions all illnesses, their similarities and differences in most cases.</item>
            <item n="2"> "The Disclosure of Secrets in Abundant Treasures," notes on what he gained
              from his experiments et al.</item>
            <item n="3"> A commentary on prophetic traditions dealing with medical matters. <pb
                n="940" ed="kopf"/>
            </item>
            <item n="4"> "The Neglected Things in the 'Book of Universals'. "</item>
            <item n="5"> "Introduction to Medicine."</item>
            <item n="6"> "On Causes and Accidents."</item>
            <item n="7"> "Guidelines Concerning Simple Drugs."</item>
          </list>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head><persName>Ibn al-Suwaīdī.</persName></head>
          <p> The illustrious physician and peerless scholar Abū Isḥāq Ibrāhīm b. Muḥammad ʿIzz al
            Dīn b. al-Suwaīdī was a descendant of Saʿd b. Maʿād from the tribe of Aws. He was born
            in the year 600/1203 in Damascus, where he grew up to become the standard of his times
            and singularity of his generation. He united in himself all the virtues, an extreme
            generosity, noble ancestry and perfect manliness, boundless kindness and constant
            amiability. He studied medicine until he mastered it utterly and reached a degree of
            knowledge unattained by any other master. He was well-versed in both its generalia and
            specialia, and used to meet with the best physicians and greatest philosophers, from
            whom he learnt medical usages and philosophical secrets. Among them was our master the
            physician Muhadhdhab al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Raḥīm b. ʿAlī.</p>
          <p>He also studied literature, in which he reached perfection, and Arabic. He was
            accomplished in all the literary arts and his poetry was unmatched by either the
            ancients or his contemporaries. It contained eloquent phrases and truthful meanings,
            clever puns and excellent parallels. Indeed he united in himself all the different
            sciences, and was equally masterful in poetry and prose. He was the quickest of men in
            composing poetry extempore and the most gifted in declaiming it. I witnessed him several
            times recite a poem he had composed on the spur of the moment, rich in various meanings,
            which nobody else could do, for this art was his specialty.</p>
          <p>His father, may he be blessed, was a merchant from al-Suwaīdī in the Horān, a man of
            good character, fine origins, gentle speech and noble deeds. He was a friend of my
            father's, and the <pb n="941" ed="kopf"/> ties between them were solid, intimate and
            praiseworthy. I also used to study with ʿIzz al Dīn in the same school, our master being
            Abū Bakr al-Saqalī, may he be blessed. Our old friendship remained the same in spite of
            the passing of time, and even grew steadily with it. The physician ʿIzz al-Dīn is indeed
            the most illustrious among all others with respect to his knowledge and memory,
            treatment and conversation, successful cures and precise methods. He is still practicing
            in the ʿNurī hospital, according the sick their heart's desires by banishing their
            maladies and bestowing upon them the finest gift in the form of their recovered health.
            He also used to frequent the hospital at the Postage Gate as well as in the fort of
            Damascus and was, in addition, the instructor of the Dahwāryīa. He received salaries
            from all of these four posts.</p>
          <p>ʿIzz al-Dīn copied in his own handwriting many medical books and works in other
            sciences — some of them in the script of Ibn al-Bawāb and others in the script of the
            Kufi school of Mawlid. Both his scripts were cleared than the brilliant stars and
            brighter than splendid jewels, finer than luxuriant gardens and more radiant than the
            rising sun. He told me that he had copied three versions of the Ibn Sīnā's Qānūn. In the
            year 632/1234 a merchant from Persia arrived in Damascus with a copy of 
            <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.267"/> Ibn Abī Ṣādiq's
            commentary to Galen's book "The Benefits of the Members." This copy was a correct one,
            taken from the author's manuscript, which had not been available in Syria previously. My
            father acquired it, on which occasion ʿIzz al-Dīn b. al-Suwaīdī wrote him a poem
            praising him, from which I recall the following lines:</p>
          <quote><p><l>Be praised, for you are the owner of noble and sublime things of the
                commentary on the book "The Benefits of the Members";</l><l> The lending of rare
                books is still a habit among the learned and virtuous. <pb n="942" ed="kopf"/>
              </l></p></quote>
          <p>So my father sent him the book, which was in two volumes. He made a copy of it, in the
            most beautiful handwriting and with the finest accuracy. </p>
          <p>The following are samples of his poetry, as he himself recited to me:</p>

          <p>[Concerning his worries, i.e., having to dye his hair black. . . . ] </p>
          <p>[Concerning my book on the history of physicians, known as "Important Information
            Concerning the Classes of Physicians"] . . . . </p>
          <p>[A riddle on the name ʿAlī] . . . . </p>
          <p>[Two other small poems] . . . .  </p>
          <p>His books are: </p>
          <list>
            <item n="1"> "The Brilliant Book of Jewels."</item>
            <item n="2"> "The Guiding Advice and Sufficient Treasures of Medicine."</item>
          </list>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head><persName>ʿImad al-Dīn al-Danīsrī.</persName></head>
          <p> The learned physician and supreme literary man Imad al-Dīn Abū Abd Allāh Muḥammad, the
            son of the judge and preacher Taqi al-Dīn Abbas b. Aḥmad b. ʿUbayd al-Rabʿī, was like
            his father, a man of virtuous soul and perfect manliness, complete magnanimity and
            all-embracing generosity, great intelligence and outstanding knowledge. 
             He was born <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.268"/>in
            the year 605/1208 in the city of Danīsr, where he grew up and studied the medical
            profession. He distinguished himself in this science and mastered all its import, being
            capable of maintaining existing health and restoring it when lost. I first met him in
            Damascus in Dhū al-Qaʿadah, 667/1258, finding him a man of firm character, resolute
            nature, manners sweeter than the breeze and words gentler than the air of paradise.</p>
          <p>He declaimed to me some of his poetry, excellent in meaning and sublime in purpose,
            containing different puns and precious parallels, eloquent phrases and truthful imports.
            As to medicine, he distingushed himself more than any of the ancients or his
            contemporaries, while <pb n="943" ed="kopf"/> in literature he was unrivaled by any poet
            or prose-writer. In addition to all this he was the leader of his generation and
            standard of his times in the science of religious law, according to the school of the
            Shafiʿite Imam. He had traveled from Danīsr to Egypt and then returned to Syria and
            settled in Damascus, where he served the families descending from al-Malik al-Nāsir
            Yūsuf in the fort of the city. He also frequented the Nurī Great Hospital in
            Damascus.</p>
          <p>The following are examples of his poetry, as he recited to me [mostly love poems
            addressed to boys] . . . .  </p>
          <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.269"/>
          <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.270"/>
          <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.271"/>
          <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.272"/>
          <p>His books are:</p>
          <list>
            <item n="1"> "The Guiding Treatise on the Grades of Simple Drugs."</item>
            <item n="2"> A general pharmacopoeia in verse.</item>
            <item n="3"> "On the Mithridaticus."</item>
            <item n="4"> "An Introduction to the Study of Hippocrates," a poem in short
              meter.</item>
            <item n="5"> An anthology of his poetry.</item>
          </list>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head><persName>Muwaffaq al-Dīn Yaʿqūb, the Samarītan.</persName></head>
          <p> The illustrious physician and unrivaled scholar, the leader of his generation and
            standard of his times, Abū Yūsuf Yaʿqub, was born and bred in Damascus. He
            distinguished himself in the science of medicine, but was also well-versed in all the
            philosophical sciences. <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.273"/>His medical knowledge 
             was perfect in both theory and practice,
            as he had mastered all its generalia and specialia; he was praised for his treatment and
            thanked for his conversation, which was noble among the notables and distinguished at
            all other times. He was a sound prop concerning the restoration and maintenance of
            health.</p>
          <p>A large group of physicians used to study under him and many students benefited from
            his knowledge. His writings have an eloquent turn of phrase and are truthful in meaning,
            sound in composition and of great significance. <pb n="944" ed="kopf"/>
          </p>
          <p>Muwuffaq al-Dīn Yaʿqūb al Sāmīrī wrote the following books:</p>
          <list>
            <item n="1"> A commentary on the universal contained in Ibn Sīnā's "Qānūn," In which he
              summarizes all Ibn Khatīb al-Ray's sayings on this subject in his commentary on the
              universal, al-Qutb al-Misrī's in his commentary on them, and also the sayings of
              others. His edition points out the contradictions In the respective utterances and is
              well composed and eloquently styled.</item>
            <item n="2"> "The Solution of Najm al-Dīn b. al-Minfagh's Doubts Concerning the
              Universals."</item>
            <item n="3"> "Introduction to the Sciences of Logic, Physics and Metaphysics." </item>
          </list>
          <p>He died in Ramadan, 681/1282.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head><persName>Abū al-Faraj b. al-Qaff</persName>.</head>
          <p> The illustrious physician and scholar Abū al-Faraj, the son of the peerless and
            learned Shaykh Muwaffaq al-Dīn Yaʿqūb b. Isḥaq b. al-Qaff, a Christian from Karak, was
            born in Karak on Saturday the 13th of Dhū al-Qaʿdah, 630/1232. His father, Muwaffaq
            al-Dīn, was a friend of mine, who kept our relationship intimate and strong throughout
            his life. Being with him was a sweet and precious experience and enjoying his friendship
            more joyful than the happiest wedding. He was the light of his generation and the most
            intelligent of his contemporaries. He was the best at memorizing poetry and an authority
            in history and biographies. He distinguished himself in the knowledge of Arabic and was
            outstanding in the literary arts, uniting in himself all the principles and different
            styles of writing and reaching the utmost in unusual meaning and excellent form. His
            well-proportioned handwriting was a pleasure to the eye, unmatched by any other copyist
            anywhere in the world.</p>
          <p>During the reign of al-Malik al-Nāsir Yūsuf b. Muḥammad he was a scribe in Sarkhad,
            working in the post office. His son Abū al-Faraj showed signs of intelligence from his
            youth, and these were indeed verified when he grew up. He was a good listener and a rare
            talker, <pb n="945" ed="kopf"/> had a broad mind and loved to hear the biographies of
            the learned. His father had the intention of teaching him medicine, and asked me to be
            his master. He attached himself to me until he memorized the first textbooks, such as
            Hunayn's "Problems," Hippocrates' "Aphorisms," the introduction to his study, etc. Abū
            al-Faraj came to know their import, understood the principles of their composition, and
            then continued to study under my guidance the ways of treatment contained in the books
            of Abū Bakr Muḥammad b. Zakarīyya al-Rāzī. Having studied them, he came to know the
            kinds of maladies and the major causes of diseases, mastered diagnostics and
            therapeutics and was familiar with different remedies. I taught him the principles and
            details of all these, their secrets and consequences.</p>
          <p>His father then moved to well-guarded Damascus, where he served in the supreme Divan.
            His son accompanied him there and studied, with a group of notables, the natural
            sciences and the philosophical arts under the master Shams al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Hamīd
            al-Khosrūshāhī and ʿIzz al-Dīn al-Ḥasan al-Ghanawī al-Darīr. He continued his medical
            studies with the physician Najm al-Dīn b. al-Mīnfāgh and Muwaffaq al-Dīn Yaʿqūb, the
            Samaritan. He also studied Euclid's book with the master Muʿayad al-Dīn al-Aradi,
            understanding it so perfectly that he solved all its difficulties.</p>
          <p>Abū al-Faraj b. al-Qaff served as physician in the fort of ʿAglūn, where he stayed for
            several years. He then returned to Damascus and served in its unconquerable fort,
            treating the sick there and being praised for his work and thanked for all his deeds.
            His books are:</p>
          <list>
            <item n="1"> "The Medical Cures."</item>
            <item n="2"> "Commentary on the Universals Contained in Ibn Sīnā's Qānun," in six
              volumes.</item>
            <item n="3"> "Commentary on the 'Aphorisms,'" in two parts.</item>
            <item n="4"> A treatise on the preservation of health. <pb n="946" ed="kopf"/>
            </item>
            <item n="5"> "The Pillar <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.274"/>of Surgery," twenty treatises.</item>
            <item n="6"> Treatise on theory and practice, mentioning all that is necessary for the
              surgeon exclusively.</item>
            <item n="7"> "The Quintessence of the Purpose," in one volume.</item>
            <item n="8"> "Marginal Notes on the Third Book of the Qānūn"; not extant.</item>
            <item n="9"> A commentary on the "Remarks"; a rough draft, unfinished.</item>
            <item n="10"> "North African Researches"; unfinished.</item>
          </list>

          <p>He died in Jumāda I, 685/1286. And Allāh knows best.</p>

        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
