<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Choice Accounts of the Types of Physicians</title>
        <author ref="https://usaybia.net/person/1">Ibn Abī Uṣaybiʿa</author>
        <sponsor ref="https://www.uni-muenchen.de">
          <orgName>Ludwig Maximilian University of Munich</orgName>
          (<orgName xml:lang="de">Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München</orgName>)
        </sponsor>
        <sponsor ref="http://www.naher-osten.uni-muenchen.de">
          <orgName>Institute of Near and Middle Eastern Studies</orgName>
          (<orgName xml:lang="de">Institut für den Nahen und Mittleren Osten</orgName>)
        </sponsor>
        <funder ref="https://www.bmbf.de/">
          <orgName>German Federal Ministry of Education and Research</orgName>
          (<orgName xml:lang="de">Bundesministerium für Bildung und Forschung</orgName>)
        </funder>
        <principal ref="#ngibson">Nathan P. Gibson</principal>
        <editor xml:id="ngibson" role="editor" ref="https://usaybia.net/documentation/editors.xml#ngibson 
          http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.html#ngibson 
          https://www.naher-osten.uni-muenchen.de/personen/wiss_ma/gibson/index.html
          http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0786-8075
          http://viaf.org/viaf/59147905242279092527">Nathan P. Gibson</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Conversion to TEI and initial correction of name transcription by </resp>
          <name type="person" ref="https://usaybia.net/editors.xml#ngibson">Nathan P. Gibson</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Additional name correction and page number alignment by </resp>
          <name type="person" ref="https://usaybia.net/editors.xml#vbirkhahn">Vanessa Birkhahn</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.1"/>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>based upon</resp>
          <name><ptr target="#sourceDesc1"/></name>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor><placeName>Ludwig Maximilian University of Munich, Institute of Near and Middle Eastern Studies</placeName></distributor>
        <authority>
          <orgName ref="https://usaybia.net">Communities of Knowledge: Interreligious Networks of Scholars in Ibn Abi Usaybiʿa’s History of the Physicians</orgName>
          (<orgName xml:lang="de"  ref="https://usaybia.net">Wissensgemeinschaften: Interreligiöse Gelehrtennetzwerke in Ibn Abi Usaybiʿa’s Geschichte der Ärzte</orgName>)
        </authority>
        <idno type="URI">https://usaybia.net/text/2</idno>
        <availability>
          <p/>
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
            <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p></licence>
          <ab><note>This electronic edition is designed for open access reuse. The base
            text is in the public domain, since the translation was conducted on behalf of 
            the United States government for the National Library of Medicine. 
            The TEI XML edition is copyrighted the Wissensgemeinschaften team and is released under a 
            Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
            Public License (CC BY 4.0).</note></ab>
          <ab>
            <!-- Is the HTML copyright notice here accurate? -->
            <note>The HTML code is copyrighted by Vanderbilt University and released under a
              under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Public License (CC-BY
              4.0, https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). Attribution for reuse
              should follow the suggested citation and also credit the copyright holder of
              the TEI XML edition.</note>
          </ab>
        </availability>
        <date calendar="Gregorian">2019-10-22</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc xml:id="sourceDesc1">
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Ibn Abi Usaibia</author>
            <editor role="translator">Lothar Kopf</editor>
            <editor role="annotator">M. Plessner</editor>
            <editor role="html-encoder">Roger Pearse</editor>
            <title>History of physicians</title>
            <ptr target="http://www.tertullian.org/fathers/ibn_abi_usaibia_03.htm"/>
            <respStmt>
              <resp when="2011">This text was transcribed by </resp>
              <name type="person" ref="https://www.roger-pearse.com">Roger Pearse (Ipswich,
                UK)</name>
            </respStmt>
            <availability>
              <licence>public domain</licence>
            </availability>
            <imprint>
              <date>1971</date>
            </imprint>
            <biblScope unit="page" from="901" to="929">901–929</biblScope>
            <funder>Translated for the National Library of Medicine, Bethesda, Maryland, under the
              Special Foreign Currency Program, carried out under a National Science Foundation
              Contract with the Israel Program for Scientific Translations, Jerusalem,
              Israel</funder>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-24">CREATED: Pasted HTML into TEI body, created
        teiHeader</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-24">replaced
        '&lt;p>&lt;u>(.+?)&lt;/p>[\n\s\t]*&lt;p> &lt;/p>' with '&lt;div>&lt;u>\1&lt;/div>'</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-24">replaced '&lt;div>&lt;u>(.+?)&lt;/u>' with
        '&lt;div>&lt;head>\1&lt;/head>'</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-24">replaced '&lt;head>(.+?)&lt;/head>' with
        '&lt;head>&lt;persName>\1&lt;/persName>&lt;/head>'</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-24">replaced '&lt;/div>' with '&lt;/p>&lt;/div>'</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-24">replaced '&lt;a name="p(\d+)">.+?&lt;/a>' with '&lt;pb
        n="\1" ed="kopf"/>'</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-24">replaced '&lt;p>&lt;a
        name="(\d+)".+?(FN\d+).+?&lt;/b>\s*(.+?)&lt;/p>' with '&lt;note n="\1"
        xml:id="\2">\3&lt;/note>'</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-24">replaced '&lt;a name="(FN\d+)"/>&lt;a
        href="#\d+">&lt;sup>(\d+)&lt;/sup>&lt;/a>' with '&lt;ref target="#\1"
        type="noteAnchor">\2&lt;/ref>'</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-24">replaced '&lt;blockquote>[\s\n\t]*&lt;p>(.+?)&lt;br/>'
        with '&lt;blockquote>&lt;p>&lt;l>\1&lt;/l>'</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-25">added various missing end tags (esp. div before
        hr)</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-25">removed font and hr HTML tags</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-25">replaced &lt;/l>(.+?)&lt;/p> with
        &lt;/l>&lt;l>\1&lt;/l>&lt;/p> in xpath //p</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-25">replaced &lt;br/> with &lt;/l>&lt;l> in xpath
        //l</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-25">replaced
        (&lt;blockquote>[\s\n\t]*)+(.+?)([\s\n\t]*&lt;/blockquote>)+ with
        &lt;quote>\2&lt;/quote></change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-25">formatted manuscript volume 4 title page</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-25">replaced &lt;sup>(.+?)&lt;/sup> with \1</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-29">formatted footnote section (back/div) and
        respStmt</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-29">replaced &lt;p>(\d+)\)(.+?)&lt;/p> with &lt;item
        n="\1">\2&lt;/item></change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-29">replaced &lt;item(.+)&lt;/item> with
        &lt;list>&lt;item\1&lt;/item> in xpath //item[preceding-sibling::p][1]</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-01-29">replaced &lt;/item>([\s\t\n]*)&lt;p> with
        &lt;/item>&lt;/list>\1&lt;p> (required additional correction)</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-02-01">used find/replace to correct transcription of common
        names: Muḥammad, al-Ḥasan, Ḥusayn, Aḥmad, ʿAlī, Masīḥī, Isḥāq, Isḥaq, Raḥīm, Raḥmān, Raḥman,
        Ismāʿīl, Yaḥyā, Yuḥannā, Yūḥannā</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-02-01">corrected transcription by replacing (\W)ibn(\W) with
        \1b.\2</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-02-01">corrected transcription by replacing` with ʿ</change>
      <change who="vbirkhahn" when="2019-10-09">corrected transcriptions and added Mueller page numbers (2.239-274)</change>
      <change who="ngibson" when="2019-10-14">edited transcriptions and Mueller page numbers (2.239-274)</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en" style="direction: ltr">
    <body>
      <div n="15" type="chapter">
        <head>CHAPTER XV: On the Classes of Famous Syrian Physicians</head>
        <div>
          <head><persName>Muhadhdhab al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Raḥīm b. ʿAlī</persName></head>
          <p> was our Shaykh, the chief of ministers, the learned and worthy Muhadhdhab al-Dīn ʿAbd
            al-Raḥīm b. ʿAlī b. Ḥāmid, known as al-Dakhwār. He was — may Allāh have mercy upon him —
            unique among his generation, peerless in his time, the most learned scholar of his
            epoch, the apogee of medical skill and knowledge, both general and specialized. No one
            matched him in diligence or learning. He tired himself out with work, straining his mind
            in order to gain knowledge, until he surpassed all contemporary physicians and won more
            remuneration and honor from kings than any doctor had ever before. He was born in
            Damascus and brought up there by his father, ʿAlī b. Ḥāmid, a famous oculist, whose
            other <pb n="902" ed="kopf"/> son, Ḥāmid b. ʿAlī, took up the same profession. At first,
            Muhadhdhab al-Dīn was also an oculist, but at the same time he worked as a copyist. His
            calligraphy was outstanding. He transcribed many books, of which I have seen a hundred
            or more, dealing with medicine and other sciences. He worked for the al-Shaykh Tāj al-Dīn
            al-Kindī Abū al-Yaman, but constantly endeavored to increase his knowledge by reading
            and memorizing — a habit he kept up until old age.</p>
          <p>At the beginning of his medical career, he was introduced to al-Makī's teachings by
            the Shaīkh Radī al-Dīn al-Rahbī — may Allāh have mercy upon him — and then became a
            close associate of Mūwafaq al-Dīn b. al-Mutrān, for whom he worked and from whom he
            learnt the art of medicine. He continued to seek out his company and study his books
            until he became expert. Afterwards Fakhr al-Dīn al-Mardīnī, who came to Damascus in the
            year 579/1189, instructed him to part of Ibn Sīnā's ʿQānūn," which Fakhr al-Dīn knew and
            comprehended thoroughly.</p>
          <p>Muhadhdhab al-Dīn worked as a physician to al-Malik al-ʿAdil Abū Bakr b. Ayyūb. This
            was because at the beginning of his career he was interested in eye diseases and wished
            to gain practice in their treatment. He worked as an oculist in <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.240"/>the Great Hospital
            established by al-Malik al-ʿĀdil Nūr al-Dīn Maḥmūd b. Zankī. Later, when he worked with
            al-Mutrān and had become noted for his medical skill, Safī al-Dīn b. Shakr, the vizier
            of al-Malik al-ʿAdil b. Ayyūb, granted him an allowance, by means of which he was able to
            practice work and at the same time increase his knowledge and proficiency. </p>

          <p> He was tireless in the service of the vizier, and the latter, knowing Muhadhadhab's
            professional merits, preferred him to all others. In the month of Shawwal, 604/1207,
            al-Malik al-ʿĀdil said to Ibn Shakr: "We want another doctor besides Muwaffaq al-Dīn
            ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz for attending the troops. This work is not congenial to <pb n="903"
              ed="kopf"/> ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz, so do as he requests." Said b. Shakr: "We have here an
            excellent physician, named Muhadhdhab al-Dakhwār, who is fit for our master's service."
            Then he ordered him to comply. When Muhadhdhab al-Dīn appeared before the vizier, the
            latter said to him: "I have recommended you to the Sultan, and you are paid a month for
            your services." But Muhadhdhab al-Dīn said: "My lord: The Doctor Muwaffaq al-Dīn ʿAbd
            al-ʿAzīz earns about a hundred dinars monthly.</p>

          <p>I know my status, and I will not serve without a decent wage. Then he took leave of the
            vizier and refused the post. But his companions made him regret his refusal, his lost
            chance to be engaged by the vizier. For his salary at the hospital was very low.</p>
          <p>About that time, Muwaffaq ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz was stricken with severe colitis, which grew
            worse and eventually caused his death. When the news of his passing reached al-Malik
            al-ʿAdil, the latter said to the vizier: "You once recommended to us a doctor by the
            name of Muhadhdhab. Appoint him in place of Muwaffad ʿAbd al-ʿAziz. "So Muhadhdhab got
            all his posts, and he remained in the service of al-Malik al-ʿĀdil from then on. He rose
            steadily in al-Malik al-ʿĀdil's esteem, and his status was enhanced, until he became his
            companion, associate and adviser. At the beginning of his service, al-Malik put his
            knowledge to some unusual tests, and the results strengthened his opinion of him and his
            reliance upon him.</p>
          <p>About that time, al-Malik al-ʿĀdil fell ill. He was attended by the best doctors.
            Muhadhdhab advised bloodletting but the other physicians present did not agree. He said:
            "By Allāh! If we let blood from him, he will bleed without our being able to staunch
            it." But they were still obstinate. Very soon the Sultan began to bleed heavily. When he
            was well again, he realized that Muhadhdhab outshone all the others. <pb n="904"
              ed="kopf"/>
          </p>
          <p>Another story has it that one day, when he was standing at the palace gate with some
            court physicians, a servant came out with a vial containing the urine of one of the
            concubines and reported that she was in pain. When the doctors had inspected the vial,
            they ventured a diagnosis. But Muhadhdhab examined it closely and said: "The pain she
            complains of does not cause this color," suspecting it to be induced by Lawsonia with
            which she had anointed herself. The servant told him that his finding was correct,
            marvelled at him and reported the incident to al-Malik al-ʿĀdil; this increased the
            latter's confidence in Muhadhdhab.</p>
          <p>One of the best anecdotes about Shaykh Muhadhdhab al-Dīn, and one that illustrates his
            savoir-faire and loyalty, is the following which was told my by my father. Once,
            al-Malik al-ʿĀdil was very angry with the chief judge, Muhyī al-Dīn b. Zakī al-Dīn, of
            Damascus. He ordered him to be detained in the fortress, demanded from him the sum of
            10,000 Egyptian dinars and pressed for payment. Muhyī al-Dīn was to remain in prison
            until the amount was settled. He paid some of the money, but was unable to raise the
            balance. Al-Malik al-ʿĀdil was inexorable, saying: "He must pay the rest, otherwise I
            shall deal very harshly with him." The judge was in dire straits. He sold all his
            possessions — his household effects, and <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.241"/> even his books. Then he wrote letters to the
            Sultan, using the good offices of many leading personalities, such as al-Shamīs, the
            court teacher, and Shams al-Khawās the vizier, asking for the remission of part of the
            amount or to be allowed to pay in installments. But the Sultan remained adamant, and as
            a result, the judge was so worried that he hardly ate or slept and thus almost killed
            himself. At this point, his old friend Muhadhdhab al-Dīn paid him a visit. The judge
            told Muhadhdhab al-Dīn his troubles, begging him to do what he could. After some
            consideration, al-Muhadhdhab said: "I shall do something for you. I hope that, God
            willing, it will be of use." Then he departed. <pb n="905" ed="kopf"/>
          </p>
          <p>Serīat al-Malik al-ʿAdil, the mother of al-Malīk al-Sālih b. al-Malīk, was unwell at
            that time. She was of Turkish origin, an intelligent, pious and good woman, very kind
            and generous. When the Doctor Muhadhdhab al-Dīn came to see her in the harem, he
            acquainted her with the case of the judge, his troubles and the unjust treatment meted
            out to him — i.e., that he was being asked to do the impossible — and requested that she
            intervene: perhaps the Sultan could show mercy to him and remit part of the debt or let
            him pay it in installments. The chief eunuch supported Muhadhdhab request. But Seriat
            said: "How can I do anything for the judge, or even mention him to the Sultan? I cannot,
            because he will ask: 'What makes you speak about the judge, and how is it that you know
            him?' If we were, say, a doctor who visits us from time to time, or a merchant who sells
            us cloth, it would be possible for me to talk and intervene; but as it is, I can do
            nothing." When Muhadhdhab heard this, he said: "My lady! You have an only son, whom you
            wish happiness and a long life. Now, you can obtain this for him from Allāh by doing
            something without actually intervening with the Sultan at all." Said she: "And what is
            that?" Said he: "When the Sultan and you sleep together, tell him you have dreamt that
            the judge is being treated unjustly"; and he told her what to say. She thereupon said,
            "It can be done."</p>
          <p>One night, when she was well again and the Sultan was sleeping with her, as the night
            was ending, she pretended to be frightened, clutched at her heart and kept shivering and
            crying. The Sultan, who loved her dearly, noticed it and said: "What is the matter with
            you?" But she did not reply. He then ordered some apple juice to be brought and had her
            drink some, sprinkled her face with rose water and said: "Will you not tell me what has
            happened to you, why you are so upset?" She said: "O Master, I have had a dream which
            almost frightened to death. I dreamt that it was Doomsday and saw a large crowd of <pb
              n="906" ed="kopf"/> people. In one place, where there was a great fire, people were
            saying: "This had been prepared for al-Malīk al-ʿĀdil because of the injustice he did to
            the judge." Then she said: "Have you ever done anything to the judge?" And he, who did
            not doubt her story, became troubled, rose early, called his servants and said to them:
            "Go to the judge and make him happy: give him my regards, ask him to forgive me and tell
            him that all he has paid will be returned to him. As for me, I will ask nothing of him."
            So they went to him. The judge was very pleased with their announcement, blessed the
            Sultan and forgave him. In the same morning the Sultan ordered that he be given a suit
            of clothes and a mule. He restored him to his office and ordered that all the books and
            other possessions he had sold be redeemed from the purchasers for the same amount as
            they had paid. Thus relief was brought to the judge after anguish, by minimum effort and
            the subtlest of tactics.</p>
          <p>In the year 610/1213, when he was in the east, al-Malīk al-ʿĀdil became very ill, and
            Muhadhdhab al-Dīn treated him until he was cured. During that illness, the king paid the
            physician 7,000 Egyptian dinars. In addition, the king's children, some eastern kings
            and others sent him gold, suits of clothes, mule carts, gold neckbands and other
            items.</p>
          <p>A similar event occurred in the year <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.242"/>612/1215, when al-Malīk al-Ādil went to Egypt and
            stayed in Cairo. At that time, a dreadful cholera epidemic killed many people. Among
            those stricken was al-Malīk al-Kāmil b. al-Maīlk al-ʿĀdil, who was the Governor of
            Egypt. Muhadhdhab al-Dīn treated him most solicitously until he became well again. This
            time, Muhadhdhab al-Dīn received 12,000 dinars' worth of gold, besides many suits of
            clothes and other splendid gifts, including fourteen mules carrying golden rings and a
            great deal of satin and other kinds of cloth. <pb n="907" ed="kopf"/>
          </p>
          <p>About that time, the Sultan appointed Muhadhdhab al-Dīn chief physician of Egypt and
            Syria. I was then with my father, who was also in the service of al-Malīk al-ʿĀdil.
            Muhadhdhab al-Dīn was in charge of ophthalmological matters; it was he who decided who
            was qualified to treat eye diseases.</p>
          <p>In the year 614/1217, having learnt of Christian maneuvers near the coast, al-Malik
            al-ʿĀdil went to Syria and stayed at Marj al-Sughr. While he was in a place called
            Manzilat al-Ālekīn, he fell ill and died, may Allāh have mercy upon him. He died in the
            second hour of Friday, the 7th day of Jumādā al-Ākhira, in the year 615/1218.</p>
          <p>When al-Malik al-Muʿazam had established his rule over Syria, he wished to employ
            several of those who had served his father, al-Malik al-ʿĀdil, among them the physician
            Rashīd al-Dīn b. al-Surī, who refused. As for Muhadhdhab al-Dīn, he gave him a salary
            and ordered him to live in Damascus, where he was to treat patients at the Great
            Hospital established by al-Malik al-ʿAdil Nūr al-Dīn b. Zankī.</p>
          <p>When Muhadhdhab al-Dīn was in Damascus, he began to teach medicine, and many of the
            best physicians joined him, besides others that studied under him. I, too, stayed in
            Damascus to learn from him (but I had first worked under him at the military camp where
            my father and he served the great Sultan). I would visit him as one of a group of
            students, and I began to study Galen. He was well-versed in the works of this author and
            others. He admired Galen very much, and whenever someone mentioned anything he had
            written concerning diseases and their therapy or the fundamentals of the medical
            science, he would say: "That is medicine."</p>

          <p>He was quick-witted, a clear thinker and a good conversationalist. I accompanied him on
            his rounds at the hospital, thus gaining personal experience. At that time, his
            associate was the eminent physician ʿAmrān. Later, their collaboration became less
            fruitful. <pb n="908" ed="kopf"/>
          </p>
          <p>Muhadhdhab al-Dīn was a supremely able medical savant and practitioner, the exponent of
            the most effective cures known in his day. Hence he eventually gained the reputation of
            a wizard.</p>
          <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.243"/>
          <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.244"/>
          <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.245"/>
          <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.246"/>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head><persName>My uncle, Rashid al-Dīn ʿĀlī b. Khalīfa.</persName></head>
          <p> Abū al-Ḥasan ʿAlī b. Khalīfa b. Yūnus b. Abī al-Qāsin b. Khalīfa, from [the tribe of]
            Kazraj, the offspring of Saīd b. ʿIbāda, was born in Aleppo in 579/1183. My father was
            born before him, in 575/1179, in Cairo the unconquerable. They both grew up in that
            city, where they also practiced. My gradfather, may he be blessed, was an ambitious man
            who greatly admired virtue and scholarship and was well-versed in the different
            sciences. He was known as Ibn Abī Usaybiʿa. He used to be in the service of al-Malik
            al-Nāsir Salah Al-Din Yūsuf b. Ayyūb and his children, and moved to Egypt when that ruler
            conquered the land. Among my grandfather's Damascene acquaintances and friends were
            Jamāl al-Dīn b. al-Hawāfir the physician and Shihāb al-Dīn Abu al-Hajjāj Yūsuf the
            oculist, for my grandfather was born and raised in Damascus, where he also spent many
            years of his life. By the time he met the two aforesaid gentlement in Egypt, my
            grandfather was already raising my father and uncle. He intended to teach them both
            medicine <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.247"/>, in consideration of the nobleness of this profession and the demand for
            physicians, knowing that he who mastered its principles would be honored and favored in
            this world and attain the highest rank in the hereafter. </p>
          <p>So he attached my father and uncle to these two Shaykhs, in order that they might reap
            from their knowledge. My father was entrusted to Abū al-Hajjaj Yūsuf, in order to study
            ophthalmology and learn its practice. Abū al-Hajjāj was then serving as an oculist in a
            hospital in Cairo, not the one situated in the fort, but one located in the market
            district of lower Cairo. My grandfather used to live just by it, so it was easy for my
            father to frequent Aba al-Hajjāj Yūsuf constantly and <pb n="909" ed="kopf"/> study from
            him until he mastered his field. He also studied with other notable master-physicians
            who lived at that time in Egypt, such as the master Mūsā al-Qurtabī, the author of
            famous works, and others like him. As for my uncle, he was attached to Jamāl al-Dīn b.
            Abī al-Hawāfir and studied general medicine under him.</p>
          <p>My uncle first started his studies with Taqī the Teacher. His full name was Abū al-Taqī
            Sālih b. Aḥmad b. Ibrāhīm b. al-Ḥasan b. Sulaymān from the tribe of Quraish, the
            Jerusalemite. This Taqī was adept in many sciences, had a fine way of teaching in school
            and a celebrated system which no one else could follow. After my uncle, may he be
            blessed, had learned the Qu'rān by heart and perfected his mathematics, all under Taqī,
            he started to study medicine thoroughly under the direction of Jamāl al-Dīn b. Abī
            al-Hawāfir, who was then chief physician of Egypt, under the rule of al-Malik al-ʿAzīz
            ʿOthmān, the son of al-Malik al-Nāsir Salāh al-Dīn. He studied with him parts of Galen's
            Sixteen Books, memorizing the whole of the first ones in the shortest time possible. He
            then joined the physicians in their consultations and their rounds of the patients in
            the hospital, learning the different maladies</p>

          <p>and the appropriate prescriptions. (There was a group of very notable physicians at the
            hospital.) At the same time he studied ophthalmology with the judge Nafīs al-Dīn b.
            al-Zubair, who was then head of the department in the hospital, and started to practice
            it. He also joined him in initiating a surgical department.</p>
          <p>The Shaykh Muwaffaq al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Latīf b. Yūsuf the Baghdadian, an intimate friend of
            my grandfather's was staying in Cairo at the time. My uncle studied a little Arabic and
            philosophy with him and they used to discuss Aristotle's books, debating the difficult
            points. My uncle also used to meet and study with Sadīd al-Dīn the Logician, who was a
            great scholar in the philosophical sciences. Before that, he had studied astronomy under
            Abī Muḥammad b. al-Jaʿdī, an expert <pb n="910" ed="kopf"/> astronomer who was
            celebrated for his judgments. This shaykh lived at the time of the Egyptian caliphs and
            was considered a favorite of theirs; his father was one of the chief emirs of their
            state.</p>
          <p>The art of music my uncle studied under the guidance of Ibn al-Dīgūr the Egyptian and
            Safī al-Dīn Abī ʿAlī b. al-Tabbān. He also knew the elite in this field, such as
            al-Bahā; the great composer, Shihāb al-Dīn al-Naqjūnī, Shujāʿ al-Dīn b. al-Ḥasan the
            Baghdadian and their equals, from which he learnt many Arabic and other melodies. From
            his youth, my uncle devoted all his leisure to study, work and the betterment of his
            soul.</p>
          <p>My grandfather moved back to Syria in 597/1200, when my uncle was about twenty years
            old. He immediately took up practicing medicine and improving his knowledge of it.
            Shaykh Radīʿ al-Dīn Yūsuf b. Haīdara from Rahba, an old friend of my grandfather's, was
            then staying in Damascus. <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.248"/>When he heard of my uncle, saw him at work and realized his virtues, he was happily surprised. My uncle constantly visited his court, studied and
            discussed medical matters with him. He worked in the hospital built by al-Malik al-ʿAdil Nūr al-Dīn b. Zankī, together with other physicians who were there at the time, such as
            Muwaffaq al-Dīn b. al-Saraf and Shaykh Muhadhdhab al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Raḥīm b. ʿAlī. Meanwhile he also studied philosophy under Shaykh Muwaffaq al-Dīn Abd al-Latīf b. Yūsuf
            the Baghdadian, for he too had returned to Syria. There was in Damascus a group of men celebrated for their literary achievements and knowledge of Arabic, such as Zaīn al-Dīn
            b. Muʿtī, with whom my uncle studied and practiced, and Tāj al-Dīn Zaid b. al-Ḥasan al-Kindī Abī al-Yaman, who was an old and intimate friend of my grandfather's since the
            days of ʿIz al-Dīn Farukhshāh. My uncle studied with him too and practiced his Arabic. <pb n="911" ed="kopf"/></p>
          <p>Before my uncle was twenty-five years old, he had already mastered all these sciences,
            becoming an exemplary shaykh in medicine and having his own disciples. He was also
            writing poems and responsa, spoke Persian, knowing all its rules and even composing
            poetry in it, and knew Turkish as well. On Friday the 15th of Ramadān, 605/1208, the
            Sultan al-Malik al-Muʿazzam ʿĪsā b. al-Malik al-ʿĀdil Abū Bakr b. Āyyūb called for him.
            Having conversed with him, he honored and favored him and asked him to stay in his
            service, but difficulties arose because of the Sultan's frequent travels. Some time
            later, al-Malik al-Amjad Majd al-Dīn Bahrām Shah b. ʿIzz al-Dīn Farūkhshāh b. Shāhinshāh
            b. ʿAyyūb, the governor of Baʿalbekk, heard of him and sent for him and my grandfather,
            whom he had known since his father's time. When they both arrived, he welcomed them,
            treated them most generously and allotted them a good salary, expenses and a high rank.
            In consequence, my uncle's position with him became so favorable that he hardly left him
            at all. The governor then became aware of my uncle's mastery of arithmetic and asked him
            to be his teacher in this field. In obedience to this order, my uncle instructed the
            governor thoroughly in this science and even compiled for his use a textbook comprising
            four treatises. Al-Malik al- 'Amjad himself, may Allāh bless him, was a virtuous man who
            showed keen respect to the learned; he wrote fine poetry, including a famous
            authology.</p>
          <p>In the year 609/1212, a dear servant of the Sultan al-Malik al-ʿĀdil Abū Bakr b. Ayyūb,
            called Sulaita, became afflicted with an eye disease. His condition was so bad that his
            sight was diminished and his case considered hopeless. All the best physicians and
            oculists tried to treat him, but none could cure him; so they decided unanimously that
            he would be blind, as no treatment had any effect whatsoever. When my father saw this
            man and examined his eyes, he said; "I will treat this man's eyes and he will see with
            both of them, if God so wishes." He started to treat him, and his condition steadily
            improved, until his recovery was complete. He returned <pb n="912" ed="kopf"/> to his
            former self and was able to ride a horse again, so that everyone was astonished and
            regarded the cure as an unrivaled miracle. In consequence, al-Malik al- Ādil's
            generosity and consideration toward my father increased greatly, and he paid him the
            utmost honor by presenting him with precious robes, etc.</p>
          <p>Even before this event, my father quite frequently, used to visit the Sultan's palace
            in the fort of Damascus, treating those who were afflicted with serious eye diseases and
            curing them in the shortest time conceivable. This also came to the knowledge of
            al-Malik al-ʿĀdil, who said; "Such a man should accompany me wherever I go!" and asked
            him to join his service. My father requested to be excused and given permission to stay
            in Damascus, but this was not granted. The Sultan granted him a salary and expenses, and
            my father enrolled in his service on the 15th of Dhū al-Hijja 609/1212. He was a
            favorite of his and of all his sons and successors, who relied upon him in all medical
            matters and <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.249"/>treated him with great generosity and perfect deference. He remained in
            service until the death of al-Malik al-ʿĀdil, may he be blessed, when he was asked to
            continue in his post by the son and successor in Damascus, al-Malik al-Muʿazam. The
            latter treated him with the same honor and esteem, or even more, as his father had done.
            My father served him from the beginning of Safar 616/1219 until he died, may Allāh have
            mercy upon him, and then was asked by his son, al-Malik al-Nāsir Da'ūd, to stay in his
            service too, promising him all the rights he had enjoyed formerly. My father remained
            until al-Malik al-Nāsir had to leave for Karak, at which point my father chose to stay
            in Damascus.</p>
          <p>He started frequenting the Sultan's palace in the fort, attending all the descendants
            of al-Malik al-ʿĀdil who succeeded him in Damascus and others as well. All revered him
            highly, relied upon him in all medical matters and allotted him a generous salary and
            expenses. He also used to frequent the Great Hospital named after <pb n="913" ed="kopf"
            /> Nur al-Dīn, where he was also remunerated. People used to come to him from every
            quarter, having heard of his rapid cures. The many maladies which were wont to be cured
            by the iron he treated thus to perfection. For other diseases habitually treated by
            drugs he indeed applied drugs, saving the afflicted from the use of the iron. This
            method was praised by Galen in his book "The Test of the Virtuous Physician," saying:
            "Whenever you see a physician administering drugs in the case of maladies which are
            usually treated with the iron, know that he is learned, experienced and skilled." He
            adds: "You should also praise the physician whom you see using drugs exclusively against
            those eye diseases for which others usually employ the scalpel, i.e., cataract, scabies,
            cold, water, opacity, growth, stye, excess or loss of flesh in the interior angle of the
            eye; you should also praise the physician whom you see promptly extract from the eye a
            collection of matter, by lowering the layer called "the grape-like" back to its place
            after it has become very swollen, until it is healed again, or perform any other
            ophthalmological operation which is similar to the above, without having recourse to the
            iron." So much for Galen's remarks.</p>
          <p>I have indeed witnessed many such cases in my father's treatments and also many eye
            diseases which were considered hopeless but which he succeeded in curing. This was
            celebrated in a poem written by one of his grateful patients, namely Shams al-Ārab,
            i.e., Abū Muḥammad Abd al-Aziz b. al-Nafīs b. Hibat Allāh b. Wahbān al-Silamī, the
            Baghdadian:</p>
          <quote><p><l>Sadīd al-Dīn has such a power in medicine, that he always saves the eyes from
                mote; </l><l> How often has he banished darkness and guarded the sight from all
                harm;</l><l> An oculist cannot treat mankind unless he is as skillful as this;
                </l><l> O savior of our generation! How many are those to whom you have given sight
                after being blind; <pb n="914" ed="kopf"/>
              </l><l> Your science is the cure to every malady, your words the balm of every
                spirit;</l><l> My gratitude is so great, I wish I could express the least of my
                thanks, O beloved!</l></p></quote>
          <p>My father remained in service in the fort of Damascus and frequented the al-Nurī
            Hospital until he died, may he be blessed, during the night of Thursday, the 22nd of
            Rabīʿ II, 649/1251. He was buried outside the Gate of Paradise, on the way to Mount
            Qāsiyūn. He died during the reign of al-Malik al-Nāsir Yūsuf b. Muḥammad, the ruler of
            Damascus. As for my uncle, he was staying with al-Malik al-Amjad in Baʿlbek when
            al-Malik al-Muʿazam came there to help him fight his adversaries. When they met
            together, my uncle would keep them company. Now during those days, there was nobody who
            <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.250"/>knew music and the art of the lute better than him, neither was there anyone with a
            sweeter voice, so that he touched the souls of his listeners in the same fashion as Abū
            Nasr al-Fārābī, according to what was said. Al-Malik al-Muʿazam was greatly impressed
            by him and engaged him in his service, which post he took up on the 1st of Jumiādā I,
            610/1213, receiving a fine salary and expenses.</p>
          <p>Al-Malik al-Muʿazzam showered on my uncle constant favors and presents; he hardly left
            him and relied on him for anything medical. The same can be said for al-Malik al-Kāmil
            Muḥammad and al-Malik al-Ashraf, who both had absolute confidence in him. Whenever one
            of them came to visit his brother al -Malik al-Muʿazam, my uncle would keep them
            constant company and obtain many presents from both rulers. I know of one occasion, when
            al-Malik al-Kāmil came to visit his brother al-Malik al-Muʿazam; they were sitting in
            audience in the company of my uncle; that same night, al-Malik al-Kāmil gave my uncle a
            splendid robe of honor and five hundred Egyptian dinars. <pb n="915" ed="kopf"/>
          </p>
          <p>When al-Malik al-Muʿazam was in Damascus, he appointed my uncle military scribe,
            insisting on his acceptance of the post. My uncle could do nothing but obey this order,
            sat on the Divan and received the privates and officers. After a while in his
            secretarial post, he realized that all his time was spent in correspondence and
            calculations, with no leisure left for himself to devote to intellectual and other
            pursuits. He thus asked the Sultan to be released, using the mediation of several of his
            intimates, until he was finally granted his request.</p>
          <p>In the year 611/1214 al-Malik al-Muʿazam made the pilgrimage [to Mecca] and my uncle
            went with him. He stayed in his service until the expedition of ʿAmta, in the middle of
            Shaban, 614/1217. The Franks having advanced, the great Sultan al-Malik al-ʿĀdil and his
            son al-Malik al-Muʿazam fell into disagreement as to the route which should be
            followed. My uncle joined the company of al-Malik al-ʿĀdil, who went in the direction of
            Damascus, while al-Malik al-Muʿazam turned toward Nablus. Later, my uncle left Damascus
            In the company of al-Malik al-Nāsir Dā'ūd b. al-Malik al-Muʿazam, but arriving at
            ʿIglun, he [al-Malik al-Muʿazam] ordered his son to come back, and they all returned to
            Damascus. My uncle then fell ill; his affliction continued for the rest of the year, and
            he found that traveling was injurious to him; in fact, by nature he was inclined to
            solitude and the peaceful study of books.</p>
          <p>On the 5th of Muharram, 615/1218 he was summoned by al-Malik al-ʿĀdil Abū Bakr b.
            Ayyūb, who had heard of his achievements and perfect conduct. He assigned him the post
            of chief physician in the two hospitals of Damascus built by al-Malik al-ʿĀdil Nūr
            al-Dīn Mahmud b. Zenkī. From then on, he used to frequent these two hospitals and the
            fort, enjoying a salary and expenses. He was also paid as the personal physician of Sitt
            al-Sā'am, the sister of al-Malik al-ʿAdil, whom he would attend at her palace. <pb
              n="916" ed="kopf"/>
          </p>
          <p>Having settled in Damascus, he established a public school where he could teach
            medicine. He had many disciples, all of them later to be distinguished members of the
            profession. At that time he used to meet with ʿAlam al-Dīn Qaisar b. Abū al-Qāsim b.
            ʿAbd al-Gānī, who was unique in his generation for his knowledge of the mathematical
            sciences. My uncle studied astronomy under him and became an expert in no time. One day,
            when ʿAlam al-Dīn was at my uncle's house teaching him some astronomical figures, he
            said to him in my presence: "O, Rashīd al-Dīn, by Allāh, what you have learnt in about
            one month would take others five years of effort to master."</p>
          <p>While in Damascus, my uncle also used to frequent the illustrious and learned Imām, the
            Shaykh of shaykhs, Sadr al-Din b. Hamawaihi. This person initiated him to Sufism on the
            20th of Ramadān, 615/1218. The following is the text of the inscription attached to his
            sufi garment, in which he was clad on that day: "In the name of Allāh the Merciful and
            Compassionate; the illustrious Mollah, noble and learned Imām, Shaykh of shaykhs, Sadr
            al-Dīn, the living proof of Islam and standard of monotheism, Abū al-Ḥasan Muḥammad, the
            son of the illustrious Imam and noble scholar, Shaykh of shaykhs Imad al-Dīn Abū Hafs
            ʿUmar b. Abū al-Ḥasan b. Muḥammad b. Hamawaih, may God maintain his support forever,
            herewith endows kindly <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.251"/> his devotee ʿAlī b. Khalīfa b. Yūnus from the tribe of Chazrag the
            Damascene, may Allāh make him succeed in his devotions, with the Sufi garment."</p>
          <p>While dressing him in it, the shaykh told my uncle that he had received that robe from
            his above-mentioned father, may he be blessed, and that his father had gotten it from
            his father, the shaykh of Islam Muʿīn al-Dīn Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad b. Hamawaih, may
            Allāh bless him. He was given it by the prophet Elijah, may he rest in peace, who in
            turn received it from the Apostle of God himself, may Allāh bless him and give him
            peace. The shaykh added that his grandfather was connected to the Prophet also by
            shaykh of his generation <pb n="917" ed="kopf"/> Abū al-Qāsim al-Karakānī, the master
            and Imām Abū ʿUthmān al-Maġribi; the shaykh of the community ʿAbd ʿAmru al-Zajājī; the
            another chain of celebrated sufīs, that is: Shaykh Abū ʿAlī al-Farandi al-Tūsī, the
            chief ofthe congregation al-Jūnaīd b. Muḥammad; his maternal uncle Sarī al-Saqatī;
            Maʿrūf al-Karhī. ʿAlī b. Mūsā al-Rida, may he be blessed (this Maʿrūf accompanied ʿAlī b.
            Mūsā, served him and was instructed by him); Mūsā b. Jaʿfar al-Kāzim; Jaʿfar b. Muḥammad
            al-Sadīq; Muḥammad b. ʿAlī al-Bāqir; ʿAlī b. al-Husain Zain al-ʿĀbidīn; al-Husain b.
            ʿAlī; ʿAlī al-Bāqir; ʿAlī b. al-Ḥusayn Zain al-ʿĀbidīn; al-Ḥusayn b. ʿAlī(W) al-Bāqir:
            ʿAlī Talib, may he be blessed; ʿAlī, may Allāh honor his countenance, was directly
            connected with the master of the apostles and Imām of the pious believers, our prophet
            Muḥammad, may the best prayers and and wishes rest upon him. According to yet another
            version, the tradition goes from Maʿrūf through Da'ūd al-Tā'i, Habīb al-ʿAgamī, Hasan
            al-Basrī the leader of the followers, to ʿAlī, may he be blessed, and then to the
            Prophet, may Allāh bless him and give him peace.</p>
          <p>The endowment of my uncle with such a robe brought upon him all of God's incumbent
            blessings, as it did upon all those who had been honored by it. This event took place on
            the 20th of Ramadān, 615/ 1218 in Damascus the well-protected. The robe was thrown on
            the aforesaid, may Allāh lead him to success, accompanied by the above-quoted lines,
            written by the hand of the Mollah Sadr al-Dīn, the Shaykh of shaykhs, Ibn Hamawaih Abū
            al-Ḥasan b. ʿUmar b. Abū al-Ḥasan b. Muḥammad, who wrote them during the month of
            Ramadān, 615/ 1218, praising God and praying for his apostle, asking pardon for his
            sins.</p>
          <p>In the year 616/1219 my uncle received a message from al-Malik al-Sālih ʿIsmāʿīl b.
            al-Malik al-ʿĀdil, in his own handwriting, asking him to come to the town of Bosrā and
            treat his mother and other sick persons who were staying with him; afterward he could
            return to Damascus. Indeed a great epidemic was raging in Bosrā <pb n="918" ed="kopf"/>
            at the time, My uncle went to Bosrā, cured the sultan's mother in the shortest time
            possible and was presented with gold and honorary robes. While in Bosrā, he was stricken
            with an acute fever, which grew steadily worse, even after his return to Damascus. He
            was treated there by the best physicians, but his term had come. He died, may Allāh have
            mercy upon him, in the second hour of Monday, the 17th of Shaban, 616/1219, at the age
            of 38. He was buried near his father and brother outside the Gate of Paradise.</p>
          <p>The following are some of his aphorisms, as I heard them from him, may his soul rest in
            peace:</p>
          <p>1. "The commandment of the early morning is to face the new day, in which you are
            capable of doing all manner of things, with the resolution to perform the finest deeds,
            such as would lead you to the highest of ranks; you have to do good, for it will bring
            you closer to God and endear you to mem, beware of evil, for it will estrange you from
            God and make people hate you. Do what would give you credit in the soul-reckoning at the
            end of the day; do not let the evil part of your nature overpower the good that is in
            you. A noble man is not he who retains his natural purity by the absence of obstacles,
            but rather he who retains it in spite of obstacles; the best way to shun these obstacles
            is to retreat into seclusion from the world.</p>
          <p>Follow the prophets' testaments and emulate the deeds of the wise.</p>
          <p>Speak the truth, for a lie belittles a man in his own eyes even more than in the eyes
            of others.</p>
          <p>Be patient and you will be thanked and honored, for hatred brings anguish and leads to
            enmity <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.252"/>and evil, just as envy does.</p>
          <p>Avoid evil men and you will spare yourself their harm;</p>
          <p>Avoid the rulers of this world and you will spare yourself the company of evil men, <pb
              n="919" ed="kopf"/>
          </p>
          <p>Accept from this world only what is essential for your physical needs.</p>

          <p>Know that this your day is a piece of your life gone forever, so spend it on something
            which might benefit you later; after having satisfied the needs of your body, dedicate
            the rest of your day to the perfection of your soul. Do unto people as you would like
            them to do unto you. Beware of anger and of haste to take revenge on an angry man or to
            be affected by him; for in most cases it would lead to repentence; you should be
            patient, for patience is the mainstay of all wisdom."</p>
          <p>2. "The commandment of the early night is to face this coming night in which you have
            no pressing physical duty to fulfill, with the resolution to work on the improvement of
            your soul, by studying the sciences, by meditating on the knowledge of truth; as long as
            you can stay awake, do this; when you feel yourself falling asleep, fix your soul to the
            subject of your concern, so that your dreams may also be of the same nature. Do what
            would give you credit in the soul-reckoning of the following morning.</p>

          <p>Endeavor to be a better person tomorrow than you were yesterday.</p>
          <p>Beware of being entrained by your nature to ponder on what you have seen during the day
            of the conditions of worldly people, for by this you will waste your time, open for
            yourself the gates of deception, trickery and guile in order to achieve worldly matters,
            corrupt your soul and spoil your position, drawing away from truths and acquiring those
            shameful characteristics which are so difficult to cast off. Know that these [worldly
            matters] are transient and useless accidents, that the needs of man are indeed very
            few.</p>

          <p>Think only of the things which might be useful to you and prepare yourself to meet
            Allāh, for the knowledge of when you will die is <pb n="920" ed="kopf"/> concealed from
            you, although your wish to stay alive another day is stronger than your fear to die this
            same night; so you should be reconciled to persevere in those things which might benefit
            you after your departure. Dixi."</p>
          <p>3. "Respect the shaykhs, even though they may not answer your questions, for their
            silence might be broken later; perhaps it was due to weariness, or to the fact that it
            was none of your business, or to their knowledge of your incapability of understanding
            the answer; keep in mind that the benefit you might derive from them is incomparably
            greater than any particular answer."</p>
          <p>4. "First of all, study the general sayings of the famous; after having mastered these,
            you can go on to study the particular sayings of each person as contained in their
            book."</p>

          <p>5. Consider the sayings of each person objectively, without love or hatred; then weigh
            them according to the rules and examine them by experiment, if possible; only then can
            you accept the truth in them. In case this is too difficult for you, enlist someone's
            aid, for each mind has a special capacity for interpreting certain meanings."</p>
          <p>6. "If you are pushed forth by virtuous people, go forth, for if you do not, you will
            lag behind."</p>
          <p>7. "Always seek the truth, for in this way you will acquire knowledge for yourself and
            love from other men."</p>
          <p>8. "Take care that your individual deeds correspond to the general rule you keep in
            your mind; this way your knowledge will be sound, your experience beneficial, the
            development of your intellect certain, and the advantages you reap from contact with
            people enhanced."</p>
          <p>9. "Study first the sayings of those whose intention was to instruct: having mastered,
            that science, consolidate it by studying the sayings of those who love truth and refute
            error; when your <pb n="921" ed="kopf"/> knowledge becomes so well-based and certain
            that it cannot be destroyed by doubt, it will not hurt you if, from time to time, you
            leaf through the books of skeptics and controversialists; for their purpose is to show
            off their power in their claims, no matter whether they really know them or not, whether
            their claims are true or false.'</p>
          <p>10. "When practicing as a physician, fear Allāh and try to act according to what you
            know for sure; when you cannot, endeavor to come as close to this as possible."</p>
          <p>11. "Having reached the rank of master, do not ever turn away the worthy, namely an
            intelligent, pure and good, naturally wise person, but do turn away all others."</p>
          <p>12. "When you know of many remedies to a single disease, choose the best one for every
            stage of it."</p>
          <p>13. "Maladies have their own life-spans, and remedies need the help of Fate; medicine
            is largely mere conjecture <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.253"/>
            and suppositions, which sometimes contain a grain of truth;
            success here is the reward of good measure and experimentation, not of sophistry and
            excess; the purpose of medicine is the preservation of health when it is good and its
            recovery when it has been lost; these two [achievements] are the mark of a sound mind
            and refined thinking, and by them you can distinguish between the master and the
            ignorant, the praiseworthy scholar and the idler, the one who acts according to good
            measure and experiment and the one seeking only wealth and high rank."</p>
          <p>14. "Knowledge is long and difficult to gain; he who tries desperately to snatch it
            quickly and succinctly, ignoring the essential factors of long life, subtle thought,
            human cooperation and perfection, will only confound his thoughts and breed havoc in his
            mind."</p>
          <p>15. "Observe the activity of nature when unhindered by any obstacles and follow her
            example in your own deeds." <pb n="922" ed="kopf"/>
          </p>
          <p>16. "How wonderful patience is, were it not paid for by time!"</p>
          <p>17. "Whenever I await something, its fulfillment seems too far off and its value too
            paltry."</p>
          <p>18. "You look forward to good, but think of it little."</p>
          <p>19. "Evil is in our nature and is capable of ignoring the fear of the other world, as
            well as the fear of the sword."</p>
          <p>20. "Good is perfected only by destruction."</p>
          <p>21. "Those who pursue their own interests are four times as many as those who feel for
            God's other creatures."</p>
          <p>22. "If you want to be mistreated by people, guard yourself from them; if you do not
            want to be mistreated by people, mistreat them yourself; as to the middle road — do not
            wish it."</p>
          <p>23. "Departure is the best time of life."</p>
          <p>24. "Seclusion is the best way of life."</p>

          <p>25. "Solitude is outcome of wisdom."</p>
          <p>26. "Evil men are always looking for somebody with whom they can pass their days in
            idle talk, amusement and vanity; when they are left alone, they are constantly grieved
            because of the evil rooted in their souls. The opposite is true of good folk, for they
            are satisfied with themselves."</p>
          <p>27. "The root of every trouble is the love of this world."</p>
          <p>28. "How long do people neglect their real interests because of their involvement in
            the affairs of this world, and then they are gone!"</p>
          <p>29. "I wonder how a man, not knowing the time of his death and being open to either
            happiness or misfortune at any given moment, can put his confidence in this world and
            ignore his most important concern."</p>
          <p>30. "How many people delight in their hopes without even starting to fulfill them!"</p>
          <p>31. "Hopes are the dreams of the wakeful." <pb n="923" ed="kopf"/>
          </p>
          <p>32. "There are too many things to be done at any one moment, and therefore you should
            choose the most important of them.</p>
          <p>33. "What would you think of him, who neglects his tasks at their appropriate time,
            hoping for other occasions to arise and deferring them constantly, until he dies still
            hoping?"</p>
          <p>34. "As long as you are in a position to take care of your body and exercise your soul,
            keeping them both in good order without languor or waste — you should not change your
            position; for you have a good motive and should stick to it as far as you can. Many a
            man who has changed his position for another that seemed better to him left it later,
            finding it worse."</p>
          <p>35. "Do not envy the happy man, for the opposite of happy is miserable."</p>
          <p>36. "If each of two enemies were to attain his purpose by the other, they would both be
            happy and victorious; therefore we were ordered, when seeking to achieve important
            goals, to put together all our individual wills and form one great cause, which will be
            aided by heavenly succor."</p>
          <p>37. "Beware of regarding people as your brothers; beware of the arrows of [their] will,
            for they smite."</p>
          <p>38. "Beware of injuring the religious doctors, for they are men of God."</p>
          <p>39. "When a man of true knowledge is mistreated, God will swiftly come to his aid,
            uncover his oppressor and destroy him."</p>
          <p>40. "God has his beloved ones, whom he guards with his eye that is always watchful;
            these are the savants."</p>
          <p>41. "The savants are the truly happy."</p>
          <p>42. According to the term as used by the mob, the happy people in this world are those
            who never hand out favors; but these are really the evil ones." <pb n="924" ed="kopf"/>
          </p>
          <p>43. "A man might hit upon a word of wisdom on one occasion and on another seek it in
            himself, but without success."</p>
          <p>44. "Whoever associates with fools in spite of their ignorance and is dragged into
            their doings by his love of this world should blame only himself when he is infected
            with their evil."</p>
          <p>45. "First fix your scales, then weigh."</p>
          <p>46. "When you come to possess a material mind, then you are a true man, in absolute
            terms." <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.254"/></p>
          <p>47. "Trust your knowledge when no objection can impair it."</p>
          <p>48. "How wonderful is unanimous opinion!"</p>
          <p>49. "How wonderful is analogous opinion!"</p>
          <p>50. "A reasonable action is not done according to the absolute good, but rather
            according to its author's intentions."</p>
          <p>51. "How wonderful is the opinion which arises between a truth-speaking adviser and an
            honest and clever man, who asks for his advice! "</p>


          <p>52. "Put your confidence only in a man who believes firmly in the subject of his hopes
            and fears and is certain of the exclusive truth of his belief. As for him who unsure of
            his belief or does not believe in anything at all, do not place your confidence in him,
            nor take him as your companion. When the believer who is certain of his truth is not a
            member of your community, beware of him also, for he might consider you impious with
            regard to his belief, regard you as an enemy and treat you with hostility."</p>
          <p>53. "Trust your religion more then its representatives."</p>
          <p>54. "The reason for practicing the precepts of religion is to gain the certainty of
            true belief; the practice of the precepts of religion is in itself a proof of the
            certainty of true belief; he who practices these precepts may indeed do so just by
            imitation of others, without knowing anything else, but he could also do so out of real
            devotion; now, the signs showing that his acts are indeed the consequence of <pb n="925"
              ed="kopf"/> the certainty of true belief are the traces of divine inspiration in his
            faith, the piety of his everyday conduct and his relationships with the other creatures
            of God, which spring entirely from his own soul."</p>
          <p>55. "Freedom is the best of life."</p>
          <p>56. "Humility is the gate to freedom."</p>
          <p>57. "Whoever is able to live contentedly in accordance with his needs and instead sells
            his soul to another, spurred by the desire for the luxuries of life, is the stupidest of
            fools."</p>

          <p>58. "How few are the needs of man, were he impartial toward himself!</p>
          <p>59. "Avoid the company of worldly-minded men, for in case you find them, they will
            enslave you, and in case you lose them, you will be sorry."</p>
          <p>60. "When annoyed, prefer the company of someone who will not divert you too much from
            your mood."</p>
          <p>61. "The loss of a friend is a portent of a journey."</p>
          <p>62. "When a wise man is hurt by you or imagines himself to have been hurt by you, you
            will benefit both by his apology, in case you have done nothing and are indeed innocent,
            and by his forgiveness, in case you have really hurt him. On the other hand, when you
            notice that a rancorous man imagines himself to have been hurt by you, robbed of his
            benefit or contradicted, beware of him, for he will constantly think of ways to injure
            you."</p>
          <p>63. "Friends are like one soul in different bodies."</p>
          <p>64. "A physician treats the human body not as being a human body categorically
            speaking, but as being related to his own; this relationship is one of the noblest, so
            that the one concerned with it should also be a noble man."</p>
          <p>65. "Money is a magnet for the souls of fools and knowledge is a magnet for the souls
            of the wise." <pb n="926" ed="kopf"/>
          </p>
          <p>66. "I have seen fools admiring the wealthy, although they know for sure that they will
            not give them any part of their wealth, except as the price for goods or payment for
            labor, the same as they get from the poor."</p>
          <p>67. "The best savant is he whose knowledge is proportionate to his mind."</p>
          <p>68. "If it is possible to live apart from people with the minimum of needs, this is the
            best situation."</p>
          <p>69. "If you are the kind of person who is stingy with money and spends it only on the
            most important things, you should better do just this with regard to your time."</p>
          <p>70. "Wisdom is in reliance upon God the Omnipotent."</p>
          <p>71. "A man comes to know his own defects by learning the defects of others."</p>
          <p>72. "Having attached fine virtues to your soul, you are paying it the utmost honor; for
            if you are not susceptible to anger, for example while all other people are susceptible
            to it, you become the finest man in this respect."</p>
          <p>73. "The more perfect a thing is, the more pleasure it gives; the more defective a
            thing is, the more pain it causes.".</p>
          <p>74. "Read much of the biographies of sages and emulate them as far as you can in your
            generation."</p>
          <p>75. "Make your soul stronger than your body."</p>
          <p>76. "Improve the quality of your food and reduce its quantity."</p>
          <p>77. "Give your body enough food to maintain its strength; beware of surpassing it, but
            increase the nourishment of your soul."  </p>
          <p>78. "The nourishment of the soul is gradual study; you should start with small and easy
            <pb ed="mueller-1884" n="2.255"/>portions and proceed slowly, until the soul grows stronger and used to difficulties;
            when it becomes thus skilled, it will crave for more and everything will be easy for
            it." <pb n="927" ed="kopf"/>
          </p>
          <p>79. "A strong stomach digests any kind of food which enters it and a virtuous soul
            accepts any kind of knowledge which reaches it."</p>
          <p>80. "As long as you cannot bear solitude you are compelled to live with people."</p>
          <p>81. "Associate people in what gives them pleasure, but do not forsake the nearness of
            God."</p>
          <p>82. "A man wrote to his shaykh complaining of difficulties in his affairs. His shaykh
            wrote back saying; "You will never be saved from what you hate if you do not give up
            many a thing you love, and you will not reach the object of your love unless you learn
            to bear many a thing you hate. Dixi."</p>
          <p>83. "Be thankful both to him who does good and to him who does no evil; forgive people
            their deeds and do not censure them; for every creature has its own particular
            nature."</p>
          <p>84. "You should approve of the same things in others as you do in yourself and
            disapprove of the same things in them as you do in yourself."</p>
          <p>85. "Do not overlook any of your deeds of devotion to God the Omnipotent."</p>
          <p>86. "Obey God truly and people will obey you."</p>
          <p>87. "There is nothing more valuable than sincere intention."</p>
          <p>88. "Take from everything that which may guide you toward the goal at which it is
            aimed."</p>
          <p>89. "Do not trust anything you get by chance."</p>
          <p>90. "Submit yourself to men, and especially to the ulemas and shaykhs [religious
            doctors and spiritual masters], and do not despise anybody; for the scholar frequently
            conceals his knowledge in order to select his spiritual heir, just as the farmer selects
            his land."</p>
          <p>91. "In every science, study the sayings of its first masters." <pb n="928" ed="kopf"/>
          </p>

          <p>92. "Study intensively the divine books of revelation, for they contain all
            wisdom."</p>
          <p>93. "Associate much with the shaykhs, for you will always benefit either from their
            knowledge or from their way of life."</p>
          <p>94. "If you observe the virtuous both in movement and at rest, you will find there much
            wisdom."</p>
          <p>95. "I have observed that the most important thing for most people is that which brings
            them money."</p>
          <p>96. "How often do people hear prophetic and wise commandments, but use only those which
            bring them monetary profit."</p>
          <p>97. "How strong is man's inclination to bodily pleasures!"</p>
          <p>98. "At any given moment do not neglect to think of the future."</p>
          <p>99. "Whoever does, not think of the future comes face to face with it unprepared."</p>
          <p>100. "Humility is at the root of everything good and noble."</p>
          <p>101. "A man can attain everything he desires through humility."</p>
          <p>102. "The humble is aided in the fulfillment of his goals."</p>
          <p>103. "Aim at the extreme degree of human perfection, for if you are unable to attain
            it, you will attain the degree which is in your power. If you aim only at the degree of
            perfection next to yours, hoping to proceed from it to the following, you will most
            probably end by taking it easy and being satisfied with less than you deserve."</p>
          <p>104. "Beware of neglecting any of the physical labors of devotion, for they are the
            most pleasant auxiliary on the way to spiritual devotion."</p>
          <p>105. "Oneness is sufficient honor, for God the Omnipotent is one."</p>
          <p>106. "The purer oneness is, the nobler it is, for absolutely no plurality of facets can
            mix with the oneness of God the Omnipotent."</p>
          <p>107. "Have recourse to God the Omnipotent, rely on him and put your trust in him alone,
            and he will guard you, supply you with all your needs and will not disappoint any of
            your hopes." <pb n="929" ed="kopf"/>
          </p>
          <p>108. "Consider yourself a part of your community, and its members — your brothers: do
            not rely on governments, for the communities are the more enduring of the two."</p>
          <p>109. "Accustom your soul to the good, both in thought and in deed, and you will be
            rewarded with good both by God the Omnipotent and by men, both here and now and in the
            hereafter."</p>
          <p>110. "Do not desire solitude as long as you still have the least desire."</p>
          <p>111. "If the weak were to stop at the end of his possibilities, he would be spared many
            a danger."</p>
          <p>112. "I wish I knew how to excuse myself for the things I know and have not done; I
            hope Allāh the Omnipotent will forgive me."</p>
          <p>[There follow samples of his poetry, as told to the author.]</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
