<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://textalign.net/release/TAN-2018/schemas/TAN-TEI.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://textalign.net/release/TAN-2018/schemas/TAN-TEI.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" id="tag:usaybia.net,2019:iu.example.kopf.en"
   xmlns:tan="tag:textalign.net,2015:ns" TAN-version="2018">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <tan:head>
      <tan:name>History of the Physicians, Ibn Abī Uṣaybiʿa, English translation based on L.
         Kopf</tan:name>
      <tan:license>
         <tan:IRI>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</tan:IRI>
         <tan:name>public domain</tan:name>
         <tan:desc>To the extent possible under law, the person who associated CC0 with this work
            has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this work.</tan:desc>
      </tan:license>
      <tan:licensor who="gibson"/>
      <tan:source>
         <tan:IRI>http://www.tertullian.org/fathers/ibn_abi_usaibia_00_eintro.htm</tan:IRI>
         <tan:name>Ibn Abī Uṣaybiʿa, History of Physicians, translated by L. Kopf with partial
            annotations by M. Plessner (Jerusalem, Israel: Institute of Asian and African Studies, The Hebrew
            University, 1971).</tan:name>
      </tan:source>
      <tan:definitions>
         <tan:work>
            <tan:IRI>http://viaf.org/viaf/215291388</tan:IRI>
            <tan:name>History of the Physicians</tan:name>
         </tan:work>
         <tan:div-type xml:id="pt" which="part"/>
         <tan:div-type xml:id="ch">
            <tan:IRI>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Chapter_(books)</tan:IRI>
            <tan:name>chapter</tan:name>
         </tan:div-type>
         <tan:div-type xml:id="bio">
            <tan:IRI>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q19389637</tan:IRI>
            <tan:name>biographical article</tan:name>
         </tan:div-type>
         <tan:div-type xml:id="par">
            <tan:IRI>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Paragraph</tan:IRI>
            <tan:name xml:lang="eng">paragraph</tan:name>
         </tan:div-type>
         <tan:person xml:id="gibson">
            <tan:IRI>http://viaf.org/viaf/59147905242279092527</tan:IRI>
            <tan:IRI>tag:usaybia.net,2019:self</tan:IRI>
            <tan:name xml:lang="en">Nathan P. Gibson</tan:name>
         </tan:person>
         <tan:role xml:id="editor">
            <tan:IRI>http://schema.org/editor</tan:IRI>
            <tan:name xml:lang="eng">Editor</tan:name>
         </tan:role>
      </tan:definitions>
      <tan:resp roles="editor" who="gibson"/>
      <tan:change when="2019-05-02" who="gibson">Started new file.</tan:change>
   </tan:head>
   <text>
      <body xml:lang="en" in-progress="true">
         <div n="3" type="pt">
            <div n="15" type="ch">
               <div n="47" type="bio">
                  <div n="12" type="par"><anchor xml:id="kopf1" corresp="iu-sample-mueller-ar-tan.xml#mueller1"/>
                     <p>An example of <persName>Amīn al-Dawlah</persName>'s own poetry was included in his letter to Burhān al-Dīn,
                     the Vizier of the Emir ʿIzz al-Dīn al-Muʿazzamī, in which he sent him his condolences on
                     the death of his father, Sharf al-Dīn ʿUmar. . . .</p></div>
                  <div n="13" type="par"><anchor xml:id="kopf2" corresp="iu-sample-mueller-ar-tan.xml#mueller2"/><p> . . . <pb n="901" ed="kopf"/></p></div>
                  <div n="14" type="par"><anchor xml:id="kopf3" corresp="iu-sample-mueller-ar-tan.xml#mueller3"/><p>The master Amīn al-Dawlah wrote "The Clear Path to Medicine," one of the best books
                        written on the science of medicine. He gathered into its five parts all of medicine's
                        universal and particular laws.</p></div>
                  <div n="15" type="par"><anchor xml:id="kopf4" corresp="iu-sample-mueller-ar-tan.xml#mueller4"/><p>The first book deals with matters of nature, the three states of the body, the
                     different kinds of disease; the symptoms of the moderate, natural and healthy humors of
                     the main organs and the surrounding areas; also other matters, highly valuable and
                     worthy of being mentioned in this context; then follows a discussion on the pulse,
                     urine, excrement, delirum.</p></div>
                  <div n="16" type="par"><anchor xml:id="kopf5" corresp="iu-sample-mueller-ar-tan.xml#mueller5"/><p>The second book deals with simple drugs and their power.</p></div>
                  <div n="17" type="par"><anchor xml:id="kopf6" corresp="iu-sample-mueller-ar-tan.xml#mueller6"/><p>The third book discusses the compound drugs and their uses.</p></div>
                  <div n="18" type="par"><anchor xml:id="kopf7" corresp="iu-sample-mueller-ar-tan.xml#mueller7"/><p>The fourth book describes the regimen of the healthy and the treatment of manifest
                     diseases, their causes and symptoms and what can be done by surgical means concerning
                     the diseased organs and other parts of the body. Here he also treats the subject of
                     proper clothing and behavior during the samum [very hot and dry weather].</p></div>
                  <div n="19" type="par"><anchor xml:id="kopf8" corresp="iu-sample-mueller-ar-tan.xml#mueller8"/><p>The fifth book is concerned with internal diseases, their causes, symptoms and
                     treatment, and also the surgery that can be employed in these cases.</p></div>
               </div>               
               <div n="48" type="bio">
                  <head><persName ref="https://usaybia.net/person/1">Muhadhdhab al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Raḥīm b. ʿAlī</persName></head>
                  <div n="1" type="par"><anchor xml:id="kopf9" corresp="iu-sample-mueller-ar-tan.xml#mueller9"/><p> was our shaikh, the chief of ministers, the learned and worthy 
                     <persName ref="https://usaybia.net/person/1">Muhadhdhab al-Dīn ʿAbd
                     al-Raḥīm b. ʿAlī b. Hāmid, known as al-Dikhwār</persName>. He was — may Allāh have mercy upon him —
                     unique among his generation, peerless in his time, the most learned scholar of his
                     epoch, the apogee of medical skill and knowledge, both general and specialized. No one
                     matched him in diligence or learning. He tired himself out with work, straining his mind
                     in order to gain knowledge, until he surpassed all contemporary physicians and won more
                     remuneration and honor from kings than any doctor had ever before. <rs  xml:id="rs-1">He was born in
                     <placeName>Damascus</placeName> and brought up there by his father, <persName>ʿAlī b. Hamid</persName>, a famous oculist, whose
                        other <pb n="902" ed="kopf"/> son, <persName ref="https://usaybia.net/person/2">Hamid b. ʿAlī</persName>, took up the same profession.</rs> At first,
                     Muhadhadhab al-Dīn was also an oculist, but at the same time he worked as a copyist. His
                     calligraphy was outstanding. He transcribed many books, of which I have seen a hundred
                     or more, dealing with medicine and other sciences. He worked for the Shaikh Tāj al-Dīn
                     al-Kindī Abū al-Yamān, but constantly endeavored to increase his knowledge by reading
                     and memorizing — a habit he kept up until old age.</p>
                     <div type="factoid" uri="https://usaybia.net/factoid/1-1" resp="#ngibson">
                        <listPerson>
                           <person>
                              <persName ref="https://usaybia.net/person/2">Hamid b. ʿAlī</persName>
                           </person>
                        </listPerson>
                        <bibl type="primary">
                           <ptr target="#rs-1"/>
                        </bibl>
                     </div>
                     <div type="factoid" uri="https://usaybia.net/factoid/1-2" resp="#ngibson">
                        <listEvent>
                           <event>
                              <desc>
                                 <persName ref="https://usaybia.net/person/1"> Muhadhdhab al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Raḥīm b. ʿAlī </persName> was born
                                 in <placeName ref="https://usaybia.net/place/1">Damascus</placeName>.</desc>
                              <ptr target="http://syriaca.org/keyword/birth"/>
                           </event>
                        </listEvent>
                        <bibl type="primary">
                           <ptr target="#rs-1"/>
                        </bibl>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="par"><anchor xml:id="kopf10" corresp="iu-sample-mueller-ar-tan.xml#mueller10"/><p>At the beginning of his medical career, he was introduced to al-Malkī's teachings by
                     the Shaikh Radī al-Dīn al-Rahbī — may Allāh have mercy upon him — and then became a
                     close associate of Muwaffaq al-Dīn b. al-Mutrān, for whom he worked and from whom he
                     learnt the art of medicine. He continued to seek out his company and study his books
                     until he became expert. Afterwards Fakhr al-Dīn al-Madīnī, who came to Damascus in the
                     year 579/1189, instructed him to part of Ibn Sīnā's ʿQānūn," which Fakhr al-Dīn knew and
                     comprehended thoroughly.</p></div>
                  <div n="3" type="par"><anchor xml:id="kopf11" corresp="iu-sample-mueller-ar-tan.xml#mueller11"/><p>Muhadhdhab al-Dīn worked as a physician to al-Malik al-ʿAdil Abū Bakr b. Ayyūb. This
                     was because at the beginning of his career he was interested in eye diseases and wished
                     to gain practice in their treatment. He worked as an oculist in the Great Hospital
                     established by al-Malik al-ʿĀdil Nūr al-Dīn Mahmūd b. Zankī. Later, when he worked with
                     al-Mutrān and had become noted for his medical skill, Safī al-Dīn b. Shakr, the vizier
                     of al-Malik al-ʿĀdil b. Ayūb, granted him an allowance, by means of which he was able to
                     practice work and at the same time increase his knowledge and proficiency. He was
                     tireless in the service of the vizier, and the latter, knowing Muhadhadhab's
                     professional merits, preferred him to all others. In the month of Shawwal, 604/1207,
                     al-Malik al-ʿĀdil said to Ibn Shakr: "We want another doctor besides Muwaffaq al-Dīn
                     ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz for attending the troops. This work is not congenial to <pb n="903"
                        ed="kopf"/> ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz, so do as he requests." Said b. Shakr: "We have here an
                     excellent physician, named Muhadhdhab al-Dikhwār, who is fit for our master's service."
                     Then he ordered him to comply. When Muhadhdhab al-Dīn appeared before the vizier, the
                     latter said to him: "I have recommended you to the Sultan, and you are paid a month for
                     your services." But Muhadhdhab al-Dīn said: "My lord: The Doctor Muwaffaq al-Dīn ʿAbd
                     al-ʿAzīz earns about a hundred dinars monthly.</p></div>
                  <div n="4" type="par"><anchor xml:id="kopf12" corresp="iu-sample-mueller-ar-tan.xml#mueller12"/><p>I know my status, and I will not serve without a decent wage. Then he took leave of the
                     vizier and refused the post. But his companions made him regret his refusal, his lost
                     chance to be engaged by the vizier. For his salary at the hospital was very low.</p></div>
                  <div n="5" type="par"><anchor xml:id="kopf13" corresp="iu-sample-mueller-ar-tan.xml#mueller13"/><p>About that time, Muwaffaq ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz was stricken with severe colitis, which grew
                     worse and eventually caused his death. When the news of his passing reached al-Malik
                     al-ʿAdil, the latter said to the vizier: "You once recommended to us a doctor by the
                     name of Muhadhdhab. Appoint him in place of Muwaffad ʿAbd al-ʿAziz. "So Muhadhdhab got
                     all his posts, and he remained in the service of al-Malik al-ʿĀdil from then on. He rose
                     steadily in al-Malik al-ʿĀdil's esteem, and his status was enhanced, until he became his
                     companion, associate and adviser. At the beginning of his service, al-Malik put his
                     knowledge to some unusual tests, and the results strengthened his opinion of him and his
                     reliance upon him.</p></div>
                  <div n="6" type="par"><anchor xml:id="kopf14" corresp="iu-sample-mueller-ar-tan.xml#mueller14"/><p>About that time, al-Malik al-ʿĀdil fell ill. He was attended by the best doctors.
                     Muhadhdhab advised bloodletting but the other physicians present did not agree. He said:
                     "By Allāh! If we let blood from him, he will bleed without our being able to staunch
                     it." But they were still obstinate. Very soon the Sultan began to bleed heavily. When he
                     was well again, he realized that Muhadhdhab outshone all the others. <pb n="904"
                        ed="kopf"/>
                  </p></div>
                  <div n="7" type="par"><anchor xml:id="kopf15" corresp="iu-sample-mueller-ar-tan.xml#mueller15"/><p>Another story has it that one day, when he was standing at the palace gate with some
                     court physicians, a servant came out with a vial containing the urine of one of the
                     concubines and reported that she was in pain. When the doctors had inspected the vial,
                     they ventured a diagnosis. But Muhadhdhab examined it closely and said: "The pain she
                     complains of does not cause this color," suspecting it to be induced by Lawsonia with
                     which she had anointed herself. The servant told him that his finding was correct,
                     marvelled at him and reported the incident to al-Malik al-ʿĀdil; this increased the
                     latter's confidence in Muhadhdhab.</p></div>
                  <div n="8" type="par"><anchor xml:id="kopf16" corresp="iu-sample-mueller-ar-tan.xml#mueller16"/><p>One of the best anecdotes about Shaikh Muhadhdhab al-Dīn, and one that illustrates his
                     savoir-faire and loyalty, is the following which was told my by my father. Once,
                     al-Malik al-ʿĀdil was very angry with the chief judge, Muhyī al-Dīn b. Zakī al-Dīn, of
                     Damascus. He ordered him to be detained in the fortress, demanded from him the sum of
                     10,000 Egyptian dinars and pressed for payment. Muhyī al-Dīn was to remain in prison
                     until the amount was settled. He paid some of the money, but was unable to raise the
                     balance. Al-Malik al-ʿĀdil was inexorable, saying: "He must pay the rest, otherwise I
                     shall deal very harshly with him." The judge was in dire straits. He sold all his
                     possessions — his household effects, and </p></div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
