<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:py="http://codespeak.net/lxml/objectify/pytype" xml:id="arabicLit.textgroup.work.H01" py:pytype="TREE">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Preface</title>
				<title xml:lang="en" level="m" ref="https://usaybia.net/work/1 http://viaf.org/viaf/215291388">The Best Accounts of the Classes of Physicians</title>
				<author xml:lang="en" ref="https://usaybia.net/person/1">Ibn Abī Uṣaybiʿah</author>
				<sponsor ref="https://www.uni-muenchen.de">
					<orgName>Ludwig Maximilian University of Munich</orgName>
					(<orgName xml:lang="de">Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München</orgName>)
				</sponsor>
				<sponsor ref="http://www.naher-osten.uni-muenchen.de">
					<orgName>Institute of Near and Middle Eastern Studies</orgName>
					(<orgName xml:lang="de">Institut für den Nahen und Mittleren Osten</orgName>)
				</sponsor>
				<funder ref="https://www.bmbf.de/">
					<orgName>German Federal Ministry of Education and Research</orgName>
					(<orgName xml:lang="de">Bundesministerium für Bildung und Forschung</orgName>)
				</funder>
				<principal ref="#ngibson">Nathan P. Gibson</principal>
				<editor xml:id="ngibson" role="editor" ref="https://usaybia.net/documentation/editors.xml#ngibson       http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.html#ngibson       https://www.naher-osten.uni-muenchen.de/personen/wiss_ma/gibson/index.html      http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0786-8075                     http://viaf.org/viaf/59147905242279092527">Nathan P. Gibson</editor>
                <editor role="contributor" ref="https://usaybia.net/documentation/editors.xml#vbirkhahn                  https://www.naher-osten.uni-muenchen.de/personen/fachschaft/vanessa_birkhahn/index.html">Vanessa Birkhahn</editor>
                <editor role="contributor" ref="https://usaybia.net/documentation/editors.xml#nloehr                 https://www.naher-osten.uni-muenchen.de/personen/wiss_ma/nadine_loehr/index.html">Nadine Löhr</editor>
                <editor role="contributor" ref="https://usaybia.net/documentation/editors.xml#mtolay                 https://www.naher-osten.uni-muenchen.de/personen/hilfskraefte/tolay/index.html">Malinda Tolay</editor>
                <editor role="contributor" ref="https://usaybia.net/documentation/editors.xml#rschmahl                 https://www.naher-osten.uni-muenchen.de/personen/hilfskraefte/schmahl/index.html">Robin Schmahl</editor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>TEI XML encoding adapted from Emilie Savage-Smith, Simon Swain, and G. J. H. van Gelder, eds., 
                        A Literary History of Medicine: The “Uyūn al-Anbā” Fī Ṭabaqāt al-Aṭibbā’ of Ibn Abī Uṣaybi’ah, 5 vols. (Leiden: Brill, 2020) by</resp>
					<name type="person" ref="#ngibson">Nathan P. Gibson</name>
				</respStmt>				
				<!-- <respStmt>
					<resp>Edited by</resp>
					<name type="person">Insert other names of people who edit this document </name>
				</respStmt> -->
			</titleStmt>
           <publicationStmt>
              <p>
                    <ref target="https://usaybia.net">Usaybia.net</ref>, <date>2020</date>
                </p>
           </publicationStmt>
           <sourceDesc>
               <biblStruct>
                <monogr>
                    <title>Annotated English Translation</title>
                    <idno type="URI">https://dh.brill.com/scholarlyeditions/reader/urn:cts:arabicLit:0668IbnAbiUsaibia.Tabaqatalatibba.lhom-tr-eng1/</idno>
                    <author>Ibn Abī Uṣaybiʿa</author>
                    <editor>Emilie Savage-Smith</editor>
                    <editor>Simon Swain</editor>
                    <editor>Geert Jan van Gelder</editor>
                    <editor role="contributor">Ignacio Sánchez</editor>
                    <editor role="contributor">N. Peter Joosse</editor>
                    <editor role="contributor">Alasdair Watson</editor>
                    <editor role="contributor">Bruce Inksetter</editor>
                    <editor role="contributor">Franak Hilloowala</editor>
                    <textLang mainLang="en">English</textLang>
                    <availability>
                        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
                    </availability>
                    <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Leiden</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Brill</publisher>
                        <date>2020</date>
                    </imprint>
                    <biblScope unit="chapter">preface</biblScope>
                </monogr>
                <monogr>
                    <title level="m">A Literary History of Medicine - The ʿUyūn al-anbāʾ fī ṭabaqāt al-aṭibbāʾ of Ibn Abī Uṣaybiʿah Online</title>
                    <idno type="URI">https://dh.brill.com/scholarlyeditions/library/urn:cts:arabicLit:0668IbnAbiUsaibia/</idno>
                    <author>Ibn Abī Uṣaybiʿa</author>
                    <editor>Emilie Savage-Smith</editor>
                    <editor>Simon Swain</editor>
                    <editor>Geert Jan van Gelder</editor>
                    <editor role="contributor">Ignacio Sánchez</editor>
                    <editor role="contributor">N. Peter Joosse</editor>
                    <editor role="contributor">Alasdair Watson</editor>
                    <editor role="contributor">Bruce Inksetter</editor>
                    <editor role="contributor">Franak Hilloowala</editor>
                    <textLang mainLang="ar">Arabic</textLang>
                    <availability>
                        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
                    </availability>
                    <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Leiden</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Brill</publisher>
                        <date>2020</date>
                    </imprint>
                    <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
                </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
           </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2020-08-28" who="#ngibson">Added header to downloaded text.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:arabicLit:0668IbnAbiUsaibia.Tabaqatalatibba.lhom-tr-eng1" xml:lang="en-Latn">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="p">
                    <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="0">
                        <head>Preface</head>
                        <head>Bruce Inksetter</head>
                        <p>In the name of God, merciful and compassionate. None but He can grant me success.</p>
                        <p>Praised be God, He who has dispersed the world’s peoples and will gather them at the Resurrection, the creator of life and healer of the sick, He who graciously bestows abundant blessings but warns those who disobey Him that painful punishment and retribution await them, He who with consummate art brings creatures into being out of nothingness, who ordains diseases and reveals remedies with the most perfect skill and utmost sagacity. I testify that God is one, speaking in all sincerity, as one who pays what is due, avoiding the sins that come of words lightly spoken and subsequently regretted. And I testify that Muḥammad is His servant and His apostle whom He sent to bring the divine message to all, Arab and non-Arab alike, and who dispelled the gloom of darkness with the shining light of his mission, destroyed the proud and tyrannical with his weapon of the miraculous Qur’an, and extirpated the disease of polytheism with the incontrovertible evidence of his prophethood. May God bless him and grant him peace forever, as long as the lightning flashes and the rain falls, together with all his exalted and noble house, his companions, who strove to follow his example, and his wives, the mothers of the believers, who are free from all blemish. May God favour them all with honour and dignity.</p>
                        <p>Turning to my subject, the art of medicine is among the noblest of professions and the most profitable of occupations. Its excellence is attested in scripture and the provisions of law, to such an extent that knowledge of the human body is deemed to be second in importance only to knowledge of religion.</p>
                        <p>Wise men have said that there are two types of aspiration: to what is good, and to what is pleasant. Now, a man cannot attain either of these unless he is in good health, for what is pleasant is obtained from this world, while what is good leads ultimately to our hope of Paradise; in both cases continuing good health and a robust constitution are essential, and those can be secured only through the art of medicine, for it maintains health and restores it when it has been lost.</p>
                        <p>Inevitably, then, since the art of medicine is such an exceptionally noble profession, and since there is such need for it everywhere and at all times, particularly great attention has always been paid to it, and there has always been the keenest and most intense interest in acquiring an understanding of its rules, both general and particular.</p>
                        <p>Consequently, from the time when the art of medicine first arose down to our own day, there have been many who have practised it and sought to investigate its fundamental principles and learn about it. These have included a number of very great physicians, men of the utmost skill and renown, whose excellence is proverbial and whose outstanding capacity and nobility have been recognized by successive generations, and whose compositions testify to their ability. To my knowledge, however, none of these masters of the art of medicine and no one with a thorough knowledge of that art has ever written a comprehensive book dealing with physicians through the ages and recounting their history in a coherent fashion.</p>
                        <p>I have therefore determined to relate in this volume a number of reports and accounts that are told of the most distinguished of the physicians, both in antiquity and in more recent times, with the information regarding them arranged sequentially in chronological order. I also propose to record some of the remarks attributed to them and stories about them that have come down to us, together with entertaining anecdotes about them and the discussions in which they engaged. Lastly, I shall list the titles of some of their books. I hope by this means to enable the reader to glean some understanding of the learning that Almighty God enabled these men to acquire and the copious natural talent and intelligence that He bestowed upon them. Many of them, though they lived long ago and their days are past, stand in much the same relation to us as a teacher does to his pupil, or a recipient of kindness to his benefactor, owing to the advantages that we derive from their written works and the benefits found in the material they gathered together in their books.</p>
                        <p>I have also included accounts of a number of wise men and philosophers who were interested in the art of medicine and gave attention to it. I have related the main events of their lives, giving anecdotes about them and listing the titles of their works. Each of these accounts appears in its appropriate place, depending on their time period and their eminence.</p>
                        <p>
                            After dealing with the art of medicine, I propose to discuss great scholars in other fields of knowledge at some length, God willing, in another book to be entitled
                            <hi rend="italic">The Outstanding Personalities of All Nations and Reports of Those Endowed with Wisdom</hi>
                            .
                            <note n="1" type="footnote">
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Kitāb Maʿālim al-umam wa-akhbār dhawī l-ḥikam</hi>
                                    .
                                </p>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            For the time being, however, I determined that it would be desirable to compose the present work, which is entitled
                            <hi rend="italic">The Best Accounts of the Classes of Physicians</hi>
                            and is divided into fifteen chapters.
                            <hi rend="italic">It is a contribution to the library of the great, learned and just minister, the paragon of masters, lord of viziers, wisest of wise men, chief of learned men, glorious sun of religion, Amīn al-Dawlah Kamāl al-Dīn Sharaf al-Millah Abu l-Ḥasan ibn Ghazāl ibn Abī Saʿīd, may God prolong his happiness and grant him his wishes in this world and the next</hi>
                            .
                            <note n="2" type="footnote">
                                <p>The italicized passage occurs only in Version 1. Amīn al-Dawlah’s biography will be found in Ch. 15.49 with further information in the Addendum to Ch. 15.49.</p>
                            </note>
                            I pray to Almighty God for assistance and for success, for these are in His hand and are His to grant if He will.
                        </p>
                        <p>The chapters are as follows:</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>Chapter 1:</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Origin and First Appearance of the Art of Medicine</hi>
                            </item>
                            <label>Chapter 2:</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Physicians Who Perceived the Rudiments of the Art of Medicine and Initiated the Practice of That Art</hi>
                            </item>
                            <label>Chapter 3:</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Greek Physicians Descended from Asclepius</hi>
                            </item>
                            <label>Chapter 4:</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Greek Physicians to Whom Hippocrates Transmitted the Art of Medicine</hi>
                            </item>
                            <label>Chapter 5:</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Physicians from or after the Time of Galen</hi>
                            </item>
                            <label>Chapter 6:</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Alexandrian Physicians and Their Christian and Other Contemporaries</hi>
                            </item>
                            <label>Chapter 7:</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Arab and Other Physicians of the Earliest Islamic Period</hi>
                            </item>
                            <label>Chapter 8:</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Syriac Physicians of the Early Abbasid Period</hi>
                            </item>
                            <label>Chapter 9:</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Physicians Who Translated Works on Medicine and Other Subjects from Greek into Arabic, and their Patrons</hi>
                            </item>
                            <label>Chapter 10:</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Iraqi Physicians and the Physicians of al-Jazīrah and Diyār Bakr</hi>
                            </item>
                            <label>Chapter 11:</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Physicians in the Lands of the Persians</hi>
                                (
                                <hi rend="italic">Bilād al-ʿajam</hi>
                                )
                            </item>
                            <label>Chapter 12:</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Physicians of India</hi>
                            </item>
                            <label>Chapter 13:</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Physicians Who Were Prominent in the Western Lands and Settled There</hi>
                            </item>
                            <label>Chapter 14:</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Famous Physicians Amongst Those in Egypt</hi>
                            </item>
                            <label>Chapter 15:</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Famous Syrian Physicians</hi>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>