<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:py="http://codespeak.net/lxml/objectify/pytype"
 xml:id="arabicLit.textgroup.work.H01" py:pytype="TREE">
 <text>
  <body>
   <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:arabicLit:0668IbnAbiUsaibia.Tabaqatalatibba.lhom-tr-eng1"
    xml:lang="en-Latn">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9">
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="1">
      <head> Chapter 9 Physicians Who Translated Works on Medicine and Other Subjects from Greek
       into Arabic, and Their Patrons</head>
      <head> Bruce Inksetter and Ignacio Sánchez</head>
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.1 Jūrjis<note n="1" type="footnote">
         <p> This chapter is included in all three versions of the book. Biographies 9.1–9.38 of
          this chapter have clear parallels in Ibn al-Nadīm, <hi rend="italic"> Fihrist</hi>
          (Flügel, 244–245; Tajaddud, 304–306; Sayyid, 2/1:144–149). Both <hi rend="smallcaps">
           IAU</hi> and Ibn al-Nadīm seem to have relied on the same unidentified source, which, in
          view of the transliterations and the religious affiliation of the translators, must have
          been originally written by a Christian author in Syriac and later translated into Arabic.
           <hi rend="smallcaps"> IAU</hi> is more detailed than Ibn al-Nadīm. The second part of <hi
           rend="smallcaps"> IAU</hi> ’s account (9.39–9.49) centres on the sponsors of the
          translation movement and has no parallel in Ibn al-Nadīm; the main source for this list of
          patrons is Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq’s <hi rend="italic"> Epistle</hi> (<hi rend="italic">
           Risālah</hi> ). The identities of the translators mentioned in this chapter have been
          discussed in Meyerhof, ‘New Light’; Gutas, <hi rend="italic"> Greek Thought, Arabic
           Culture</hi> , 121–140; Nasrallah, <hi rend="italic"> Histoire</hi> , ii:74–91; Micheau,
          ‘Mécènes et médecins’; Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq, <hi rend="italic"> Galen Translations</hi> ,
          Appendix 2.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> The first of those who began the work of translating medical and other works from Greek
       into Arabic. Jūrjis undertook this task at the invitation of the caliph al-Manṣūr, who
       treated him with the utmost generosity. An account of his life has been given in an earlier
       chapter of this work.<note n="2" type="footnote">
        <p> See Ch. 8.1.</p>
       </note>
      </p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="2">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.2 Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq<note n="3" type="footnote">
         <p> See Ch. 8.29 for the full biography.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> Ḥunayn knew four languages – Arabic, Syriac, Greek and Persian – including rare words as
       well as common vocabulary. His works are superb examples of the translator’s art.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="3">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.3 Isḥāq ibn Ḥunayn</hi>
      </p>
      <p> Isḥāq was conversant with all the languages that his father knew, and was comparable to
       him as a translator. His style was mellifluous and his diction fluent. However, Ḥunayn has
       more works to his credit, both original compositions and translations, than Isḥāq. Accounts
       of the lives of both Isḥāq and his father have been given in an earlier chapter of this
        work.<note n="4" type="footnote">
        <p> For these two earlier biographies, see Chs. 8.29 and 8.30.</p>
       </note>
      </p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="4">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.4 Ḥubaysh al-Aʿsam<note n="5" type="footnote">
         <p> The nephew of Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq; his biography will be found in Ch. 8.31. See also <hi
           rend="italic">
           <hi rend="smallcaps"> EI</hi> Three</hi> art. ‘Ḥubaysh b. Ḥasan al-Dimashqī’
          (G. Strohmaier).</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> The son of a sister of Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq, and Ḥunayn’s pupil. An admirable translator,
       worthy to be ranked with Ḥunayn and Isḥāq. An account of his life has been given in an
       earlier chapter as well.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="5">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.5 ʿĪsā ibn Yaḥyā ibn Ibrāhīm<note n="6" type="footnote">
         <p> A very brief notice will be found at Ch. 8.35. For Ḥunayn’s numerous references to his
          translations, see Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq, <hi rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> (index).</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> Another pupil of Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq. An excellent translator: Ḥunayn praised him and held
       his translation work in high regard. ʿĪsā’s translations are closely modelled on those of
       Ḥunayn. He also produced original compositions.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="6">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.6 Qusṭā ibn Lūqā al-Baʿlabakkī</hi>
      </p>
      <p> He was a translator experienced in languages and accomplished in the philosophical and
       other sciences. An account of his life and works will be presented later in this work, God
        willing.<note n="7" type="footnote">
        <p> See Ch. 10.44 for a lengthy biography.</p>
       </note>
      </p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="7">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.7 Ayyūb, known as al-Abrash (‘the Speckled’)<note n="8" type="footnote">
         <p> Although <hi rend="smallcaps"> IAU</hi> does not include al-Ruhāwī in the name, this
          must be Ayyūb al-Ruhāwī al-Abrash (d. ca. 220/835), otherwise known as Iyob or Job of
          Edessa. Another short biography of him is given in Ch. 8.22. ‘<hi rend="italic">
           Al-abrash</hi> (‘the speckled’, or ‘the spotted’) was sometimes used as a euphemism for
           <hi rend="italic"> al-abraṣ</hi> (‘the leper’), as in the case of the pre-Islamic
          Jadhīmah, but whether this meaning was applicable to Job of Edessa is unknown. He was a
          Christian physician, although his exact confession is unknown, and worked as physician for
          the Abbasid caliphs and the governor of Khorasan, ‘Abd Allāh ibn Ṭāhir. Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq
          refers to Ayyūb al-Ruhāwī as the translator of thirty-six Galenic works (Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq,
           <hi rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> , index s.v. Aijūb al-Ruhāwī; <hi rend="italic"> Galen
           Translations</hi> , s.v. Ayyūb al-Ruhāwī). On this translator, see Roggema, ‘Iyob of
          Edessa’. For bibliographic references, see Sezgin, <hi rend="italic">
           <hi rend="smallcaps"> GAS</hi>
          </hi>
          <hi rend="smallcaps"> III</hi> , 230; Ullmann, <hi rend="italic"> Medizin</hi> ,
          101 f.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> An unproductive and mediocre translator, until late in life, when he produced a number of
       translations worthy of Ḥunayn.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="8">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.8 Māsarjīs<note n="9" type="footnote">
         <p> Māsarjīs, also called Māsarjawayh (Persian Māsargōye), was a physician of Judeo-Persian
          origin. He is one of the few known physicians from the Umayyad period, but the exact dates
          of his life are unknown: see <hi rend="italic">
           <hi rend="smallcaps"> EI</hi>
          </hi>
          <hi rend="italic">
           <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
          </hi> art. ‘Māsard̲j̲awayh’ (A. Dietrich). His biography is also given in Ch. 8.19.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> A translator from Syriac into Arabic, and renowned for his knowledge of the art of
       medicine. He is the author of works entitled:</p>
      <list>
       <label> 1.</label>
       <item> On the effectiveness of foods: their beneficial and harmful effects (<hi rend="italic"
         > K. quwā al-aṭʿimah wa-manāfiʿihā wa-maḍārrihā</hi> )</item>
       <label> 2.</label>
       <item> On the effectiveness of drugs: their beneficial and harmful effects (<hi rend="italic"
         > K. quwā al-ʿaqāqīr wa-manāfiʿihā wa-maḍārrihā</hi> )</item>
      </list>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="9">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.9 ʿĪsā ibn Māsarjīs<note n="10" type="footnote">
         <p> ‘Īsā, the son of Māsarjīs, was also a physician. Almost nothing is known about his
          life. See <hi rend="italic">
           <hi rend="smallcaps"> EI</hi>
          </hi>
          <hi rend="italic">
           <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
          </hi> art. ‘Māsard̲j̲awayh’ (A. Dietrich).</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> ʿĪsā ibn Māsarjīs followed in his father’s footsteps. He is the author of:</p>
      <list>
       <label> 1.</label>
       <item> On colours (<hi rend="italic"> K. al-alwān</hi> )</item>
       <label> 2.</label>
       <item> On scents and flavours (<hi rend="italic"> K. al-rawāʾiḥ wa-l-ṭuʿūm</hi> )</item>
      </list>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="10">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.10 Shahdā al-Karkhī<note n="11" type="footnote">
         <p> Little is known about either Shahdā al-Karkhī or his son. Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq states that
          Ibn Shahdā (written Sahdā) had translated Galen’s <hi rend="italic"> De Sectis</hi> into
          Syriac, but was a mediocre translator (Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq, <hi rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> ,
          4; Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq, <hi rend="italic"> Galen Translations</hi> , 11); he also translated
          Galen’s <hi rend="italic"> Ars medica</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> De pulsibus ad
           tirones</hi> (<hi rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> , 6; <hi rend="italic"> Galen
           Translations</hi> , 13, 15).</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> Shahdā, a native of Karkh,<note n="12" type="footnote">
        <p> A district of Baghdad. See <hi rend="italic">
          <hi rend="smallcaps"> EI</hi>
         </hi>
         <hi rend="italic">
          <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
         </hi> art. ‘al-Kark̲h̲’ (M. Streck &amp; J. Lassner).</p>
       </note> was much like the aforementioned<note n="13" type="footnote">
        <p> The expression <hi rend="italic"> qarīb al-ḥāl</hi> is puzzling; it seems to compare
         Shahdā to translators mentioned before, with <hi rend="italic"> minhum</hi>
         understsood.</p>
       </note> as a translator.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="11">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.11 Ibn Shahdā al-Karkhī</hi>
      </p>
      <p> As a translator, he produced work similar to that of his father. The translations he
       produced later in life, however, are superior to those of his father, although still
       undistinguished. Ibn Shahdā al-Karkhī translated from Syriac into Arabic. Among other things,
       he translated Hippocrates’ work on embryos.<note n="14" type="footnote">
        <p> Ibn al-Nadīm also states that Ibn Shahdā was the translator of Hippocrates’ <hi
          rend="italic"> On Embryos</hi> (<hi rend="italic"> K. al-Ajinnah</hi> ; <hi rend="italic">
          De natura pueri</hi> ; see Fichtner, <hi rend="italic"> Corpus Hippocraticum</hi> ,
         no. 46); see Ibn al-Nadīm, <hi rend="italic"> Fihrist</hi> (Flügel, 244; Tajaddud, 305;
         Sayyid, 2/1:148).</p>
       </note>
      </p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="12">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.12 al-Ḥajjāj ibn Maṭar<note n="15" type="footnote">
         <p> Al-Ḥajjāj ibn Yūsuf ibn Maṭar (fl. 169–218/786–833) translated Euclid’s <hi
           rend="italic"> Elements</hi> at the request of Hārūn al-Rashīd (r. 169–193/786–809) and
          reworked it under the caliph al-Maʾmūn (r. 197–218/813–833); see <hi rend="italic">
           <hi rend="smallcaps"> EI</hi> Three</hi> art. ‘al-Ḥajjāj b. Yūsuf b. Maṭar’ (G. de Young
          &amp; S. Brentjes). An anecdote about a mission dispatched by al-Maʾmūn to Byzantium, in
          which this translator is said to have participated, will be found in the biography of
          Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq in Ch. 8.29. Ibn al-Nadīm, <hi rend="italic"> Fihrist</hi> (Sayyid,
          1/2:145), records a translation of the <hi rend="italic"> Almagest</hi> .</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> Al-Ḥajjāj ibn Maṭar translated for the caliph al-Maʾmūn. Among other works, he produced a
       translation of Euclid’s <hi rend="italic"> Elements</hi> which was subsequently revised and
       corrected by Thābit ibn Qurrah al-Ḥarrānī.<note n="16" type="footnote">
        <p> For the biography of Thābit ibn Qurrah, see Ch. 10.3.</p>
       </note>
      </p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="13">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.13 Ibn Nāʿimah<note n="17" type="footnote">
         <p> ʿAbd al-Masīḥ ibn ʿAbd Allāh al-Ḥimṣī al-Nāʿimī was a Syriac Orthodox scholar mainly
          known for his translation of the so-called ‘Theology of Aristotle’, which is a
          periphrastic selection from the last three <hi rend="italic"> Enneads</hi> by Plotinus
          revised by al-Kindī around 225/840. He also translated Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic">
           Sophistici Elenchi</hi> . See Zimmermann, ‘Origins’.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> Ibn Nāʿimah – that is, ʿAbd al-Masīḥ ibn ʿAbd Allāh al-Ḥimṣī al-Nāʿimī – was a generally
       undistinguished translator, although he produced some respectable work on occasion.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="14">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.14 Zarūyā ibn Mānaḥūh al-Nāʿimī al-Ḥimṣī<note n="18" type="footnote">
         <p> The precise form of the name of this little-known translator is uncertain. With the
          exception of <hi rend="smallcaps"> MS</hi> A, all manuscript copies, as well as Ibn
          al-Nadīm, write the name as Zarūbā, while Zarūyā perhaps reflects a Syriac origin or a
          masculine equivalent of the Biblical name Zeruiah, the sister of David. The second part of
          the name, Mānaḥūh, may also be doubtful, and Mājūh might be a preferred reading.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> He produced facile translations, which, however, did not measure up to those of his
       predecessors.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="15">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.15 Hilāl ibn Abī Hilāl al-Ḥimṣī<note n="19" type="footnote">
         <p> Hilāl ibn Abī Hilāl al-Ḥimṣī (d. 218/833) was a mathematician associated with the Banū
          Mūsā, and one of the translators of Apollonius’ <hi rend="italic"> Conic Sections</hi>
           (<hi rend="italic"> K. al-Makhrūṭāt</hi> ); see Toomer, <hi rend="italic"> Apollonius’
           Conics</hi> , xviii, 620, 628. His father, Hilāl al-Ḥimṣī, was a physician and author of
          a book quoted by al-Rāzī; see Ullmann, <hi rend="italic"> Medizin</hi> , 122; Nasrallah,
           <hi rend="italic"> Histoire</hi> , ii:79.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> His translations are sound, but are lacking in literary style and elegance.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="16">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.16 Pethion the Translator<note n="20" type="footnote">
         <p> Pethion (fl. second half of the 3rd/9th century) was an East Syrian Christian, author
          of a lost ecclesiastical history. He is one of <hi rend="smallcaps"> IAU</hi> ’s and
          Barhebraeus’ main sources for the physicians from Gondēshāpūr, probably via quotations in
          Elias of Nisibis’ <hi rend="italic"> Chronicle</hi> . Although nothing is known about his
          life, it has been suggested that he is the Pethion of Elam to whom the Catholicos Timothy
          addressed his ninth letter; see Berti, <hi rend="italic"> L’ au-delà de l’ âme</hi> ,
          26–32. For Fathyūn al-tarjumān, see also Sezgin, <hi rend="italic">
           <hi rend="smallcaps"> GAS</hi>
          </hi>
          <hi rend="smallcaps"> III</hi> : 231.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> I have found his translations barbarously ungrammatical; his grasp of the Arabic language
       was most imperfect.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="17">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.17 Abū Naṣr ibn Nārī ibn Ayyūb</hi>
      </p>
      <p> He produced few translations, and those he did produce are considered less reliable than
       those of other translators.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="18">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.18 Basīl al-Muṭrān<note n="21" type="footnote">
         <p> According to Ibn al-Qifṭī, Basīl translated the first four books of Porphyry’s
          commentary on Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic"> Physics</hi> ; see Ibn al-Qifṭī, <hi
           rend="italic"> Taʾrīkh al-ḥukamāʾ</hi> , 39.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> A prolific and passably good translator.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="19">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.19 Iṣṭifan ibn Basīl<note n="22" type="footnote">
         <p> Little is known about the life of Iṣṭifan ibn Basīl (d. ca. 298/910). Presumably the
          son of the former translator, Iṣṭifan was a member of the Church of the East and,
          according to Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq, the author of nine translations of works by Galen
          commissioned by Muḥammad ibn Mūsā; he was also the translator of Oribasius’ <hi
           rend="italic"> Collectiones</hi> . Ḥunayn and Iṣṭifan collaborated in the translation of
          Galen’s <hi rend="italic"> Causes of Breathing</hi> (Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq, <hi rend="italic">
           Risālah</hi> , 24; Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq, <hi rend="italic"> Galen Translations</hi> , 53),
          and in the first translation of Dioscorides’ <hi rend="italic"> Materia Medica</hi> . On
          this translator see <hi rend="italic">
           <hi rend="smallcaps"> EI</hi> Three</hi> art. ‘Iṣṭifan ibn Basīl’ (I. Sánchez).</p>
         <p> According to a marginal annotation in an Istanbul manuscript containing several works
          on logic, the translator of Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic"> Prior Analytics</hi> , Tadhārā
          Ibn Basīl, was Iṣṭifan’s brother (Dāneshpazūh, <hi rend="italic"> Manṭiq</hi> , viii;
          Lameer, <hi rend="italic"> Al-Fārābī and Aristotelian Syllogism</hi> , 4). On this author,
          see Nasrallah, <hi rend="italic"> Histoire</hi> , ii:79–81; <hi rend="italic">
           <hi rend="smallcaps"> EI</hi> Three</hi> art. ‘Greek into Arabic’ (C. D’Ancona); Graf,
           <hi rend="italic"> Geschichte</hi> , ii:131.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> Not far short of the standard of Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq himself as far as his ability as a
       translator goes; however, Ḥunayn’s style is smoother and more graceful.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="20">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.20 Mūsā ibn Khālid the Translator<note n="23" type="footnote">
         <p> Mūsā ibn Khālid was a disciple of Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq; see Ibn al-Qifṭī, <hi rend="italic"
           > Taʾrīkh al-ḥukamāʾ</hi> , 171.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> I have found many works translated by this scholar, including Galen’s <hi rend="italic">
        Sixteen Books</hi>
       <note n="24" type="footnote">
        <p> That is, the Alexandrian medical curriculum: see Ch. 6.3 for the account of them by Ibn
         Riḍwān.</p>
       </note> and other works, but in terms of skill he fell far short of the standard of Ḥunayn
       ibn Isḥāq.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="21">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.21 Usṭāth<note n="25" type="footnote">
         <p> Usṭāth (Eustathius) (first half of the 3rd/9th c.) was one of the scholars of the
          circle of al-Kindī, for whom he translated Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic"> Metaphysics</hi>
          ; he was also the translator of the <hi rend="italic"> Nicomachean Ethics</hi> . See
          Endress, ‘The Circle of al-Kindī’, 52; Nasrallah, <hi rend="italic"> Histoire</hi> ,
          ii:81.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> A mediocre translator.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="22">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.22 Khayrūn ibn Rābiṭah<note n="26" type="footnote">
         <p> An otherwise unidentified translator. In all copies, the first letter is undotted,
          while the third letter is a <hi rend="italic"> rāʾ</hi> in three copies (A, P, R) but
          dotted in <hi rend="smallcaps"> MS</hi> Sb. Thus the name could be read as Ḥayzūn or
          Ḥayrūn, but Khayrūn seems more likely.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> Not renowned for the quality of his translations.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="23">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.23 Theodore the Syncellus<note n="27" type="footnote">
         <p> In Arabic al-Sunqal, a transcription of ‮ܣܘܢܩܠܐ‬‎, the Syriac rendition of the Greek
          σύγκελλος (referring specifically to the chief minister of the Constantinopolitan
          patriarch). Nothing is known about this translator. There was a certain Theodore at Mar
          Saba, brother of Michael the Syncellus, who might correspond to this figure, but Michael
          and his brothers left for Constantinople after the sack of the monastery in 197/813. See
          Brock, ‘Syriac into Greek at Mar Saba’.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> I am familiar with his translations of various philosophical works. They are quite
       acceptable in terms of quality.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="24">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.24 Sergius of Rēsh ʿAynā<note n="28" type="footnote">
         <p> Sergius of Rēsh ʿAynā (d. 536) was the most important translator of Greek medical works
          into Syriac. There is a brief notice on him in Ch. 3 6, and he is mentioned several times
          in <hi rend="smallcaps"> IAU</hi> ’s biography of Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq in Ch. 8.29. Ḥunayn ibn
          Isḥāq reports on his numerous translations in his <hi rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> . On
          this translator, see also Griffith, ‘Sergios of Rešʿaina’; Aydin, <hi rend="italic">
           Sergius of Reshaina</hi> .</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> Sergius al-Raʾsī was a native of the city of Rēsh ʿAynā.<note n="29" type="footnote">
        <p> Rēsh ʿAynā, a city in upper Mesopotamia, is the modern Raʾs al-ʿAyn, in the Ḥasakah
         Governorate of Syria, near the Turkish border.</p>
       </note> He translated many works, but was undistinguished as a translator. Some of his works
       were revised by Ḥunayn, and those are excellent, whereas those works that Ḥunayn did not
       revise are of indifferent quality.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="25">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.25 Ayyūb al-Ruhāwī (Ayyūb of Edessa)<note n="30" type="footnote">
         <p> This is the well-known Yaʿqūb of Edessa (ca. 630–708), a Syriac Orthodox polymath who
          revised previous translations of Severus of Antioch and the translation of the Old
          Testament. See Salvesen, ‘Yaʿqūb of Edessa’. Edessa, in upper Mesopotamia, later known as
          al-Ruhā (or al-Ruhāʾ), is the modern Şanlıurfa (or simply Urfa) in southeastern
          Turkey.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> Not the Ayyūb al-Abrash who was mentioned earlier. This Ayyūb was an excellent translator
       with a good knowledge of languages, although his Syriac was better than his Arabic.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="26">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.26 Yūsuf the Translator<note n="31" type="footnote">
         <p> Yūsuf al-Khūrī or al-Qass (the priest). According to Ibn al-Qifṭī, he worked as a
          physician during the caliphate of al-Muktafī (r. 288–295/902–908) and received the
          nickname ‘the sleepless’ either because of his habit of studying during the night or due
          to a tumour in his head that prevented him from sleeping. Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq is very
          critical of his translation of Galen’s <hi rend="italic"> Simple Medicines</hi> (Ḥunayn
          ibn Isḥāq, <hi rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> , 30; <hi rend="italic"> Galen
           Translations</hi> , 67). Yūsuf also translated Archimedes’ book on triangles. On this
          translator, see Ullmann, <hi rend="italic"> Medizin</hi> , 124, 319. See also
          Ch. 8.39.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> Abū Yaʿqūb ibn Yūsuf ibn ʿĪsā, known as ‘the doctor’<note n="32" type="footnote">
        <p>
         <hi rend="italic"> Al-mutaṭabbib</hi> , or medical practitioner, not necessarily in a
         pejorative sense.</p>
       </note> and ‘the translator’, and also dubbed ‘the sleepless’ (<hi rend="italic">
        al-nāʿis</hi> ), was a pupil of ʿĪsā ibn Ṣaharbukht.<note n="33" type="footnote">
        <p> ʿĪsā ibn Ṣaharbukht was a Christian physician from Gondēshāpūr, student of Jūrjis ibn
         Jibrīl ibn Bukhtīshūʿ and author of a treatise entitled <hi rend="italic"> On the
          Effectiveness of Simple Drugs</hi> . On this author, see Reinink, ‘Ṣharbokht bar Msargis’.
         The biography of ʿĪsā ibn Ṣahār Bukht (as he is there called) was given at Ch. 8.37.</p>
       </note> Yūsuf was a native of Khuzestan,<note n="34" type="footnote">
        <p> Khuzestan (Khūzistān) is a province in the southwest of Iran, situated between the
         Zagros Mountains and the Persian Gulf, bounded on the west by the Iran-Iraq border. The
         conquest of Khūzistān by Muslim armies between c. 635 and 642 is recorded in a detailed
         account preserved in a mid-to-late 7th c. east-Syriac history; see Robinson, ‘The conquest
         of Khūzistān’.</p>
       </note> and suffered from a speech impediment. His translations are unimpressive.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="27">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.27 Ibrāhīm ibn al-Ṣalt<note n="35" type="footnote">
         <p> Ibrāhīm ibn al-Ṣalt was a physician who belonged to the Church of the East. Almost
          nothing is known about his life. Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq mentions him three times as the author
          of translations into Arabic and Syriac, one sponsored by the Banū Mūsā (Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq,
           <hi rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> , 31, 34, 35; <hi rend="italic"> Galen Translations</hi>
          , 71, 81, 83).</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> A mediocre translator. His work is similar to that of Sergius of Rēsh ʿAynā.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="28">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.28 Thābit the Translator<note n="36" type="footnote">
         <p> Presumably Thābit ibn Qurrah, whose biography is given in Ch. 10.3.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> Also mediocre, albeit better than Ibrāhīm ibn al-Ṣalt. He was not a prolific translator.
       Galen’s <hi rend="italic"> Juices</hi>
       <note n="37" type="footnote">
        <p> Thābit ibn Qurrah’s translation of Galen’s <hi rend="italic"> Good and Bad Juices</hi>
         into Arabic is also mentioned by Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq (<hi rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> , 36;
          <hi rend="italic"> Galen Translations</hi> , 85) with the title <hi rend="italic"> K. fī
          l-Kaymūs</hi> . Cf. Fichtner, <hi rend="italic"> Corpus Galenicum</hi> , no. 39, and
         Ch. 5.24 for a long extract from the work.</p>
       </note> is among the works that he translated.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="29">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.29 Abū Yūsuf the Secretary<note n="38" type="footnote">
         <p> Abū Yūsuf al-Kātib is otherwise unknown.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> An undistinguished translator. He translated a number of the works of Hippocrates.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="30">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.30 Yūḥannā ibn Bukhtīshūʿ<note n="39" type="footnote">
         <p> Yūḥannā ibn Bukhtīshūʿ (d. ca. 300/912), a Christian physician of the Nestorian church,
          was the son of Bukhtīshūʿ ibn Jibrīl. Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq states that he collaborated with
          him in the translation of Galen’s <hi rend="italic"> On Antidotes</hi> (Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq,
           <hi rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> , 38; <hi rend="italic"> Galen Translations</hi> , 91).
          For his biography, see Ch. 8.32, and Ullmann, <hi rend="italic"> Medizin</hi> , 111
          no. 5a; Graf, <hi rend="italic"> Geschichte</hi> , ii:111.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> Translated numerous works into Syriac, but is not known to have done any translation into
       Arabic.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="31">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.31 al-Biṭrīq<note n="40" type="footnote">
         <p> Little is known about al-Biṭrīq, a Byzantine Melkite scholar whose translations,
          produced mainly under the caliphate of al-Manṣūr (r. 136–158/754–75), are easily confused
          with those of his son Yaḥyā. He translated medical works by Galen and Hippocrates, and
          also, according to Ibn al-Nadīm, Ptolemy’s <hi rend="italic"> Tetrabiblos</hi> , for the
          astronomer/astrologer ʿUmar ibn al-Farrūkhān; see Ibn al-Nadīm, <hi rend="italic">
           Fihrist</hi> (Flügel, 273; Tajaddud, 336; Sayyid, 2/1:232). On this author, see Dunlop,
          ‘The Translations of al-Biṭrīq’; Nasrallah, <hi rend="italic"> Histoire</hi> ,
          ii:81–82.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> Lived in the time of al-Manṣūr. The caliph ordered him to undertake the task of
       translating a number of ancient works. He did so, translating numerous books, but as a
       translator he is not up to the standard of Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq. I have seen Arabic versions of
       many of the medical works of Hippocrates and Galen that are by al-Biṭrīq.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="32">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.32 Yaḥyā ibn al-Biṭrīq<note n="41" type="footnote">
         <p> Yaḥyā (or Yūḥannā) ibn al-Biṭrīq (d. ca. 200/815) was, according to Ibn Juljul, the
          client (<hi rend="italic"> mawlā</hi> ) of al-Maʾmūn, a status that usually implies a
          conversion to Islam. Yaḥyā is one of the first translators of philosophical works into
          Arabic, and the translation of the pseudo-Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic"> Secretum
           Secretorum</hi> (<hi rend="italic"> Sirr al-asrār</hi> ) has also been attributed to him
           (<hi rend="italic"> Sirr al-asrār</hi> , 69; Ibn Juljul, <hi rend="italic"> Ṭabaqāt
           al-aṭibbāʾ</hi> , 26). Ibn al-Biṭrīq also composed two medical treatises: <hi
           rend="italic"> On poisons and their dangers</hi> (<hi rend="italic"> K. al-sumūmāt
           wa-dafʿ maḍārrihā</hi> ) and <hi rend="italic"> On the Classes of Insects</hi> (<hi
           rend="italic"> K. ajnās al-ḥasharāt</hi> ). On this author, see Dunlop, ‘The Translations
          of al-Biṭrīq’; <hi rend="italic">
           <hi rend="smallcaps"> EI</hi>
          </hi>
          <hi rend="italic">
           <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
          </hi> art. ‘Yaḥyā (or Yūḥannā) b. al-Biṭrīḳ‘ (F. Micheau); <hi rend="italic">
           <hi rend="smallcaps"> EI</hi> Three</hi> art. ‘Ibn al-Biṭrīq, Yaḥyā’ (G. Strohmaier);
          Sezgin, <hi rend="italic">
           <hi rend="smallcaps"> GAS</hi>
          </hi>
          <hi rend="smallcaps"> III</hi> , 225; Ullmann, <hi rend="italic"> Medizin</hi> , 326;
          Nasrallah, <hi rend="italic"> Histoire</hi> , ii:82–86.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> Belonged to the circle of al-Ḥasan ibn Sahl.<note n="42" type="footnote">
        <p> Al-Ḥasan ibn Sahl (d. 236/850–851), secretary and governor of Iraq under al-Maʾmūn. See
          <hi rend="italic">
          <hi rend="smallcaps"> EI</hi>
         </hi>
         <hi rend="italic">
          <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
         </hi> art. ‘al-Ḥasan b. Sahl’ (D. Sourdel).</p>
       </note> He did not know much of either Arabic or Greek, as he was a Latin<note n="43"
        type="footnote">
        <p> Yaḥyā ibn al-Biṭrīq belonged to a Byzantine Melkite family, had Greek as his mother
         tongue, and translated directly from Greek (not Syriac). Ancient Greek is here identified
         with the uncial script. ‘Contemporary vernacular form of Greek’: literally ‘language of the
         Romans of the day’.</p>
       </note> who was fluent in the contemporary vernacular form of Greek and knew how to write it
       in its characteristic cursive script instead of the discrete letters of ancient Greek
       writing.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="33">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.33 Tūmā al-Ruhāwī (Thomas of Edessa)<note n="44" type="footnote">
         <p> The manuscripts of <hi rend="smallcaps"> IAU</hi> give the name as Qīḍā, but this is an
          error. Tūmā al-Ruhāwī (Thomas of Edessa) was a contemporary of Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq. Ḥunayn
          refers to him as ‘a certain man from Edessa’. Thomas translated the last part of Galen’s
           <hi rend="italic"> A Man’s Ability to Know the Imperfections of his Soul</hi> (Ḥunayn ibn
          Isḥāq, <hi rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> , 49; <hi rend="italic"> Galen Translations</hi> ,
          121; <hi rend="italic"> De propriorum animi cuiuslibet affectuum dignotione et
           curatione</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> De animi cuiuslibet peccatorum dignotione et
           curatione</hi> , Fichtner, <hi rend="italic"> Corpus Galenicum</hi> nos. 29–30). Nothing
          is known about his life, but he is mentioned in other major sources: see Ibn al-Qifṭī, <hi
           rend="italic"> Taʾrīkh al-ḥukamāʾ</hi> , 131; Ibn al-Nadīm, <hi rend="italic">
           Fihrist</hi> (Flügel, 291; Tajaddud, 349; Sayyid, 2/1:280).</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> Whenever Ḥunayn had a great deal of translation work in hand and was pressed for time, he
       would ask Tūmā al-Ruhāwī (Thomas of Edessa) to do some of the translation, subsequently
       revising what he had done.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="34">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.34 Manṣūr ibn Bānās<note n="45" type="footnote">
         <p> Almost nothing is known about this translator. According to Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq, Ibn Bānās
          was a Sabian, author of a deficient Syriac translation of Galen’s <hi rend="italic">
           Character Traits</hi> (Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq, <hi rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> , 49 [written
          Ibn Athānās]; <hi rend="italic"> Galen Translations</hi> , 121).</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> Approximately as good a translator as Thomas of Edessa. His Syriac was stronger than his
       Arabic.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="35">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.35 ʿAbdīshūʿ ibn Bahrīz (ʿAbdishoʿ bar Bahrīz)<note n="46" type="footnote">
         <p> ʿAbdishoʿ bar Bahrīz was the metropolitan of Harran, Mosul and Ḥazza; see Roggema,
          ‘Abdisho bar Bahrīz’. For Jibrīl ibn Bukhtīshūʿ (d. 212/827), the son of Bukhtīshūʿ ibn
          Jūrjis, see his biography in Ch. 8.3.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> The metropolitan of Mosul. He was a friend of Jibrīl ibn Bukhtīshūʿ and one of his
       translators.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="36">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.36 Abū ʿUthmān Saʿīd ibn Yaʿqūb al-Dimashqī<note n="47" type="footnote">
         <p> Saʿīd ibn Yaʿqūb al-Dimashqī was a very important physician and translator of medical
          and philosophical texts, including definitive versions of Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic">
           Topica</hi> and Porphyry’s <hi rend="italic"> Isagoge</hi> ; he is also mentioned in Ibn
          al-Qifṭī, <hi rend="italic"> Taʾrīkh al-ḥukamāʾ</hi> , 409; and Ibn al-Nadīm, <hi
           rend="italic"> Fihrist</hi> (Flügel, 298; Tajaddud, 356; Sayyid, 2/1:304). See <hi
           rend="italic">
           <hi rend="smallcaps"> EI</hi> Three</hi> art. ‘Abū ʿUthmān al-Dimashqī’ (G. Endress). For
          his biography, see Ch. 10.16.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> A translator of the first order who served ʿAlī ibn ʿĪsā<note n="48" type="footnote">
        <p> The well-known Abbasid vizier (d. 334/946), twice vizier under al-Muqtadir bi-Allāh. See
          <hi rend="italic">
          <hi rend="smallcaps"> EI</hi> Three</hi> art. ‘ʿAlī b. ʿIsā b. Dāʾūd b. al-Jarrāḥ’
         (M.L.M. van Berkel); <hi rend="italic">
          <hi rend="smallcaps"> EI</hi>
         </hi>
         <hi rend="italic">
          <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
         </hi> art. ‘ʿAlī b. ʿIsā’ (D. Bowen); Gutas, <hi rend="italic"> Greek Thought, Arabic
          Culture</hi> , 72, 132.</p>
       </note> exclusively.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="37">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.37 Abū Isḥāq Ibrāhīm ibn Baks<note n="49" type="footnote">
         <p> Ibrāhīm ibn Baks (fl. 4th/10th c.) was a Christian physician active in Baghdad, whose
          biography is given in Ch. 10.42. Ibn al-Qifṭī, who refers to him as Ibrāhīm ibn Bakkūsh
          al-ʿAshshārī, states that he translated three works. The first one is Aristotle’s <hi
           rend="italic"> Sophistica</hi> , which he translated into Arabic from Ibn Nāʿimah’s
          Syriac version (Ibn al-Qifṭī, <hi rend="italic"> Taʾrīkh al-ḥukamāʾ</hi> , 37); according
          to the colophon of the Paris <hi rend="smallcaps"> MS</hi> , he collated the Greek
          original with the help of Yūḥannā ibn Fātilah (see Peters, <hi rend="italic"> Aristoteles
           Arabus</hi> , 25). The other two are translations of Theophrastus’ <hi rend="italic"> The
           Causes of Plants</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> On Sense Perception</hi> (Ibn al-Qifṭī, <hi
           rend="italic"> Taʾrīkh al-ḥukamāʾ</hi> , 107). Two sources suggest that he was already
          active during the first half of the 4th/10th century. <hi rend="smallcaps"> IAU</hi>
          states that a physician named Abū l-Ḥasan ibn Nafīs commissioned the translation of
          Yūḥannā ibn Sarābiyūn’s <hi rend="italic"> al-Kunnāsh al-ṣaghīr</hi> in 312/924–925.
          According to the Qāḍī ʿAbd al-Jabbār, ‘one Abū l-Ḥasan ibn Nafīs’ was the teacher of Ibn
          Baks (ʿAbd al-Jabbār, <hi rend="italic"> Tathbīt</hi> , 619), and Ibn Baks was one of the
          physicians who struggled to fight an epidemic that spread over Baghdad in 330/941–942
          (ʿAbd al-Jabbār, <hi rend="italic"> Tathbīt</hi> , 619). On this physician, see Ullmann,
           <hi rend="italic"> Die Natur- und Geheimwissenschaften</hi> , 73–74; Gutas, <hi
           rend="italic"> Greek Thought, Arabic Culture</hi> , 151.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> A renowned physician who translated many works into the Arabic language. His translations,
       too, are highly esteemed.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="38">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.38 Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Ibrāhīm ibn Baks<note n="50" type="footnote">
         <p> Like his father, ʿAlī ibn Ibrāhīm ibn Baks (d. 394/1003–1004) was a physician: he
          worked at the ʿAḍudī Hospital in Baghdad (Ibn al-Qifṭī, <hi rend="italic"> Taʾrīkh
           al-ḥukamāʾ</hi> , 235–236). His biography is also given in Ch. 10.43.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> Also a well-known physician, and a reliable translator as well.</p>
      <p>
       <hi rend="italic"> The patrons of these translators, other than caliphs, are listed
        below</hi> :</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="39">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.39 Sabrīshūʿ ibn Quṭrub (Sabrishoʿ bar Quṭrub)<note n="51" type="footnote">
         <p> Sabrīshūʿ ibn Quṭrub (Syriac, Sabrishoʿ bar Quṭrub) was a physician from Gondēshāpūr,
          mentioned by Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq as the commissioner of Galen’s <hi rend="italic"> On
           Sects</hi> , one of his earliest translations, made when he was in his early twenties
          (Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq, <hi rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> , 5; <hi rend="italic"> Galen
           Translations</hi> , 11). The name in all <hi rend="smallcaps"> MSS</hi> is written as <hi
           rend="italic"> Sh-y-r-sh-w-ʿ</hi> . On this author, see Micheau, ‘Mécènes et médecins’,
          162–163.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> He was from Gondēshāpūr and was always generous to translators, constantly bestowing
       presents upon them; he sought to attract them and obtain books from them by paying them as
       much as he could manage. It was Syriac translations that he prized, rather than Arabic.
       Sabrīshūʿ ibn Quṭrub was of Khuzestani origin.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="40">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.40 Muḥammad ibn Mūsā the Astrologer<note n="52" type="footnote">
         <p> Mūsā ibn Shākir was an astronomer and companion of the caliph al-Maʾmūn since the days
          of his governorate in Khorasan. Mūsā’s three sons, Muḥammad, Aḥmad and al-Ḥasan, played a
          central role in the intellectual life of 3rd/9th c. Baghdad, especially as sponsors of
          translations. Muḥammad ibn Mūsā (d. 259/873) is mentioned by Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq as the
          commissioner of numerous translations (see Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq, <hi rend="italic">
           Risālah</hi> , index). One source also refers to him as the author of a work entitled <hi
           rend="italic"> On Realms and Routes</hi> (<hi rend="italic"> K. al-Mamālik
           wa-l-Masālik</hi> ); see Contadini, <hi rend="italic"> World of Beasts</hi> , 93. On the
          Banū Mūsā family, see <hi rend="italic">
           <hi rend="smallcaps"> EI</hi>
          </hi>
          <hi rend="italic">
           <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
          </hi> art. ‘Mūsā, Banū’ (D.R. Hill); Gutas, <hi rend="italic"> Greek Thought, Arabic
           Culture</hi> , 133–134; Micheau, ‘Mécènes et médecins’, 167–170.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> One of the sons of Mūsā ibn Shākir, who were noted arithmeticians and celebrated for their
       skill, learning and writings on the mathematical sciences. This one, Muḥammad, was a most
       generous patron to Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq, who translated numerous medical works for him.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="41">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.41 ʿAlī ibn Yaḥyā, known as Ibn al-Munajjim<note n="53" type="footnote">
         <p> The Banū l-Munajjim were a Zoroastrian family of Persian origin who joined the Abbasid
          court of al-Manṣūr (r. 136–158/754–775) as astrologers, whence their name. They enjoyed
          high status for several generations and stand out as one of the most influential families
          in the intellectual life of the 3rd–4th/9th–10th cc. and as sponsors of the translation
          movement. Among other works, ʿAlī ibn Yaḥyā commissioned Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq’s famous <hi
           rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> . On this family, see <hi rend="italic">
           <hi rend="smallcaps"> EI</hi>
          </hi>
          <hi rend="italic">
           <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
          </hi> art. ‘Munad̲j̲d̲j̲im, Banū’ l-’ (M. Fleischhammer); <hi rend="italic">
           <hi rend="smallcaps"> EI</hi> Three</hi> art. ‘Banū Munajjim family’ (L. Berggren);
          Gutas, <hi rend="italic"> Greek Thought, Arabic Culture</hi> , 128; Micheau, ‘Mécènes et
          medecins’, 164–167.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> A secretary and companion of the caliph al-Maʾmūn, who held him in high regard. He was
       interested in medicine and commissioned the translation of numerous works on that
       subject.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="42">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.42 Tādurā <emph> al-usquf</emph> (Theodore the Bishop)<note n="54"
         type="footnote">
         <p> The Arabic Tādurā is a transcription of the Syriac rendition of Theodore (‮ܛܐܕܘܖܐ‬‎).
          Theodore the Bishop (<hi rend="italic"> al-usquf</hi> ) is to be identified with Theodore
          of Karkh Guddan, bishop of that city, who was a patron of letters and a translator closely
          associated with Sergius of Rēsh ʿAynā: see Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq, <hi rend="italic">
           Risālah</hi> , 12; <hi rend="italic"> Galen Translations</hi> , 27. See Aydin, <hi
           rend="italic"> Sergius of Reshaina</hi> , sections 2.1.1, 2.1.7, 4.8.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> A bishop in al-Karkh in Baghdad. He was an avid book-collector, and accordingly sought to
       win the hearts of translators. In this way he acquired many books. A number of Christian
       physicians composed important works for him which they published under his patronage.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="43">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.43 Muḥammad ibn Mūsā ibn ʿAbd al-Malik<note n="55" type="footnote">
         <p> The identification of this patron is conjectural, but it is likely that he corresponds
          to Abū ʿImrān Mūsā ibn ʿAbd al-Malik ibn Hishām al-Iṣbahānī (Muḥammad is not part of his
          name). Mūsā ibn ʿAbd al-Malik (d. 246/860–861) was in charge of the land tax (<hi
           rend="italic"> ṣāḥib dīwān al-kharāj</hi> ) and the caliphal chancellery (<hi
           rend="italic"> dīwān al-rasāʾil</hi> ) under al-Mutawakkil; see Ibn Khallikān, <hi
           rend="italic"> Wafayāt</hi> , v:337–341 (n. 750).</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> A number of medical works were translated for him. He himself was a man of considerable
       learning and prepared summaries of various books, retaining their valuable parts and
       discarding those that were of no interest.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="44">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.44 ʿĪsā ibn Yūnus, the Secretary and Accountant<note n="56"
         type="footnote">
         <p> ʿĪsā ibn Yūnus <hi rend="italic"> al-kātib al-ḥāsib</hi> is unidentified. A ‘civil
          servant’ was usually either a drafter of documents and epistles (<hi rend="italic">
           kātib</hi> ) or a financial expert and accountant (<hi rend="italic"> ḥāsib</hi> ). For a
          debate between the two, see al-Tawḥidī, <hi rend="italic"> Imtāʿ</hi> , i:96, and van
          Berkel, ‘Accountants and Men of Letters’. Some, like ʿĪsā ibn Yūnus, combined the two.
          According to the recension B of Ḥunayn’s <hi rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> , Isḥāq ibn
          Ḥunayn translated Galen’s <hi rend="italic"> The Usefulness of Pulse</hi> for ‘Īsā ibn
          Yūnus, which might refer to the same person; see Bergsträsser, ‘Neue Materialen’, 34;
          Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq, <hi rend="italic"> Galen Translations</hi> , 57.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> A distinguished scholar of Iraq. He was a keen collector of ancient books and had a deep
       interest in Greek learning.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="45">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.45 ʿAlī, known as al-Fayyūm<note n="57" type="footnote">
         <p> Unidentified. Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq translated Galen’s <hi rend="italic"> Parts of
           Medicine</hi> for him (Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq, <hi rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> , 32; <hi
           rend="italic"> Galen Translations</hi> , 73). Since it was a translation into Syriac,
          ʿAlī al-Fayyūm must have been a Christian; see Meyerhof, ‘New Light’, 720.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> So dubbed because of his tenure as governor of the Fayyum.<note n="58" type="footnote">
        <p> The Fayyum (al-Fayyūm) is a large district in central Egypt that had a large Christian
         population. For a full analysis of the cadastral survey of the Fayyum by al-Nābulusī in the
         mid-7th/13th c., see Rapoport, <hi rend="italic"> Rural Society</hi> , and Rapoport, <hi
          rend="italic"> Rural Economy and Tribal Society</hi> .</p>
       </note> He was generous to translators, who grew fat on his bounty.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="46">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.46 Aḥmad ibn Muḥammad, known as Ibn al-Mudabbir, the Secretary<note n="59"
         type="footnote">
         <p> Aḥmad ibn Muḥammad ibn al-Mudabbir (d. 270 or 271/883 or 884) was a high-ranking
          official at the courts of al-Wāthiq and al-Mutawakkil and a man of letters. Ḥunayn ibn
          Isḥāq translated for him the <hi rend="italic"> Commentary of the Hippocratic
           Aphorisms</hi> (Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq, <hi rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> , 40; <hi rend="italic"
           > Galen Translations</hi> , 97). On this patron, see <hi rend="italic">
           <hi rend="smallcaps"> EI</hi>
          </hi>
          <hi rend="italic">
           <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
          </hi> art. ‘Ibn al-Mudabbir’ (H.L. Gottschalk); Micheau, ‘Mécènes et médecins’,
          172–174.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> An unfailing source of ample money and benefits for translators.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="47">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.47 Ibrāhīm ibn Muḥammad ibn Mūsā, the Secretary<note n="60"
         type="footnote">
         <p> Ibrāhīm ibn Muḥammad ibn Mūsā might be the son of the aforementioned (Ch. 9.40)
          Muḥammad ibn Mūsā al-Munajjim; see Meyerhof, ‘New Light’, 715; Micheau, ‘Mécènes et
          médecins’, 169–170. Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq translated for him Galen’s <hi rend="italic">
           Commentary on Hippocrates’ ‘Prognosis’</hi> (Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq, <hi rend="italic">
           Risālah</hi> , 41; <hi rend="italic"> Galen Translations</hi> , 97).</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> He took a great interest in the translation of Greek works into the Arabic language. He
       was extremely generous toward men of learning and scholarship, including translators in
       particular.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="48">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.48 ʿAbd Allāh ibn Isḥāq<note n="61" type="footnote">
         <p> Almost nothing is known about ʿAbd Allāh ibn Isḥāq. In recension A of the <hi
           rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> , Ḥunayn states that he corrected for him a translation of
          Galen’s <hi rend="italic"> The Best Physician is also a Philosopher</hi> (Ḥunayn ibn
          Isḥāq, <hi rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> , 47); in recension B, he states that he made a
          second translation; see Bergsträsser, ‘Neue Materialen’, 37; Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq, <hi
           rend="italic"> Galen Translations</hi> , 109.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> He also was deeply interested in having works translated and collecting them.</p>
     </div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="biography" n="49">
      <p>
       <hi rend="bold"> 9.49 Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd al-Malik ibn al-Zayyāt<note n="62" type="footnote">
         <p> Ibn al-Zayyāt (d. 243/847) was vizier under the Abbasid caliphs al-Muʿtaṣim and
          al-Wāthiq, but fell into disgrace with al-Mutawakkil, who had him imprisoned and tortured.
          A poet himself, Ibn al-Zayyāt was an important Maecenas who patronized authors such as
          al-Jāhiẓ and sponsored the translation of Galenic works. Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq states that he
          translated Galen’s <hi rend="italic"> On Voice</hi> for Ibn al-Zayyāt (Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq,
           <hi rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> , 24; <hi rend="italic"> Galen Translations</hi> , 55),
          and that he had to postpone his translation of Galen’s <hi rend="italic"> Character
           Traits</hi> due to his dealings with the vizier (<hi rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> , 49;
           <hi rend="italic"> Galen Translations</hi> , 121). See also <hi rend="italic">
           <hi rend="smallcaps"> EI</hi>
          </hi>
          <hi rend="italic">
           <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
          </hi> art. ‘Ibn al-Zayyāt’ (D. Sourdel); Micheau, ‘Mécènes et médecins’, 171–172.</p>
        </note>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p> He spent nearly 2,000 dinars a month on translators, scholars and copyists. Many books
       were translated under his patronage, including Greek works, and a number of distinguished
       physicians prepared translations for him, including Yūḥannā ibn Māsawayh,<note n="63"
        type="footnote">
        <p> Yūḥannā ibn Māsawayh (d. 243/877), the Latin Mesue, was one of the first physicians who
         wrote medical works in Arabic. His biography is given in Ch. 8.26. On his role as patron
         and translator, see Micheau, ‘Mécènes et médecins’, 152–155.</p>
       </note> Jibrīl ibn Bukhtīshūʿ, Bukhtīshūʿ ibn Jibrīl ibn Bukhtīshūʿ,<note n="64"
        type="footnote">
        <p> On the role of the Bukhtīshūʿ family as translators and patrons, see Micheau, ‘Mécènes
         et médecins’, 155–158. Their biographies are given in Ch. 8.3 and Ch. 8.4 respectively.</p>
       </note> Dāwūd ibn Sarābiyūn,<note n="65" type="footnote">
        <p> Meyerhof suggests that Dāwūd ibn Sarābiyūn corresponds to the Dāwūd al-Mutaṭabbib who
         commissioned five Syriac translations of Galenic works from Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq (<hi
          rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> , 3, 6, 49; <hi rend="italic"> Galen Translations</hi> , 9,
         13, 121); see also Meyerhof, ‘New Light’, 719. Ḥunayn states that Dāwūd was in his thirties
         when he translated Galen’s <hi rend="italic"> On the Medical Art</hi> (Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq,
          <hi rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> , 6; <hi rend="italic"> Galen Translations</hi> , 13).
         According to Ibn al-Qifṭī, Dāwūd, a native of Beth Garmai, was one of the court physicians
         under al-Hādī (r. 159–170/775–786) and the brother of Yūḥannā ibn Sarābiyūn, the author of
         the <hi rend="italic"> Pandectae</hi> (<hi rend="italic"> al-Kunnāsh</hi> ) (Ibn al-Qifṭī,
          <hi rend="italic"> Taʾrīkh al-ḥukamāʾ</hi> , 431). Ullmann, who has questioned the dating
         of this work in view of the various quotations from authors who lived in the second half of
         the 3rd/9th century, argues that the publication of Ibn Sarābiyūn’s <hi rend="italic">
          Kunnāsh</hi> should be dated at the end of that century, and that Dāwūd and Yūḥannā were
         separated by a century (Ullmann, ‘Yūḥannā ibn Sarābiyūn’, 280). <hi rend="smallcaps">
          IAU</hi> also refers to Dāwūd ibn Sarābiyūn as the brother of Yūḥannā and mentions him
         elsewhere several times, often in connection with the Bukhtīshūʿ family (Chs. 8.2; 8.3; and
         8.25); he states that Abū l-Ḥasan ibn Nafīs, teacher of Ibn Baks, commissioned the
         translation of Ibn Sarābiyūn’s <hi rend="italic"> al-Kunnāsh al-ṣaghīr</hi> in the year
         313/925–926 (Ch. 6.5). On Dāwūd al-Mutaṭabbib, see also Micheau, ‘Mécènes et médecins’,
         159–161.</p>
       </note> Salmawayh ibn Bunān,<note n="66" type="footnote">
        <p> Salmawayh ibn Bunān (d. 225/840) was a Christian physician to the caliph al-Muʿtaṣim (r.
         218–227/833–842). His biography is given in Ch. 8.20. He sponsored fourteen Syriac and
         Arabic translations of Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq and collaborated with him in the translation of
         Galen’s <hi rend="italic"> The Method of Healing</hi> (<hi rend="italic"> K. fī ḥīlat
          al-burʾ</hi> ). Ḥunayn wrote a short epistle addressed to him as an introduction to his
         Syriac translation of Galen’s <hi rend="italic"> Habits</hi> . See Micheau, ‘Mécènes et
         médecins’, 150–152.</p>
       </note> al-Yasaʿ,<note n="67" type="footnote">
        <p> That is, Elisha. A certain al-Yasaʿ commissioned the Syriac translation of Galen’s <hi
          rend="italic"> Classification of the Diseases of the Internal Parts</hi> to Sergius of
         Rēsh ʿAynā; see Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq (<hi rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> , 12; <hi rend="italic">
          Galen Translations</hi> , 27).</p>
       </note> Isrāʾīl ibn Zakariyyā ibn al-Ṭayfūrī,<note n="68" type="footnote">
        <p> Isrāʾīl ibn Zakariyyā ibn al-Ṭayfūrī, of the Nestorian church, belonged to a well-known
         family of physicians. Following in the steps of his father, Ibn al-Ṭayfūrī became the
         personal physician of the vizier al-Fatḥ ibn Khāqān and worked at the court until the time
         of al-Muntaṣir, whom he was accused of poisoning (Ṭabarī, <hi rend="italic"> Taʾrīkh</hi> ,
         iii:1496). Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq reports that he asked him to write a second Syriac translation
         of Galen’s <hi rend="italic"> Classification of the Diseases of the Internal Parts</hi>
         (Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq, <hi rend="italic"> Risālah</hi> , 13; <hi rend="italic"> Galen
          Translations</hi> , 29). On this physician (and his father and grandfather), see Micheau,
         ‘Mécènes et médecins’, 161–162. The biographies of members of the Ṭayfūrī family are given
         in Chs. 8.10; 8.11; and 8.12.</p>
       </note> and Ḥubaysh ibn al-Ḥasan.<note n="69" type="footnote">
        <p> The biographies of most of these physicians will be found in Ch. 8. The last-named of
         them, Ḥubaysh ibn al-Ḥasan, is the Ḥubaysh al-Aʿsam mentioned earlier in Ch. 9.4.</p>
       </note>
      </p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
