<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> {460}
al-ʿAbbāsah, a town in Egypt favoured by Ayy-ubids as a retreat for hunting and fishing 14.54.4
Abdera, ancient Greek city  4.1.2; 4.1.9.2
Abīward `see` Bāward
Abū Hurayra, village west of al-Raqqah 14.50n
Abū Najīḥ Street (Sikkat Abī Najīḥ), in Mosul 10.81.2
Acragas, ancient Greek city in Sicily, the modern Agrigento 3.4n; 3.5n; 4.1.11.3n; 4.3.4.2n
Acre (Akko, ʿAkkā), a city in the northern coastal plain of modern-day Israel 15.11.2; 15.11.2.1; 15.40.3 Ādharbayjān `see` Azerbaijan
ʿĀdiliyyah Law College (al-Madrasah al-ʿĀdiliyyah), in Damascus 15.19
ʿAḍudī Hospital (al-Bīmāristān al-ʿAḍudī), in Baghdad 10.31; 10.32; 10.33; 10.37.1; 10.37.2; 10.42; 10.58.3; 10.72n; 10.79; 11.5.2; 11.5.3; 11.5.4; 11.5.5; 11.5.6; 11.5.7; 14.22.5.1n; 15.3.1n; 15.13n
Aegina, Greek island 4.1.9.2n; 4.1.11.3n; 8.29.22n
Afqah `see` Maghārat Afqah
Afrūjiyyā `see` Phrygia
Afshanah, a village near Bokhara, birthplace of Ibn Sīnā 11.13.2.1
Āghmāt, town in mid-southern Morocco 13.66.3n Agrigento `see` Acragas
Ahlat `see` Khilāṭ
al-Ahwāz (or Ahvaz), an early important commercial town on the river Kārūn (or Dujayl) situated halfway between Bagh-dad and Shiraz 8.3.10; 8.3.14; 8.15.1; 10.25; 11.16 no. 1.33; 14.22.4.3 no. 23; 14.22.4.4 ʿAjlūn (Ajloun), a hilly town in the north of
present-day Jordan 15.51.5; 15.60.1 Akhmīm, city in Upper Egypt, the ancient
Panopolis 2.1.4n
ʿAkkā, Akko `see` Acre
Alarcos, city in today’s province of Ciudad Real (Spain) 13.66.3n
Alburz, mountain range in northern Persia 8.20.11n
Aleppo (Ḥalab, Greek Beroea), city in Syria 5.1.19; 8.26.10n; 10.38.2; 10.69.4 no. 5n; 11.21 no. 6; 14.21 no. 3; 14.22.3.2; 14.49.2n; 15.1.5 no. 72; 15.2n; 15.5; 15.6; 15.7; 15.12; 15.15; 15.16; 15.18.1; 15.18.1.3; 15.18.1.4; 15.23.2.1; 15.30; 15.31; 15.32; 15.40.5; 15.40.6; 15.40.7; 15.40.9 nos. 24, 73, 78, 85, 168; 15.41; 15.45.3; 15.49.3; 15.50.6; 15.51.1; 15.51.4n; 15.54
Alexandria (al-Iskandariyyah) 4.1.10.3n; 4.1.11.2; 4.1.11.3; 5.1.21.1; 5.1.25; 5.1.26; 5.1.37 no. 115; 6.1.1; 6.1.2; 6.1.3 (Museum/ House of Knowledge); 7.1.5n; 7.4; 8.19.1n; 8.29.9; 11.8.6 no. 15; 13.51.3; 13.51.4 no. 3; 13.58.2.1; 13.58.4.2; 13.86.2; 14.1; 14.11; 14.25.2n; 14.26.3 no. 2; 14.32.5 no. 3; 14.54.10; 15.1.2; 15.31.1; 15.33
ʿĀlij, of uncertain location, often said to be a sandy tract in Arabia 10.69.3.10(p)
ʿĀliqīn, location outside of Damascus 14.38.1n
Almeria (Almería, al-Mariyyah), town in al-Andalus 13.30; 15.8.1n
{461}
al-ʿAlth, town north of Baghdad, on the east bank of the Tigris 8.25.7
Alzira (Jazīrat al-Shuqar), city in the province of Valencia (Spain) 13.84
Amida (Āmid), an ancient town in eastern Anatolia 10.2.3.1; 10.10.5; 10.75.3; 11.13.7.9(p); 15.22n; 15.56.1 al-Amīniyyah Law College (al-Madrasah al-Amīniyyah), in Damascus 15.34 ʿAmmūriyah (Amorion/Amorium; Syriac
Amūrīn), stronghold on the military road from Constantinople to Cilicia, southwest of Ankara 8.26.3; 8.26.5; 8.29.3n
Amorion/Amorium `see` ʿAmmūriyah
ʿAmtā, small village in Jordan 15.51.5 Anatolia (Bilād al-Rūm; `see also` Asia Minor)
10.82; 15.40.5
Anazarbus, Anazarba `see` ʿAyn Zarbah al-Anbār (Greek Bērsabōra), important town
on the left bank of the Euphrates near Baghdad 8.3.16; 5.16.1
Ancyra, the modern Ankara 8.26.3 al-Andalus, Islamic Spain and Portugal
1.7n; 8.3.6; 8.19.2n; 10.9.1n; 13 `passim`; 14.6n; 14.27.2n; 15.11.1 Anṭākiyah `see` Antioch
Antioch (Anṭākiyah, Antakya), ancient town in northern Syria (now in Turkey) 5.1.8.2; 6.1.3; 7.4; 10.38.6 no. 7; 10.61; 14.3; 14.4.1; 14.27.3; 15.1.2 Apamea, Greek city in north-west Syria
4.10.1.3n
Aphrodisias, ancient Greek city in south-western Anatolia 4.1.10.5; 4.1.11.3; 4.8; 4.8.2
ʿAqrabāʾ, a locality near the Syrian city of Damascus 15.32
al-Aqṣā Mosque (al-Jāmiʿ al-Aqṣā), in Jerus-alem 15.40.5
Aquileia, Roman city of northern Italy Arabian Peninsula 7.5.3n
Arbil `see` Erbil
Argos, Greek city of the Peloponnese al-ʿArīsh, Egyptian city on the Mediterranean coast of Sinai 7.5.6
Armenia (Armīniyah), region of the southern Caucasus 5.1.16.1; 10.44.4; 10.46.4 no. 15 Arzan al-Rūm `see` Erzerum
Arzanjān `see` Erzinjan
Ascalon, coastal city of Palestine 6.1.1n; 14.33.3n; 15.1.3n
Asia Minor (Bilād al-Rūm; `see also` Anatolia) 14.3n; 14.54.11; 14.58.1; 14.58.2
ʿAsqalān `see` Ascalon
Aswān, town on the eastern bank of the Nile in Upper Egypt 14.22.3.1
Asyūṭ (Assiut), city of Upper Egypt import-ant for trade and agriculture 5.1.21.1 Atarneus, ancient Greek city in Asia Minor
4.6.2.1
Athens 2.1.6.1n; 2.1.6.4n; 4.1.10.2n; 4.1.11.3; 4.4.2.1; 4.4.2.3; 4.4.3; 4.5.1; 4.5.2; 4.6.2.1; 4.6.2.3; 4.6.3.1; 5.1.21.1; 5.1.25n
Atlantic Ocean (Baḥr al-Ẓulmah, Sea of Dark-ness) 13.4n
al-ʿAttābiyyah, a quarter in Baghdad famous for its cloth called `ʿattābī` 15.18.1.3n ʿAydhāb, a once important port on the Red
Sea in what is now modern-day Sudan 15.23.2.1
ʿAyn Jālūt `see` Wādī Kanʿān
ʿAyn Shams, now a suburb of Cairo, the ancient Heliopolis 4.3.4.2
ʿAyn Zarbah/Zarbā (Anazarbos, Anazarba), ancient city in south-western Anatolia 4.1.11.2; 4.1.11.3; 5.1.8.2; 14.29.1
Azerbaijan (Ādharbayjān), a country in the Caucasus region of Eurasia 8.11n; 8.20.11n; 11.13.7.9(p); 11.21 al-Azhar Mosque (al-Jāmiʿ al-Azhar)
14.22.2; 14.22.3.1; 15.40.4 al-ʿAzīziyyah, a region consisting of five vil-lages in Egypt named after the Fatimid
caliph al-ʿAzīz 14.54.3
al-ʿAzīziyyah Law College (al-Madrasah al-ʿAzīziyyah), in Damascus 15.40.5
Baalbek (Baʿlabakk, Greek Heliopolis), an ancient settlement and small town in modern-day eastern Lebanon 5.1.8.2; 15.20; 15.37; 15.48; 15.49.2; 15.51.2; 15.51.4; 15.51.10.1(p); 15.51.11 no. 1; 15.52.1
Bāb al-Azaj (the ‘Portico Gate’), a quarter in eastern Baghdad with many markets and large businesses 10.8.4; 10.81.1
Bāb Baradān, one of the gates of Baghdad, located on the Baradān road 8.10.3; 8.25.7
{462}
Bāb al-Barīd, district in Damascus 15.57.1 Bāb al-Farādīs (or Bāb al-Imārah), one of the
seven gates of Old Damascus 15.51.4, 8 Bāb al-Faraj (Gate of Deliverance), the name
of gates in both Damascus and Aleppo 15.18.1; 15.18n
Bāb al-Fatḥ (Victory Gate), in Seville 13.61.3.2; 13.62.3; 13.64.2.1
Bāb al-Gharabah (‘Willow Tree Gate’), in Baghdad 10.64.7
Bāb al-Imārah `see` Bāb al-Farādīs
Bāb al-Jawz (Walnut Tree Gate), in Cordova 13.21.2.1
Bāb Khirbat al-Harrās, gate in Baghdad 10.77.3
Bāb Khurāsān, a gate of al-Manṣūr’s Round City (`Madīnat al-Salām`, the official name of Baghdad), located to the northeast, on the Khorasan road 8.10.3
Bāb al-Maydān `see` al-Maydān Gate
Bāb al-Naqb, a place midway between the Bāb Khurāsān and the Bāb Baradān in Baghdad 8.10.3
Bāb al-Naṣr (Victory Gate), one of the city gates of Damascus 15.20
Bāb al-Raḥmah (the Door/Gate of Mercy), one of the doors of the Golden Gate in Jerusalem 14.49.3
Bāb al-Ṣaghīrah, one of the city gates of Damascus 15.52.2
Bāb Shāʿ, in al-Ruhā 14.54.3
Bāb Tūmā one of the city gates of Damascus 15.3.1.5
Bāb Zuwaylah, a gate in the southern wall of the Fatimid fortifications of Cairo 14.31.6n
Babel (Bābil), ancient Babylon in Mesopot-amia 1.1; 2.1.3; 2.1.4; 4.3.4.1; 10.68.2.2(p); 10.69.3.8(p); 11.13.7.9(p); 15.8.6(p); 15.56.1n
Bābilyūn or Bābalyūn `see` Qaṣr al-Shamaʿ Bactria `see` Balkh
Badajoz (Baṭalyaws) 13.21.1; 13.21.2.2 al-Badandūn, Badhandūn `see` Budandūn Badhdh, a district and fortress of northern
Azerbaijan 8.11n
Badr, a place southwest of Medina, site of a battle between the nascent Muslim com-munity and the Meccans 7.2.3n
Baghdad (Baghdād or Baghdādh, and Ma-dīnat al-Salām, ‘the City of Peace’, the official name of Baghdad) 1.11n; 2.1.1n; 4.1.11.1n; 8.1.1; 8.3.5; 8.3.15n; 8.3.16; 8.3.17; 8.4.2; 8.4.4; 8.4.11n; 8.5.2; 8.5.3; 8.5.4; 8.6n; 8.7; 8.8.2; 8.8.6; 8.10.2n; 8.10.3n; 8.10.4; 8.15.1; 8.18.2; 8.20.5; 8.20.6n; 8.20.10; 8.25.2; 8.25.4; 8.25.7; 8.26.4; 8.26.5; 8.26.8; 8.27.4; 8.29.1; 8.29.5n; 8.29.9; 8.29.22; 8.30.3; 8.33; 9.11n; 9.37n; 9.38n; 9.42; 10.1.4; 10.1.6; 10.1.7; 10.1.9; 10.1.12; 10.2.3.1; 10.2.4 no. 19; 10.3.2.3; 10.3.4; 10.4.2; 10.4.4.1; 10.4.7; 10.4.8; 10.5.4; 10.6; 10.7; 10.8.2; 10.8.3; 10.8.4; 10.8.10; 10.8.11; 10.11; 10.12.1; 10.13.1; 10.13.2; 10.13.3; 10.13.5; 10.14.1; 10.15; 10.16; 10.20; 10.21; 10.22.2; 10.23.1; 10.23.2; 10.26; 10.28; 10.29; 10.31; 10.32; 10.33; 10.37.1; 10.37.3; 10.37.5 no. 40; 10.38.1; 10.51.1; 10.38.2; 10.60; 10.63.2; 10.63.3; 10.64.1; 10.64.3n; 10.64.6; 10.64.7; 10.64.12; 10.64.13; 10.64.16; 10.64.17.1n; 10.64.17.2n; 10.64.17.3; 10.66.1; 10.66.2; 10.66.6; 10.67.5 no. 1n; 10.68.1.1; 10.68.1.3; 10.68.2.1n; 10.67.2.2n; 10.68.2.3n; 10.68.2.4n; 10.68.2.7(p); 10.70; 10.71; 10.72; 10.73; 10.76.2; 10.77.1; 10.77.2; 10.77.3; 10.78; 10.79; 10.81.1; 10.81.2; 10.81.4n; 10.81.5n; 11.5.1; 11.5.2; 11.5.3; 11.5.4; 11.5.6; 11.5.11; 11.5.25,
no. 93; 11.7; 11.8.2; 11.13.8 no. 75; 11.21; 12.2 no. 7n; 11.13.7.9(p); 12.5; 12.6; 13.1.2; 13.19; 13.34.1; 13.49; 13.61.3.1; 14.1; 14.2; 14.22.4.2 no. 19; 14.22.4.3
no. 23; 14.22.5.1n; 14.22.5.1 no. 3n; 14.22.5.1 no. 13; 14.22.5.2 no. 73n; 14.25.9 no. 22n; 14.25.9 no. 25n, 64n, 78n; 14.29.1, 2; 14.31.5; 15.1.1; 15.1.2; 15.1.3.2; 15.1.5 no. 32; 15.3.1; 15.5; 15.8; 15.12; 15.13; 15.17; 15.24; 15.35; 15.36; 15.40; ＡＩＩ.5
Bahnasāʾ, a locality on the road between Malatya and Aleppo 15.40.6
Baḥr al-Ẓulmah `see` Atlantic Ocean Bahrain (al-Baḥrayn) 10.1.3 Bājarmā `see` Beth Garmai
Bājat al-Gharb `see` Beja
Bajjānah `see` Pechina Baʿlabakk `see` Baalbek
{463}
Balad or Balaṭ, a city on the Tigris    8.20.10n; 10.48; 10.66.1; 11.13.7.9(p)
Balansiyah `see` Valencia
Balkh (ancient Bactria), city in Khorasan, in the north of present-day Afghanistan 11.5.9; 11.13.2.1; 11.13.7.9(p)
Baluchistan 14.25.9 no. 42n
Bamyan (Bāmyān), a town in modern-day Afghanistan situated on the ancient silk route 11.19.3
Bānyās canal (Nahr Bānyās), near Damascus 10.75.1
Baʿqūbā, a place north-east of Bagdad, fam-ous for its dates and fruit 10.68.1.4 Baradā, the river on which Damascus stands
7.7.2; 10.69.3.9(p)
Baradān Bridge, one of the bridges over the Tigris in Baghdad 8.25.7
Barāhān `see` Fardajān
Barakhsh `see` Warakhshah
Barqah, the eastern coastal region of modern Libya 7.5.6
Basra (al-Baṣrah), a city on the Shaṭṭ al-ʿArab waterway, southeast of Baghdad (medi-eval Basra is located in Zubayr, 20 km southwest of modern Basra) 1.9; 8.3.14; 8.3.15; 8.3.22; 8.4.3; 8.7; 8.19.1; 8.19.3; 8.26.17n; 8.29.1; 10.1.4; 11.10; 13.34.1; 14.22.1–2; 14.22.4.3 no. 36; 14.22.4.4; 14.22.5.1 no. 8n; 14.22.5.2 no. 80n; 15.8.8
al-Baṣṣah, small town in Northern Palestine 13.58.4.4
Baṭalyaws `see` Badajoz
Bāward (also Abīward), town in Khorasan 11.13.2.11
Bawwān, a valley in southern Persia 15.54(p)
Bayn al-Qaṣrayn (‘between the two palaces’), a square between the eastern and western palaces built by the Fatimids in the centre of Cairo 14.51.2
Bayt Laḥm `see` Bethlehem
Bayt al-Maqdis `see` Jerusalem
Beja (Bājat al-Gharb), city in the Alentejo region (Portugal) 13.78
Beruniy see Bīrūn Beth Garmai (Bājarmā), region around Kirkuk 6.5.1; 9.49n
Bethlehem (Bayt Laḥm) 5.1.8.1 Bīʿat Mār Tūmā (The Church of Saint
Thomas), in Baghdad 10.22.3 Bīʿat Sūq al-Thalāthāʾ (Tuesday Market
Church) `see` Tuesday Market
Bijāyah `see` Bougie
Bilād al-ʿAjam, Lands of the Persians, Greater Persia 11; 10.3.7.3; 11.5.14
Bilād al-Rūm, Lands of the Romans or Byz-antines `see` Anatolia `and` Byzantine
Empire `and` Asia Minor Bilād al-Shām `see` Syria
Bilbays, a town in lower Egypt, northeast of Cairo on the edge of the desert 15.49.4 Biʾr Maymūn, a well in or near Mecca, exact
location uncertain 8.9
Biʾr Zuwaylah, a well or pit near a quarter in Cairo called Ḥārat Zuwaylah, where the caliphal horses were kept 14.31.6 al-Birbāʾ, locality in Upper Egypt, near Pano-polis 2.1.4n
Birkat al-Fīl (‘the Elephant Pond’), the largest of several ponds and marshy areas in Cairo left by the River Nile as it shifted towards the West 14.54.6
Birkat al-Ḥabash (‘the Pond of the Abyssini-ans’), pool or lake on the southern fringes of Fustat 13.58.4.5
Bīrūn, formerly known as Kath and capital of Khwārazm (modern-day Uzbekistan); in 1957 renamed ‘Beruniy’ in honour of al-Bīrūnī 11.15
Bistam, Bisṭām, town in Persia 11.5.12 Bithynia, ancient region in northwestern Asia
Minor 4.1.11.2n; 4.6.2.1
Bokhara (Bukhara, Bukhārā) 11.13.2.1; 11.13.2.3; 11.13.2.9; 11.13.2.11
Bosra (Buṣrā, Bostra), a town in southern Syria near the Jordan border, an import-ant stopover on the ancient caravan route to Mecca 15.51.8
Bostra `see` Bosra
Bougie (Bijāyah), town in modern Algeria 13.66.3
Bruttium, ancient region in southern Italy, the modern Calabria 4.3.4.3n Budandūn (al-Badandūn, Badhandūn, mod-ern Bozantı), a river and town in Anatolia 8.26.17
{464}
al-Buḥayrah, the western province of the Nile delta during the Fatimid period no. 2 14.26.3
Bukhārā `see` Bokhara
Burj, a village near Isfahan    10.68.1.4n; 11.16n
Būrnūs, unidentified; possibly Praesus, an ancient coastal town in eastern Crete, or Portus, the port of Rome 1.8 Būshanj, a town in eastern Persia  8.10.4; 8.27.4
Buṣrā `see` Bosra
Byblos, locality in present-day Lebanon 15.20n
Byzantine Empire (`balad al-Rūm`, ‘land of the Romans’) 8.26.5; 9.12n; 10.3.2.2; 10.23.2; 15.23.1; 15.39
Caesarea (Qaysāriyyah or Qaysariyyah), a coastal town of Palestine 5.1.8.1n; 14.10n
Cairo (al-Qāhirah, Miṣr) [`see also` Old Cairo] 6.3.1n; 8.5.3; 13.51.1; 13.51.2; 13.51.3; 13.58.2.1; 13.58.4.2; 13.86.2; 14.7; 14.14.3; 14.14.7; 14.21 no. 2; 14.22.2; 14.22.3.1–
2; 14.22.5.2 no. 91n; 14.24; 14.25.1; 14.25.3;14.25.9 no. 61; 14.26.3 no. 2; 14.27.3; 14.29.2, 3; 14.31.5, 6, 8; 14.32.1n; 14.33.3n, 4; 14.34.1; 14.36.2; 14.37; 14.39.2n; 14.40.1, 2; 14.41; 14.42.1, 3 no. 3; 14.43.1; 14.44.2, 3; 14.45; 14.47.2; 14.48.2; 14.50; 14.51.2, 4; 14.54.3, 4, 6n, 7, 8, 15; 14.55.1, 2; 14.56.1; 14.57.2; 14.58.3; 15.1.5 no. 32; 15.3.1.2; 15.13; 15.14; 15.29; 15.40.3; 15.40.4; 15.40.5; 15.49.2; 15.49.4; 15.50.3; 15.51.1; 15.53
Campanar, town located north-west of Valen-cia (Spain) 13.87n
Campanario, city in the province of Badajoz (Spain) 13.87n
Candlestick Market `see` Sūq al-Qanādīl Canjáyar (Qanjayrah), city in the region of
Almería (Spain) 13.79
Carmona (Qarmūniyah), a city in al-Andalus 8.19.2n Carrhae `see` Ḥarrān
Carthage, Roman city of North Africa 5.1.8.2n
Carystus, ancient Greek city-state on Euboea 3.4n; 4.1.9.2n
Castle of Barqā (Qalʿat Barqā), unidentified place in Armenia 10.46.4 no. 15
Caulonia, ancient town in southern Italy 4.3.4.3
Cave of Afqah `see` Maghārat Afqah Centuripae, Sicilian town near Mt. Etna
4.3.4.2
Ceuta (Sabtah), a city in North-Africa 14.22.3.2n; 15.41n
Chaeronea, ancient Greek city of Boeotia 4.6.2.2n
Chalcedon, Greek city on the Bosporus 4.1.10.5; 6.1.3 (Council of Chalcedon) Chalcidice, region in northern Greece
4.6.2.1; 4.6.6.2n
Chalcis, ancient Greek city 4.6.6.2 China 8.3.16n; 14.47.1n
Chios, Aegean island 2.1.1n; 5.1.21.1 Chorasmia, Chorezm `see` Khwārazm Church of Saint Theodore (Kanīsat Mār
Thawādrus), Coptic church lying just to the south of Old Cairo 14.10
Circesium (Qarqīsiyā), town in north-eastern Syria 5.1.16.1n
Citium, ancient city in Cyprus  4.1.10.3n; 4.1.10.5n; 4.1.11.3n
City of Peace `see` Baghdad
Cnidos `see` Knidos
Constantine `see` Qusṭanṭīnah Constantinople (al-Qusṭanṭīniyyah)
5.1.8.2; 5.2.15; 6.1.3; 8.26.5; 8.29.6; 9.23n; 10.36; 10.38.4; 10.38.6 no. 10; 13.36.2.2; 14.25.2n
Cordova (Córdoba, Qurṭubah) 1.7n; 4.2; 13.4; 13.5.1; 13.7; 13.9; 13.12; 13.23; 13.27.2; 13.29.2n; 13.34.2; 13.35; 13.36.2.1; 13.36.2.3; 13.36.2.4; 13.36.3 no. 1; 13.38.1; 13.66.1; 13.66.3; 13.81.1; 13.82; 14.39.1n; 15.41
Corinth, Greek city on the Isthmus 5.1.25 Cos `see` Kos
Cranon, ancient Greek city in Thessaly 4.1.5 Crete (Iqrīṭish, Iqrīṭush) 1.1; 1.8n; 1.11; 4.3.4.3
(spelled e]n]k]o) Croton, ancient Greek city in southern Italy 4.3.4.2; 4.3.4.3 Ctesiphon `see` al-Madāʾin
Cyprus 4.1.10.1n; 4.1.10.2n; 5.1.21.1
{465}
Dabarkī (or Divrigi), small town and district of Sivas Province in modern-day Turkey 15.40.6
al-Dakhwāriyyah College, medical school in Damascus 15.50.5n; 15.57.1
Damascus (Dimashq or al-Shām, which may also refer to Greater Syria; Jilliq, properly a site in the Ghūṭah, sometimes stands for Damascus, esp. in poetry) 1.4n; 2.1.3n; 4.8; 7.5.1; 7.5.3; 7.5.6; 7.7.1; 7.7.2; 7.8.3; 8.5.3; 8.26.14; 8.29.22n; 10.38.4; 10.64.13; 10.69.3.9(p, Jilliq); 10.69.3.10(p, Jilliq); 10.69.4 no. 4; 10.75.1; 10.75.2; 11.13.7.9(p, Jilliq); 13.4; 14.3; 14.22.2n; 14.31.5; 14.32.2; 14.36.2; 14.38.1n; 14.39.1n; 14.42.1; 14.42.3 nos. 3, 4; 14.44.2; 14.49.2n; 14.50; 14.51.2; 14.54.2; 14.54.3; 14.54.9; 14.55.3n; 14.56.1, 2; 14.57.2; 14.58.2; 14.58.3; 15.1.1; 15.1.1.1; 15.1.1.2; 15.1.5
no. 32; 15.3.1; 15.3.1.1; 15.3.1.2; 15.3.1.5; 15.3.1.6; 15.8; 15.9; 15.10; 15.11; 15.12; 15.13; 15.14; 15.15; 15.17 (Dimashq and Jilliq); 15.18.1; 15.18.1.1; 15.18.1.2; 15.19; 15.20; 15.21; 15.22; 15.23.1; 15.23.2.1; 15.23.2.2; 15.23.3; 15.23.4.1; 15.23.4.2; 15.24; 15.27; 15.29; 15.30; 15.31.1; 15.32; 15.33; 15.34; 15.35; 15.36.1; 15.37.1; 15.37.3; 15.37.4; 15.38; 15.39; 15.40.1; 15.42; 15.43; 15.44; 15.45; 15.46; 15.47.2.1(p); 15.48; 15.49.1; 15.49.2; 15.49.3; 15.49.6; 15.50.1; 15.50.2; 15.50.3; 15.50.5; 15.50.6(p); 15.50.7
no. 3; 15.51.1; 15.51.2; 15.51.3; 15.51.4; 15.51.5; 15.51.6; 15.51.7; 15.51.8; 15.52.1; 15.53; 15.54 (Dimashq and Jilliq); 15.56.1; 15.57.1; 15.58; 15.59; 15.60.1; ＡＩ.1; ＡＩＩ.15
Damascus Gate (Bāb al-Shām), in Baghdad 10.4.6
Damāwand `see` Dunbāwand Damietta (Dimyāṭ), a port in Egypt   10.61; 14.49.2; 14.54.9; 14.54.10; 14.54.15; 15.45.2 Dāniyah `see` Dénia
Daqūqāʾ, a town in the Jazīrah province of modern Iraq, on the main road between Baghdad and Mosul 8.5.2
Dār al-Dhahab (Golden House), a law college (kacnaoag) in Baghdad 15.40.2
Dār al-Ḥijārah, area in Damascus 15.8.1
Dār Ibn al-Zaʿfarānī (the House of Ibn al-Zaʿfarānī), in al-Ruhā 14.54.3
Dār al-Rūm, the Christian quarter of Bagh-dad 8.5.2; 8.25.2
Dārā, fortress town of northern Mesopot-amia 5.1.16.1
Darb al-Fālūdhaj (Sweetmeats Alley), in Baghdad 15.40.2
Daybul, seaport of Sind 8.21.4n Daylam, highlands in Iran close to the
Caspian Sea, also the name of its people 10.4.9 no. 8; 11.13.7.9(p) (spelled al-Daylamān)
Dayr al-ʿAdhārā, a convent near the town of al-ʿAlth 8.25.7n
Dayr al-ʿAlth, a convent near the town of al-ʿAlth 8.25.7n
Dayr Banī l-Ṣaqr, unidentified locality not far from Baghdad or Sāmarrā 8.20.5
Dayr Durtā `see` Durtā
Dayr al-Jamājim, a Nestorian monastery in central Iraq 7.9.4n
Dayr al-Khandaq, monastery north of Cairo 14.50; 14.51.4
Dayr Qunnā, a Nestorian monastery on the Tigris S. of Baghdad 10.21
Dayr al-Quṣayr, the Monastery of Saint Arsenius near the town of Ṭurā, south of Cairo 14.15
Dayr al-Sīq, monastery south of Jerusalem 15.43.2
Delos, Greek island 4.3.4.1
Dénia (Dāniyah), town in al-Andalus 13.7; 13.58.1; 13.60.2
Dezful, city in western Iran 8.1.1n
Dhāt al-Ajraʿ (the sandy tract), unidentified desert location 11.13.7.1(p)
Dhū Murār, unidentified place   7.5.4(p)
Dihistān 11.13.2.11
Dijlah `see` Tigris
Dimashq `see` Damascus
Dimyāṭ `see` Damietta
Diospolis, ancient city in Egypt    4.3.4.2
Divrigi `see` Dabarkī
Diyār Bakr (Diyarbakır), city in Eastern Anatolia 8.6n; 10.1n; 10.13.3n; 10.38.4; 11.13.7.9(p); 11.21; 14.50n; 14.54.3n; 15.17n; 15.18n; 15.22n; 15.46n
{466}
Diyār Muḍar, region in northern Mesopot-amia 14.50n; 15.17n
Diyār Rabīʿah 10.38.4; 11.13.7.9(p) Dorylaeum, ancient Greek city in Phrygia
6.1.3
Dunaysir, town (now ruins) south-west of the city of Mārdīn in modern-day Turkey 15.58
Dunbāwand (or Damāwand), a mountain in northern Persia 8.8.4
Durtā, place of a monastery in Iraq 10.51.6(p)
Ecbatana `see` Hamadan
Edessa `see` al-Ruhā
Egypt (Miṣr; al-Diyār al-Miṣriyyah) `see` also
Old Cairo 1.3; 1.5; 1.7n; 1.10n; 2.1.3; 2.1.4; 4.3; 4.3.4.2; 4.5.2; 5.1.16.1; 5.1.37 no. 115; 8.5.3; 6.1.2; 7.4n; 7.5.6; 8.18.3; 8.21.4; 8.26.9; 10.1.7; 10.38.2; 10.38.3; 10.38.4; 11.13.7.9; 11.20; 12.6; 13.2.1; 13.2.2.1; 13.3.4 no. 20; 13.34.1; 13.51.1; 13.58.2.1; 13.58.2.1; 13.58.4.5; 13.58.5
no. 1; 13.59.4 no. 17; 13.60.2; 13.86.1; 14.1; 14.2; 14.3; 14.4.1; 14.4.4; 14.10; 14.11; 14.13; 14.14.1; 14.14.3; 14.14.7; 14.17; 14.14.8 no. 4; 14.15; 14.18; 14.21n; 14.22.1–2; 14.22.3.1; 14.22.5.2 no. 91; 14.23.1–2; 14.25.1; 14.25.3; 14.25.9 nos. 15, 61, 100; 14.26.1–2; 14.27.1, 2, 4 nos. 2, 4; 14.28; 14.29.1, 2, 4 nos. 1, 4; 14.31.3n, 4n, 5.6n; 14.32.2; 14.32.3; 14.32.4; 14.33.3n; 14.35n; 14.36.1, 2; 14.37; 14.39.1, 2; 14.40.2; 14.42.1; 14.43.2n; 14.43.3 no. 1; 14.44.2; 14.45n; 14.46; 14.47.1, 2; 14.48.2; 14.49.1, 2; 14.50; 14.51.1, 2n; 14.53; 14.54.2, 3; 14.54.4n; 14.54.9; 14.54.12n; 14.54.13; 14.55.1n; 14.55.3n; 14.56.1n; 14.56.3; 14.57.1, 2; 14.58.3; 15.1.1.2; 15.24; 15.25; 15.31.1; 15.31.2; 15.31.3; 15.31.4; 15.32; 15.33; 15.38; 15.40.1; 15.40.2; 15.40.9
nos. 57, 58, 59; 15.41; 15.45; 15.49; 15.50.3; 15.51.1; 15.54; 15.58; ＡＩ.3; ＡＩＩ.11; ＡＩＩ.16
Egyptian provinces (al-Diyār al-Miṣriyyah) 14.2; 14.14.3; 14.22.2
Elea (Velia), ancient Greek city on the Tyrrhenian coast of Italy 3.4n; 4.1.11.3n
Elephant Pond `see` Birkat al-Fīl
Elvira, Roman city in today’s province of Granada (Spain) 13.29.2n
Emesa, the modern Homs (Ḥimṣ) in Syria 4.1.10.2n; 4.1.11.2
Ephesus 4.1.10.2n; 4.1.11.2n; 4.3.4.1; 6.1.3 (Robber Council of); 8.29.22n
Epidaurus (Fīdārūs and Qindārūs), in the Peloponnese 1.6; 2.1.2n; 2.1.6.4n
Epirus, ancient Greek state in the western Balkans 14.25.9 no. 34n
Erbil (or Arbil or Irbil), city in northern Iraq, east of Mosul 15.24
Eresos, ancient Greek city on Lesbos 15.1.2 Erzerum, Erzurum (Arzan al-Rūm), city in Anatolia, modern-day Turkey 15.40.5; 15.40.6
Erzinjan (Arzanjān), city in Anatolia, modern-day Turkey 15.40.5; 15.40.6; 15.40.9 nos. 96, 160
Etruria – land of Etruscans, Tyrrhenia 1.1n Euphrates (al-Furāt), one of the two great
rivers of Mesopotamia 8.26.12n; 11.13.7.9(p)
Fārāb (or Farāb; modern Otrar or Utrar), town in Khorasan now southern Kaza-khstan 15.1
Faramā (Greek Pelusium), strategic city on the eastern Delta 5.1.21.1; 14.4.1
Fardajān, also known as Barāhān, a fortress near Hamadān 11.13.3.7; 11.13.8 nos. 16, 17,
18
Farghāmus `see` Pergamum
Farghānā, region in eastern Transoxiana 8.20.5n
Fārs `see` Persia
Fās `see` Fez
Fasā, town in Fars Province of Persia 11.10
Fayd, a town in the Ḥijāz, at halfway point on the pilgrimage route between Iraq and Mecca 8.9
Fayyum (al-Fayyūm) – a large district in central Egypt that had a large Christian population 9.45
Feltmakers’ Market (al-Labbādīn), in Damas-cus 15.8.1; 15.10; 15.11.1
Fez (Fās), city in Morocco 13.59.3; 13.74; 14.39.2n; 15.41
{467}
Fīdārūs `see` Epidaurus
Filasṭīn `see` Palestine
Fīlmān, unidentified locality; possibly cor-ruption of Fīlān (an eastern Caucasian region close to the western coasts of the Caspian) 15.20
Fīrūzkūh, a fortified city in the province of Ghūr in Central Afghanistan, capital of the senior branch of the Ghūrid sultans 11.19.3
al-Furāt `see` Euphrates
Fustat (al-Fusṭāṭ; Old Cairo, Miṣr al-ʿAtīqah; Miṣr al-Qadīmah), the first Muslim cap-ital of Egypt 10.38.3; 10.38.4; 10.38.6
no. 6; 13.34.1; 14.2; 14.3; 14.4.1; 14.11; 14.12; 14.15n; 14.14.7; 14.25.3; 14.32.1; 14.32.3; 14.33.1n; 14.38.1; 14.39.2; 14, 40.1
Gate of Exile `see` Bāb al-Ghurbah Gate of Victory `see` Bāb al-Fatḥ Gaza (Ghazzah), town in Palestine  14.49.3n
Gerasa, the modern Jerash, Jordan   4.1.11.2; 4.6.1
Ghallah Lane (Darb al-Ghallah), in Baghdad 10.77.3 Gharnāṭah `see` Granada
Ghaznah, a town in eastern Afghanistan, now called Ghazni 11.15 no. 13
Ghazzah `see` Gaza
Ghūr, province of Central Afghanistan in medieval times 11.19.3n
al-Ghūṭah, the fertile land south and east of Damascus 15.54n
al-Ghuwayr, name of several locations in Ara-bia 13.63.8.1(p)
Giza (al-Jīzah), a town on the west bank of the Nile 14.25.3; 14.54.8 Gondēshāpūr (Jundaysābūr), ruins of
ancient city to the southeast of Dizfūl in southwest Iran 7.1.1; 8.1.1; 8.1.2; 8.2; 8.16; 9.1n; 9.16n; 8.3.22; 8.4.2; 8.25.1; 8.25.2; 8.25.4; 8.25.8; 8.29.1; 8.29.2; 8.37; 9.16n; 9.26n; 9.39; 11.1; 12.2 no. 7n
Granada (Gharnāṭah), city in al-Andalus 13.6.1.2; 13.59.3; 13.70; 13.74; 13.75
the Great Hospital (al-Bīmāristān al-Kabīr) `see` Nūri Hospital
Greece (bilād al-Yūnāniyyīn, Yūnān) 4.2; 4.3.1; 4.3.6.2 (`ʾ-l-ā-dh-ā`, i.e. Hellas)
Green Sea (al-Baḥr al-Akhḍār) `see` Mediter-ranean
Gūn Gunbad, a gate and quarter in Isfahan 11.13.3.9; 11.13.4
Gurgān `see` Jurjān
Gurgānj (Kurkānj, al-Jurjāniyyah)   11.13.2.5; 11.13.2.11; 11.13.8 no. 31
Hadramaut (Ḥaḍramawt) 10.1.3
Hajar, in eastern Arabia 15.49.6.1(p) Ḥakamān, a town near Basra, Iraq 8.19.3 Ḥalab `see` Aleppo
Ḥallāwiyyah Law College (al-Madrasah al-Ḥallāwiyyah), in Aleppo 15.18.1.3 Hama (Ḥamāh), city in Syria 15.22; 15.22 no. 6; 15.24; 15.46.3; 15.54; 15.55
Hamadan (Hamadhān, modern Hamadān, ancient Ecbatana), city in Persia 8.10.2; 10.75.1; 11.13.3.3, 11.13.3.4; 11.13.3.6; 11.13.3.8; 11.13.3.9; 11.13.3.11; 11.13.3.19; 11.13.4; 11.13.8 nos. 2, 7, 19, 75, 76, 88; 11.19.2; 15.17
Ḥammām al-Faʾr (the Bathhouse of the Mouse), in Fustat 14.15
al-Ḥanbaliyyah Law College (al-Madrasah al-Ḥanbaliyyah), in Damascus 15.35
al-Ḥaram (the Holy Precinct, in Mecca) 15.8.2(p)
al-Ḥarasiyyāt (or al-Ḥarashiyyāt? reading uncertain), estates in Iraq 10.10.3
Harāt `see` Herat
al-Ḥarbiyyah, a quarter by the Ḥarb gate in Baghdad 10.16
Harpūt `see` Kharpūt
Ḥarrān, an ancient town (Carrhae) of Upper Mesopotamia, in the modern Turkish province of Diyarbakır 1.5n; 2.1.4n; 4.1.11.2; 7.4; 8.29.6n; 9.35n; 10.3.1; 10.3.2.2; 10.3.10; 13.9; 15.1; 15.47.1 Harthamah’s Camp, a district in the eastern
part of Baghdad 8.10.3
al-Ḥasakah, city and governorate in modern Syria 8.29.3n; 9.25n
Hatra (Haṭrā, Hāṭrā), a place near Samarra (not to be confused with ancient Hatra/al-Ḥaḍr near Mosul) 10.68.2.2n Ḥawrān (Hauran or Houran), a volcanic plat-eau in southwestern Syria extending into
{468}
the northwestern corner of modern-day Jordan 10.83.4; 15.27; 15.27n; 15.57.1 Ḥazzah, a settlement west of Irbil (Arbil), in
Iraq 9.35n
Hejaz `see` al-Ḥijāz
Heliopolis `see` ʿAyn Shams `and` Baalbek Heraclea, ancient city in what is now Turkey
4.3.4.1
Herat (Harāt), a city in modern-day Afgh-anistan 8.10.4; 11.19.2; 11.19.3; 11.19.5; 11.19.6.1; 11.23
al-Ḥijāz (Hijaz, Hejaz), a region in the west-ern Arabian Peninsula, Najd to the east and Tihāmah to the west 7.5.2; 8.9; 11.13.7.9(p); 15.8.12(p)
al-Ḥillah, town in Iraq 10.64.19.13n
Ḥimṣ `see` Homs
Ḥimyar, ancient kingdom of south-west Ara-bia 15.11.2n
al-Hind `see` India
Ḥīnī (modern Hani), a town near the city of Diyarbakır in eastern Anatolia 10.75.2; 15.46.3
al-Ḥīrah, a town on the Euphrates, southwest of the modern Najaf, in Iraq 8.3.7; 8.3.16; 8.9; 8.29.2; 8.29.11n; 15.49.6.1n
Ḥiṣn al-Faraj (Victory Castle, Aznalfarache), in Seville 13.63.5
al-Ḥiyār (or Ḥiyār Banī l-Qaʿqāʿ), probably in northern Syria 8.13.2
the Holy Precinct `see` al-Ḥaram
Homs (Ḥimṣ), a city in Syria 4.1.1n; 10.68.2.7
(p); 15.23.4.1; 15.31.1; 15.42; 15.56.1 Houran `see` Ḥawrān
the House of Ibn al-Zaʿfarānī `see` Dār Ibn al-Zaʿfarānī
al-Ḥuwayzah, place in Khuzistan 10.68.2.1n
Hymettus, a mountain in Attica  4.3
Ibiza (Yābisa) 13.36.2.3n
Īdhaj (also known as Māl-i Amīr), city in western Persia 11.13.3.18
Ifrīqiyah, area that comprises today’s Tunisia, Western Libya and Eastern Algeria 13.1.2; 13.2.1; 13.3.2.1; 13.3.2.2; 13.66.3; 13.85
al-Īghārān, two fiefs in western Persia 10.68.1.4
Īlāq, town near Nishapur    11.14n
Īliyāʾ `see` Jerusalem
Imros, Greek Aegean island 4.3.4.1 ʿIndān, unidentified village near Aleppo(?)
15.15
India (al-Hind) 1.1; 1.5; 2.1.3; 8.21.4; 11.2; 11.9.2.1(p); 12.1; 12.2; 12.3; 12.4; 12.5; 12.6; 13.6.1.1 no. 6; 13.6.2 no. 7
Indian Ocean, Ocean 14.25.9 no. 42n
Indus, river `see` Mihrān
Ionia (Yūnān), ancient Greek city and islands states of the eastern Aegean and its sea-board 2.1.1n
al-ʿIqāb `see` Navas de Tolosa
Iqrīṭīsh, Iqrīṭush `see` Crete
Iraq (al-ʿIrāq), the southern part of modern Iraq 1.5; 7.1.1n; 7.8.3; 7.9.1n; 8.5.2; 8.29.3; 9.32n; 9.44; 10 `passim`; 11.13.7.9(p); 12.2n; 12.5; 12.6; 13.86.1; 14.1; 14.26.2; 14.43.3 no. 1; ＡＩＩ.5
Irbil `see` Erbil
ʿĪsābādh, a palace and pleasure ground built by the caliph al-Mahdī on the eastern side of Baghdad 8.10.3
Isfahan (Iṣfahān), city in Persia/Iran, south of Tehran 8.10.4n; 8.20.11; 10.67.1; 11.13.3.9, 10, 11, 17, 18; 11.13.4; 11.13.8 nos. 12, 13, 21, 33, 53; 15.13
al-Iskandariyyah `see` Alexandria Istanbul 8.29.22n; 9.19n; `see also` Con-stantinople
al-Ītākhīyyah `see` Dayr Banī l-Ṣaqr Italy 4.3.4.1; 4.3.4.2; 4.3.4.3
al-Jabal `see` al-Jibāl
Jabal Tayyiʾ, an upland region in northern Arabia encompassing Mt. Ajaʾ and Mt. Salmā 8.10.4
Jaʿbar, a fortress in the mediaeval town of al-Raqqah in present day Syria  14.50; 14.51.2; 14.54.3; 15.32
Jaén ( Jayyān), city in Andalusia   15.45.1n
Jaʿfarī Canal, a canal in Samarra   10.1.7
Jājarm, town in Khorasan 11.13.2.11 al-Janādil, the ‘cataracts’ of the River Nile
14.22.3.1
Jarkh Band, place in Armenia or Azerbaijan 10.79
Játiva (Shāṭibah), town in eastern al-Andalus 13.61.3.1n
Jayrūn, a gate in Damascus 15.8.1; 15.29n
{469}
al-Jāzir, unidentified location 11.13.7.9(p) (`see also` Khāzir)
al-Jazīrah, northern Mesopotamia 5.1.37
no. 115; 8.18.2; 10.38.4; 13.9 al-Jazīrah (Jazīrat Miṣr), the island of
Rawḍah (Roda) in the River Nile near Cairo 14.31.6
Jazīrat al-ʿArab, the Arabian Peninsula 8.18.2n
Jazīrat ibn ʿUmar (later, Gazarta), modern-day Cizre in southeastern Turkey    15.36.1; 15.36.1.4
Jazīrat al-Shuqar `see` Alzira
Jerusalem (al-Quds, Bayt al-Muqaddas, Bayt al-Maqdīs, Īliyāʾ) 5.1.8.2; 5.1.21.2; 8.5.3; 10.75.1; 14.10; 14.14.1–3; 14.14.6; 14.49.1; 14.49.2–4; 14.56.1; 15.11.2.1(p); 15.11.3 no. 7; 15.23.2.1; 15.31.4; 15.31.6 no. 11n; 15.40.3; 15.40.5; 15.40.9 no. 59; 15.43.2; 15.45.1; 15.45.2; 15.51.1
al-Jibāl (‘the Mountains’, i.e. the Zagros Mountains; also al-Jabal), region in west-ern Persia, ancient Media 8.20.11n; 9.26.n; 11.5.22; 11.6n; 11.13.3.1
Jīlān (or al-Jīlān), a region in Tabaristan, near the southern coasts of the Caspian Sea 8.5.2n; 8.20.11n; 15.20
Jilliq `see` Damascus
al-Jīzah `see` Giza
Jordan, river 5.1.8.1
Jordan, country 14.50n
Jundaysābūr `see` Gondēshāpūr
Jurjān (Gurgān) 11.13.2.11; 11.13.3.1; 11.13.3.15; 11.13.8 nos. 9, 10, 22 al-Jurjāniyyah `see` Gurgānj
Jūrqab, a district near Shīrāz in Persia/mod-ern Iran 8.5.2
al-Kaʿbah, the Kaaba, Bayt Allāh (‘God’s House’) 1.11n; 10.62.3(p); 10.67.4.1n; 15.46.2(p)
Kairouan (al-Qayrawān), a holy city in mod-ern Tunisia 1.7n; 13.1.2; 13.2.1; 13.3.1; 13.3.2.1; 13.3.2.3; 13.25; 13.60.2
Kamākh (or Kemah), a fortress near the city of Erzerum, modern-day Turkey 15.40.6
Kanaan (Kanʿān) 11.13.7.9(p)
Kanīsat Mār Thawādrus `see` Church of Saint
Theodore Karaj (al-Karaj, Karaj Abī Dulaf), a city in the Jibāl province of Persia 10.68.1.4n; 11.13.3.18. `See also` al-Īghārān
Karak (al-Karak), a fortress situated to the east of the Dead Sea 1.11; 14.50; 14.51.2; 14.52; 14.53; 15.21; 15.23.2.2; 15.42; 15.44; 15.45; 15.51.3; 15.60.1
Karkh (al-Karkh), a district of Baghdad 9.11; 9.42; 10.76.2
Karkh Guddan, ancient city near the modern Iraq-Iran border 9.42n
Kārūn (or Dujayl, the ‘small Tigris’), river in Khuzestan 14.22.4.3n
Kashkar (or Kaskar), an ancient town on the west bank of the Tigris, opposite Wāsiṭ 8.8.6n; 8.10.1; 8.13.3n Kath `see` Bīrūn
Khabūshān, town near Nishapur 14.36.2n al-Khandaq (lit. ‘the moat’, ‘the trench’), a
village near New Cairo (al-Qāhirah) 14.22.3.1
Khānqāh al-Sumaysāṭī, in Damascus 14.36.2
al-Kharibah (lit. ‘the site of ruins’), an unidentified Egyptian locality 14.54.3
Kharmaythan, a district of Bukhara 11.13.2.1 Kharpūt (or Harpūt, Kharberd, Kharpert; Arabic Khartabirt), a town north of the city of Diyarbakir, the modern the town of Elāzij in eastern Turkey 15.18 no. 2; 15.18n
al-Khaṭṭ, place in eastern Arabia famous for its lances 10.68.2.2(p); 13.58.4.4(p); 15.8.5(p)
Khātūn Mosque (Masjid Khātūn), in Damas-cus 15.33
al-Khawarnaq, legendary Sasanian palace in southern Iraq 15.54(p)
Khaybar, oasis c. 95 miles north of Medina 10.68.2.1(p); 10.69.3.12(p)
al-Khayf, name of several places in the Hijaz, including one at Minā near Mecca 7.1.6n; 10.81.5(p)
Khāzir or Khāzar, river between Irbil and Mosul 11.13.7.9(n)
Khilāṭ (modern Ahlat), a town on the west bank of Lake Van in Asia Minor 10.81.2; 11.13.7.9(p); 15.46.3
Khiva `see` Khwārazm
{470}
Khorasan, the eastern part of Persia, includ-ing parts of what are today Central Asia and Afghanistan 7.7.2n; 8.3.7; 8.3.17; 8.10.2n; 8.10.4n; 8.11n; 8.18.2; 8.19.3n; 8.20.11n; 8.27.4n; 8.29.2n; 9.7n; 9.40n; 10.4.2; 10.9.1; 11.5.9; 11.5.12; 11.5.14; 11.5.25 nos. 35n, 90; 11.12; 11.13.2.11; 11.13.3.13; 11.13.7.9(p); 15.1.1; 15.29; 15.40.2
Khujanda, city in Transoxiana 8.11n Khūnaj, town near Zanjān in Azerbaijan
14.48.n
Khurasan, Khurāsān `see` Khorasan Khusrawshāh (modern Khosrow Shahr), a
small settlement west of Tabrīz in Persia 15.21
Khuwayy, a town in Azerbaijan 15.19 Khuzestan (Khūzistān), a province in the southwest of Iran, between the Zagros
mountains and the Persian Gulf 8.3.10n; 8.20.11n; 8.26.9; 9.26; 9.37; 10.68.2.1n; 14.22.4.3n; 14.22.5.1 no. 8n
Khwārazm (Khuwārizm, Khwārizm, Khorezm, Chorasmia), a city in the Xorazm province of present-day Uzbek-istan; modern name Khiva 11.13.3.14; 11.13.7.9(p); 11.15; 11.19.6.1
Kirmān, a province of Persia, lying south of Khorasan 8.5.2; 8.20.5n; 10.38.4; 10.64.17.2(p)
Kirmānshāh (Qarmīsīn) 11.13.3.4 Knidos (or Cnidos) – island/peninsula in
Mediterranean 1.1; 4.1.1; 3.1.n
Kos (or Cos)– Greek island state of the Dodecanese 1.1; 1.6; 2.1.5; 3.5n; 3.6n; 4.1.1; 4.1.2; 4.1.10.1n
Kufa (al-Kūfah), town in Iraq, near present-day Najaf 8.3.7n; 8.3.14n; 8.8.3n; 8.10.4n; 8.18.1; 8.18.2; 8.20.6n; 8.26.13; 8.29.2; 10.1.2
al-Kūlam, a town in India, now the port of Quilon in Kerala 14.47.1
Kurkānj see Gurgānj Kūthā, place of a monastery near Baghdad 10.51.6n
al-Labbādīn `see` Feltmakers’ Market al-Lādhiqiyyah `see` Latakiyah
Laʿlaʿ, a place of uncertain location 15.51.10.2(p)
Laribus or Lorbeus (al-Arīs), city in Libya 13.2.2.1
Latakiyah (al-Lādhiqiyyah), the principal port of in Syria 15.15; 15.18n
Lemnos, Aegean island 4.3.4.1; 5.1.21.1n Libn, a place said to be in China (error for
Yemen?) 8.3.16n Libya 4.3.2
al-Liwā, desert location in Arabia 15.43.3(p) Locris, region in ancient Greece 4.3.4.3; 4.5.2n
Lower Mesopotamia, southern Iraq 1.1n Lucena (al-Yussānah), city in today’s
province of Cordoba (Spain) 13.66.3
al-Maʿarrah (or Maʿarrat al-Nuʿmān), a city in northwestern Syria 15.12; 15.55
Macedon (Macedonia), ancient kingdom on the periphery of Greece 4.1.10.2n; 4.6.2.1
al-Madāʾīn, an ancient town (Ctesiphon) 20
miles southwest of Baghdad 7.1.2n; 8.3.20; 8.20.6n; 8.26.8; 10.80
al-Madīnah `see` Medina
Madīnat al-Salām `see` Baghdad Madīnat al-Zahrāʾ caliphal city on
the outskirts of Cordova 13.19.1; 13.19.2.1
al-Madrasah al-ʿĀdiliyyah `see` al-ʿĀdiliyyah Law College
al-Madrasah al-Amīniyyah `see` al-Amīniyyah Law College
al-Madrasah al-ʿAzīziyyah `see` al-ʿAzīziyyah Law College
al-Madrasah al-Dakhwāriyyah `see` al-Dakhwāriyyah College
al-Madrasah al-Ḥallāwiyyah `see` al-Ḥallāwiy-yah Law College
al-Madrasah al-Ḥanbaliyyah `see` al-Ḥanbaliy-yah Law College
al-Madrasah al-Niẓāmiyyah `see` al-Niẓāmiy-yah Law College
al-Madrasah al-Qilījiyyah `see` al-Qilījiyyah Law College
Madrasat Ibn Muhājir (Law College of Ibn Muhājir), in Mosul 15.40.3
Madrid (Majrīṭ) 13.5n
Maghārat Aqfah (the Cave of Aqfah), village and cave between the villages of Baal-{471}
bek and Byblos, northeast of modern-day Beirut 15.20
Maghrib (al-Maghrib, ‘the West’), North Africa excluding Egypt 10.38.4; 11.20; 11.21; 13.1.2, 13.2.2.1; 13.61.4 no. 9; 14.14.3; 14.27.1; 14.39.2; 14.58.1; 15.41; 15.50.6; 15.53
Magnesia, ancient Greek city 4.3.4.1 al-Maḥallah, a provincial town in Egypt,
probably al-Maḥallah al-Kubrā 14.42.1 al-Maḥallah al-Kubrā, town in the Delta,
Egypt 14.42.2n
Mahdia (al-Mahdiyyah), city in the coast of Tunisia 13.58.4.1; 13.58.4.2; 13.64.2.1 Makkah `see` Mecca
Makrān (or Mukrān), the coastal region of southern Baluchistan that today is the political boundary between Pakistan and Iran 14.25.9 no. 42
Málaga (Mālaqah), city in al-Andalus 14.25.4
Malatya (Malaṭyah), a city in the eastern Anatolia region of Turkey 15.40.6 Malāzkird (or Mantzikert; modern Malaz-girt), a town a little north of Khilāṭ in Asia
Minor 15.46.3
Manbij, city northeast of Aleppo 14.49.2n al-Manṣūr, name of the camp of Saladin on
the outskirts of Acre 15.11.2
Manṣūrī Hospital (Bīmāristān al-Manṣūrī), established in Cairo in 683/1285    ＡＩ.2; ＡＩ.3
Mantzikert `see` Malāzgird
Maqābir al-shuyūkh (‘Cemetery of the Vener-able Men’), in Marrakesh 13.63.3 Maʿqil Canal (Nahr Maʿqil), in Basra
15.8.8(p)
Mar Saba, monastery in Palestine    9.23n
Maragheh (Marāghah), a city on the river Sufi Chay in the Azerbaijan province of Iran, famous for an early observatory 11.19.1; 11.21; 15.60.1n
Marand, a city in the modern-day east Azerbaijan Province, Iran 11.19.2 al-Marāwizah, a quarter in Baghdad contigu-ous with al-Ḥarbiyyah where the people
of Marv used to dwell 10.20n
Mardē `see` Māridīn
Māridīn (Mārdīn), city of northern Mesopot-amia 5.1.16.1n; 15.17n; 15.58; 10.75.1; 10.75.2; 10.81.2; 15.58.5
al-Mariyyah `see` Almería
Marj al-Ṣuffar, a large plain south of Damas-cus, Syria 15.40.4; 15.50.3 Marrakesh (Marrākush), city in Morocco
13.61.4 no. 9; 13.63.3; 13.64.2.1; 13.66.3n; 13.66.5; 13.68.3; 13.70; 13.71; 13.72; 13.73; 13.78; 13.87
Marw `see` Merv
Mary `see` Merv
Mashhad, a city in Iran 8.10.4n; 8.29.2n al-Maṣīr, a district within the city of Samarra
8.20.5
Maṣīṣ (perhaps Mases in the Argolid) 4.1.11.2 Masjid `see` Mosque
Maṣṣīṣā `see` Mopsuestina
Mā warāʾ al-Nahr `see` Transoxiana al-Mawṣil `see` Mosul
al-Maydān Gate (Bāb al-Maydān), in Mosul 10.81.4
Mayyāfāriqīn (Martyropolis; modern Silvan), settlement east of the city of Diyarbakir in eastern Anatolia (now in Turkey) 8.5.4; 8.5.5; 8.6; 10.13.3; 10.41; 10.54.1; 10.54.2; 15.17n; 15.18.1.4; 15.19; 15.46.3; 15.46.3.9(p); 15.46.4 no. 3
Mazdākhān or al-Mazdaqān, a village near al-Rayy 11.19.6.1
Mecca (Makkah) 7.1.1; 7.1.6n; 7.2.1; 7.2.3n; 7.5.3; 7.5.4; 7.6; 8.3.8; 8.4.11n; 8.8.3n; 8.9; 10.62.3(p); 10.64.19.8n; 15.24; 15.40.4; 15.51.5; 15.51n
Media `see` al-Jibāl
Medina (al-Madīnah) 7.2.1n; 7.2.3n; 7.4n; 7.5.3n; 7.5.5n; 8.4.11n; 8.18.1n; 8.18.2n; 11.16 no. 1.38; 15.46n
Medina Sidonia `see` Sidonia Mediterranean Sea 5.1. 21.1 (‘Green Sea’); 8.21.4 (‘Roman Sea’); 8.21.4; 13.3.2.1; 13.4n; 14.3n
Memphis, city in ancient Egypt 2.1.3; 4.3.4.2 Mendes, ancient city in the Nile delta
4.5.1n; 4.5.4n
Merv (or Merw, Marw), a medieval city in present-day Turkmenistan, now called Mary 8.10.4; 10.20n; 15.1.2; 15.1.3; 15.13n Mesopotamia 1.5n; `see also` al-Jazīrah
{472}
Metapontum, ancient Greek city in southern Italy 4.3.4.3
Methone, ancient city in Thrace 4.6.2.1 Mihrān, the River Indus 8.21.2n; 8.21.3; 8.21.4
Miletus, ancient Greek city on the western coast of Asia Minor 4.3.4.1
Minā, a place near Mecca 7.1.6n
Miṣr `see` Egypt and Cairo
Miṣr al-ʿAtīqah, Miṣr al-Qadīmah `see` Fustat Monastery `see` Dayr
Monastir (al-Munastīr), city on the coast of Tunisia 13.3.2.1; 13.58.4.1
Mopsuestia (Maṣṣīṣā), city of Cilicia in south-ern Anatolia 4.1.11.2
Mosque of al-Ḥājib Luʾluʾ (Masjid al-Ḥājib Luʾluʾ), in Cairo 15.40.3
Mosque of al-Khabūshānī (Masjid al-Khabūshānī), in Damascus 14.36.2 Mosul (al-Mawṣil), a city in northern Iraq on
the west bank of the Tigris near ancient Nineveh 1.11n; 8.5.4; 9.35; 10.38.4; 10.46.2; 10.47; 10.49; 10.63.2; 10.68.1.4; 10.69.4 no. 5n; 10.81.1; 10.81.2; 10.81.4; 10.81.6; 10.82; 10.83.1; 10.83.2; 10.83.3; 10.83.4; 11.13.7.9(p); 11.21; 14.26.3 no. 2n; 15.4; 15.5; 15.24; 15.40.1; 15.40.3
Mount Ajaʾ, a mountain in the Jabal Ṭayyiʾ region 8.10.4n
Mount Ḥaḍan, in Arabia 7.5.6(p) Mount Lebanon, a mountain range in
Lebanon 15.45.4
Mount Qāsiyūn, a mountain overlooking Damascus 15.13; 15.21; 15.34; 15.36.1.4; 15.37; 15.50.6; 15.51.4; 15.57.2
Mount Salmā, a mountain in the Jabal Ṭayyiʾ region 8.10.4n
Mount Sinai (Ṭūr Sīnāʾ), 1.1
Mufaḍḍal Lane (Darb al-Mufaḍḍal), location in East Baghdad 10.5.2 al-Muḥammadiyyah `see` Dayr Banī l-Ṣaqr Mukrān `see` Makrān
al-Munastīr `see` Monastir
al-Munaybiʿ, a locality just west of Damascus in Syria 15.33
Mūrāṭīr `see` Murviedro
Murcia (Mursiyah), a city in south-east al-Andalus 13.42; 13.53; 13.62.2.2; 13.81.2n; 13.83; 15.8.1n
Murviedro (Mūrāṭīr), city in Spain known today as Sagunto 13.68.1
al-Mushaqqar, a settlement and port on the eastern coast of Arabia, exact location unknown 10.1.3
Mutān, a village near Ṣarkhad in Syria 10.83.4
Muṭbaq, name of a prison in the southern part of Baghdad 8.29.16
Mysia, a region in the northwest part of ancient Anatolia 1.1
Nablus (Nābulus), a city approximately 49 km N. of Jerusalem 15.51.5
Nadrūmah `see` Nedroma
Najaf, town in south central Iraq 8.9 Najd, central Arabian plateau 14.47.1(p); 15.51.10.2(p)
Naḥlah (Nahle), village near Baalbek 15.37.4(p)
Nahr Bānyās `see` Bānyās canal
Nahr ʿĪsā, canal in Baghdad 10.4.4.2n
Nahr al-Kalbah, one of the canals of Baghdad 8.11
Nahr al-Mahdī, one of the canals of Baghdad 8.10.3
Nahr al-Malik, canal and district in Baghdad 10.4.4.2
Nahr Maʿqil `see` Maʿqil Canal
Nahr Ṣarṣar, one of the four main canals around Baghdad 8.2
al-Nahrawān, a town and system of canals on the lower Tigris River 8.27.4
Najaf, city in Iraq 8.29.1n
Naples 4.1.10.2n
Nasā, a town in Khorasan 11.13.2.11 (`see also`
Nisā) Naṣībīn (modern Nusaybin; ancient Nisibis or Nasibis), in south-eastern Analtolia, on the Syrian border 4.1.10.2n; 4.1.11.3n; 5.1.7; 5.1.16.1n; 8.1.2; 15.36.1
Nāṣirī Hospital (al-Bīmāristān al-Nāṣirī), in Cairo 14.32.1n; 14.39.2n; 14.40.1n; 14.43.1; 14.47.2
Navas de Tolosa (al-ʿIqāb), city in today’s province of Jaén 13.71
Naysābūr `see` Nishapur
Nedroma (Nadrūmah), town near to the city of Tlemcen (Morocco) 13.81.1
{473}
Nighyā, settlement near al-Anbār 5.1.16.1 al-Nīl, town near al-Ḥillah in Iraq 10.56n Nile, river (Baḥr al-Nīl) 8.21.4; 10.38.4; 13.58.4.5(p); 14.15n; 14.22.3.1; 14.25.3.1; 14.31.6n; 14.54.6n; 14.54.8n; 15.40.3
Nilometer (al-Miqyās)   14.31.6n
Nineveh (Nīnawah), Iraq 2.1.4n; 11.13.7.9(p); 11.18n
Nisā or Nasā, a village near Nishapur   8.10.4
Nishapur (Naysābūr, Nīsābūr; modern Nishapur), a city of north-eastern Khor-asan province of Iran 7.7.2n; 7.9.2n; 11.5.12; 11.13.7.9(p); 11.19; 11.20; 14.36.2n Nisibis `see` Naṣībīn
al-Niẓāmiyyah Law College (al-Madrasah al-Niẓāmiyyah), in Baghdad 10.64.2; 10.81.4; 14.22.5.1n; 15.40.2
North Africa (excluding Egypt) `see` Maghrib al-Nūbah, Nubia 8.21.4
Nūrī Hospital, ‘the Great Hospital’ (al-Bīmāristān al-Nūrī, al-Bīmāristān al-Kabīr) founded by Nūr al-Dīn in Dam-ascus in 543/1154 15.9; 15.13; 15.23.4.2; 15.24; 15.30; 15.33; 15.34; 15.35; 15.36.1; 15.37.1; 15.38; 15.39; 15.42; 15.46.3; 15.50.1; 15.50.3; 15.50.5; 15.51.3; 15.51.6; 15.52.1; 15.53; 15.57.1; ＡＩ.2n
Old Cairo (Miṣr al-Qadīmah) `see` Fustat; `see also` Qaṣr al-Shamaʿ
Olynthus, ancient Greek city in Chalcidice 4.6.2.1
Osuna (Ushūnah), city in the province of Seville (Spain) 13.33n
Otrar `see` Fārāb
Oxus river 10.68.2.1n
Palermo, city in Sicily 4.6.3.3
Palestine (Filasṭīn)    5.1.37 no. 115; 8.20.10; 8.20.11; 12.6
Palmyra (Tadmur), ancient city of Syria 15.49.6.1n
Pechina (Bajjānah), city in today’s province of Almería (Spain) 13.71
Peloponnese, peninsula and region in south-ern Greece 2.1.1n
Pelusium, ancient city on the eastern fringe of the Nile delta 4.1.10.5n; `see also` al-Faramā
Perfume Market (Sūq al-ʿIṭr), in Baghdad 10.64,7
Pergamum (Pergamon, Farghāmus; mod-ern Bergama), a Greek city in the Aeolis region of western Asia Minor 1.6; 5.1.15; 5.1.18.1; 5.1.25; 5.1.26; 5.1.37 no. 36n Persia (Fārs [specifically for southern Iran]
ln Bilād al-ʿAjam, a vague term for an area rather larger than modern Iran) 1.1; 1.5; 2.1.3; 4.1.5; 4.1.9.2; 7.1.1; 7.5.6n; 8.3.4; 8.5.2; 8.20.6; 8.20.11n; 8.29.9; 10.37.3; 10.38.4; 10.64.1; 11.5.14; 11.10; 11.16; 11.17; 11.19.3; 11.19.5; 11.20; 11.21; 14.22.4.3n??; 14.32.4n; 15.30; 15.40
Petra, ancient city in southern Jordan 1.5n; 4.1.11.3n
Pharos, Raʾs al-Tīn quarter of Alexandria 6.1.3
Phrygia (Afrūjiyā) – an ancient and in part mythical kingdom in the west-central part of Asia Minor 1.1
Pontus, ancient region on the southern coast of the Black Sea 4.1.10.2n; 8.20.11n
Port-Vendres (Haykal al-Zuharah), coastal town in the Eastern Pyrenees 13.4n
Portico Gate `see` Bāb al-Azaj
Praesus, an ancient coastal town in eastern Crete 1.8n
Pytho, old name for Delphi 4.3.4.3
al-Qābūn, a stop on road from Damascus to Iraq, today a part of greater Damascus 15.18.1.2
al-Qādisiyyah, a town on the east bank of the Tigris, southeast of Samarra 8.3.7n; 8.20.6; 8.29.2
al-Qāhirah `see` Cairo
al-Qalāʾīn, a place on the western side of Baghdad 8.25.7
Qalʿat Barqā `see` Castle of Barqā
Qalʿat Jaʿbar `see` Jaʿbar
Qamrā (Qamrāʾ, Qamrāw), a village near Ṣarkhad in Syria 10.83.4
Qanādir, town in Iṣfahān 8.10.4n Qānariz, town near Nishapur 8.10.4n Qanjayrah `see` Canjáyar
al-Qarāfah Cemetery, in Cairo 14.48.2 al-Qarash, a village in Syria ＡＩ.1 Qarduwān, unidentified place 10.5.4
{474}
Qarmīsīn `see` Kirmānshāh
Qarmūniyah `see` Carmona
Qāsiyūn `see` Mount Qāsiyūn
Qaṣr Faraj, a quarter in the eastern side of Baghdad 8.5.2
Qaṣr Ibn Hubayrah, a town in Iraq, midway between Baghdad and Kufa 8.10.4 Qaṣr al-Shamaʿ (or al-Shamʿ), the Arabic
name for the Graeco-Coptic township of Babylon (Bābilyūn), on the east bank of the Nile 14.10n; 14.15; 14.25.3
Qaṭīʿat al-Raqīq (or al-Daqīq), a fiefdom in Baghdad; `see also` Bīʿat Mār Tūmā 10.22.3
al-Qāṭūl (‘canal’), a district of Samarra 8.20.5; 8.20.6 Qaṭwān Steppe 11.14n
al-Qayrawān `see` Kairouan
Qaysāriyyah or Qaysariyyah `see` Caesarea Qazwīn, a town and district northwest of
Tehran and south of Gīlān, in northern Persia 8.20.11; 11.13.3.3
al-Qilījiyyah Law College, al-Madrasah al-Qilījiyyah, in Damascus 15.52.1 Qubādir Zubayrūn, of uncertain identity,
possibly Qanādir in Iṣfahān or Qānariz near Nīshapur 8.10.4
al-Quds `see` Jerusalem
Qūliyāthā, an estate near Wāsiṭ 10.62.3(p)
Qurrah, village near Smyrna 5.1.16.2 Qurṭubah `see` Cordova
Qūṣ, town in Upper Egypt not far from mod-ern Luxor 13.59.3
Qusṭanṭīnah (Constantine), city in present-day Algeria 13.58.4.3(p) al-Qusṭanṭīniyyah `see` Constantinople Quṭrabbul, a village not far from Baghdad
8.1.1; 8.27.4
al-Rabadhah, a way station on the main pil-grimage route between Kufa and Mecca 8.8.3
Raḍwā, Mt., a mountain in Arabia 7.5.6(p) al-Raḥbah (or Raḥbat Mālik ibn Ṭawq or Raḥ-bat al-Shām), a town on the right bank of the Euphrates; modern al-Mayādīn in eastern Syria 10.53; 10.69.3.7; 15.36.1
al-Rāhib, a place on the road between Samarra and Damascus 7.8.3
al-Ramlah, a town on the coastal plain west-northwest of Jerusalem 14.14.3
Raqqa (al-Raqqah), a city on the north bank of the Euphrates, about 160 kilometres east of Aleppo, Syria 7.5.3n; 8.3.13; 8.8.6; 10.8.11; 10.17.n; 14.50n; 15.2; 15.32n; 15.52.1; 15.52.2 no. 1
Raqqādah, palace city of the Aghlabids southwest of Kairaouan 13.2.2.2
Raʾs al-ʿAyn `see` Rēsh ʿAynā
al-Rawḍah `see` al-Jazīrah (Jazīrat Miṣr) Rayy (or al-Rayy), a town near the modern
city of Tehran 1.10n; 6.4n; 7.7.2n; 8.5.2; 8.5.3; 8.5.4; 8.10.2; 8.10.3; 11.5.1; 11.5.7; 11.5.9; 11.5.11; 11.5.12; 11.5.14n.; 11.5.22; 11.6; 11.9.2.4(p); 11.13.3.3; 11.13.7.9(p); 11.13.8 no. 11; 11.19.1; 11.19.4; 11.19.5; 11.19.6.1; 11.20; 15.19; 15.21; 15.21 no. 3; 15.31 no. 5; 15.40.9 no. 19; 15.59 no. 1
Rēsh ʿAynā (Raʾs al-ʿAyn), an ancient city on the modern Syria-Turkey border, today forming a single divided city with Ceylan-pınar in Turkey 5.1.8.2n; 5.1.16.1; 8.29.3; 8.29.8n; 9.24
Rhodes, the largest island in the Dodecanese island chain off the Anatolian coast of Turkey 1.1; 4.1.1; 4.1.11.3n; 4.6.13.2n; 15.1 Ribāṭ al-Fatḥ, district in north-west Morocco
13.64.2.1
Roda `see` al-Jazīrah ( Jazīrat Miṣr)
Roman Sea `see` Mediterranean
Rome (Rūmiyah) 1.8n; 1.10n; 2.1.2; 4.1.9.2; 4.1.10.4n; 4.1.11.2n; 4.3.4.2n; 4.4.2.3; 4.6.13.2n; 5.1.9; 5.1.10.1; 5.1.11; 5.1.17; 5.1.19; 5.1.21.1; 5.1.21.2; 5.1.25; 5.1.26; 5.1.37 no. 37; 15.1.2; 15.11.2.1(p)
al-Ruhā or al-Ruhāʾ (Edessa, modern Urfa), ancient city now in northern Mesopot-amia 9.7n; 9.25; 9.33; 10.57n; 11.13.7.9(p); 14.50; 14.51.2; 14.54.3; 15.11.2 Rūmiyah `see` Rome
Sabta `see` Ceuta
Sābūr Khwāst, a town between Khuzestan and Isfahan 11.13.3.10; 11.13.8 no. 14 al-Ṣafrāʾ, a place 17 miles from Badr in the
Ḥijāz 7.2.3; 7.2.4
Saint Acisclo Church, church in Cordova 13.14
{475}
Salé (Salā), coastal city in north-western Morocco 13.64.2.1
Ṣalkhad `see` Ṣarkhad
Ṣamʿ, unidentified village near Aleppo  15.15
Samanqān, town in Khorasan 11.13.2.11 Samarkand (or Samarqand), a city in
modern-day Uzbekistan 8.11n; 11.19.5; 11.22; 11.23
Samarra (Sāmarrāʾ, Surra Man Raʾā), a town on the east bank of the middle Tigris in Iraq, north of Baghdad 7.8.3; 8.2.3; 8.4.3n; 8.4.7; 8.12.2; 8.20.4n; 8.20.5; 8.20.7n; 8.25.7n; 8.26.18; 10.1.7n; 10.44.5 no. 5n; 11.3; `see also` al-Sāmir
al-Samāwah, the steppe and desert lands between southern Iraq and Syria 10.64.18
al-Sāmir, possibly = Samarra 11.13.7.9(p) Samos, an island off the western coast of
Anatolia 2.1.1n; 4.1.11.3n; 4.3.4.1; 4.3.4.3
Samosata (Sumaysāṭ), an ancient city in south-east Anatolia on the upper Euphrates 15.28
Sanaa (Ṣanʿāʾ), in Yemen 15.18.2(p) Şanlıurfa (or Urfa) `see` al-Ruhā
Saqṭīthā, a hamlet near Baghdad 8.11 Saragossa (Saraqusṭah, Zaragoza), city and
petty kingdom in al-Andalus 13.9; 13.29.1; 13.46; 13.50; 13.63.8.2
al-Ṣarāh, canal in Baghdad  10.81.5(p)
Sarakhs, town in Khorasan   10.2.1n; 11.19.7n
Saraqusṭāh `see` Saragossa
Ṣarkhad (or Ṣalkhad), a stronghold in south-ern Syria near the border of present-day Jordan b10.83; 15.23.3; 15.37.4; 15.46.3; 15.49.6; 15.60.1
Ṣarṣar, a town near Baghdad 8.2 al-Sawād, the fertile alluvial plains of south-ern Iraq 8.3.22; 8.4.5; 8.10.1; 8.10.4; 14.34.2n
Sāwah, town in northern Persia 10.64.19.19 Saydnāyā (Sednaya), a city in the mountains
north Damascus 15.3.1
Scyros, Greek island 4.3.4.1
Seville (Ishbīliyah, Sevilla), city in al-Andalus 13.10; 13.60.1; 13.60.2; 13.61.3.1; 13.61.3.2; 13.62.2.2; 13.62.2.3; 13.62.3; 13.62.4 no. 7; 13.63.2; 13.63.5; 13.63.8.1; 13.63.8.2; 13.64.2.1; 13.64.2.2; 13.65; 13.66.3; 13.73; 13.75; 13.76; 13.77; 13.78n; 13.80.1; 13.81.1; 13.81.2; 13.86.1; 13.86.2; 13.87; 13.88.1; 15.45.1n
Shadūnah `see` Sidonia
Shahrazūr, district in western Kurdistan 11.13.7.9(p)
al-Shām `see` Damascus `and` Syria Shammāsiyyah Gate quarter, a neighbour-hood on the eastern side of Baghdad 8.25.7
Shaqqā (or Shaqqah), a village in the Ḥawrān, Syria 15.27
al-Sharā, a region proverbial for lions, said to be in Yemen 10.64.17.2(p); 15.8.5(p) Shāsh, Tashkent, in modern Uzbekistan
8.1.4 Shāṭibah `see` Játiva
al-Shawbak `see` Shoubak
Shiraz (Shīrāz), ancient city in the Fārs region of southwestern modern Iran 8.5.2; 11.5.6; 11.13.3.15; 14.22.4.3n
Shirimsāḥ (or Shirmasāḥ), a town near Dami-etta in Lower Egypt 14.49.2
Shoubak (al-Shawbak), a fortress town in the Transjordan 5.1.32
Shushtar `see` Tustar
Sicily (Ṣiqilliyah or Ṣiqilliyyah) 4.3.4.2; 4.3.6.2 no. 17; 4.5.2; 4.6.2.1; 5.1.21.2 Sidonia (Shadūnah), city in today’s province
of Cádiz (Spain) 13.22; 13.27.1
Ṣiffīn, a place near the modern al-Raqqah, in Syria 7.5.3; 7.10n
Siʿird (or Siʿirt, Isʿird; modern Siirt), a town in south-eastern Anatolia 1.3.1
Sijistān (Sīstān), province in eastern Iran 2.1.1n; 15.1.3.1n Silvan `see` Mayyāfāriqīn
Sinai `see` Mount Sinai
Sind (al-Sind or Sindh), a region along the lower Indus River 8.21.2; 8.21.3; 11.15 Sinjar (or Sinjār), a town in Iraq near Mount
Sinjar 11.18n
al-Sīq, the ‘Great Lavra’ of the Dayr Mār Sābā monastery near Jerusalem 15.43.2 Sīstān `see` Sijistān
Smyrna, ancient Greek city of Asia Minor 4.1.11.3n; 4.5.1n; 4.5.4n; 5.1.16.2; 5.1.25; 5.1.37 no. 36
{476}
Stagira, ancient Greek city 4.6.2.1; 4.6.2.2; 4.6.2.3; 4.6.3.2; 4.6.6.2
Sumaysāṭ `see` Samosata
Sūq al-ʿIṭr `see` Perfume Market
Sūq al-Qamḥ `see` Wheat Market
Sūq al-Qanādīl (Candlestick Market), a quarter in Fustat 14.32.3
Sūq al-Thalāthāʾ `see` Tuesday Market
Sūq Yaḥyā (Yaḥyā’s Market), a district on the eastern side of Baghdad 8.8.2; 10.4.6
Ṣūr `see` Tyre
Sūrā, town in southern Iraq 10.4.4.2
Surra Man Raʾā `see` Samarra
al-Sūs (ancient Susa; modern Shūsh), a town in the southwestern province of Khuzestan 8.3.22 Susia `see` Ṭūs
al-Suwaydāʾ, a town in the Ḥawrān in south-ern Syria 15.57.1
Syria (al-Shām, i.e. Greater Syria, normally also including modern Syria, Jordan, Palestine/Israel, and Lebanon) 1.5; 2.1.4; 4.1.1n; 4.2; 4.3; 5.1.37 no. 115; 7.2.3n; 7.5.2; 8.3.14n; 8.3.18n; 8.18.2; 8.20.6n; 10.38.4; 10.64.13; 10.83.4; 13.4n; 13.58.4.4; 13.86.1; 14.3n; 14.4.1; 14.4.4; 14.25.9 no. 39; 14.31.5, 6; 14.32.3n; 14.43.3 no. 1; 14.46; 14.49.2n; 14.50n; 14.51.1n; 14.54.3n; 14.54.4n; 15.1.5 no. 32; 15.4; 15.11.1; 15.17(p); 15.18.1; 15.19; 15.21; 15.23.2.1; 15.25; 15.29; 15.30; 15.31.1; 15.32; 15.36.1; 15.38; 15.40.2; 15.40.5; 15.41; 15.49.4; 15.50.3; 15.51.2; 15.34.13; 15.57.1; 15.58
Syracuse, Greek city in Sicily 4.3.4.2n Syrus, Greek island of the Cyclades 4.3.4.1
Ṭabarān (gates of Isfahan) 11.13.3.9 Tabaristan (Ṭabaristān), region of north-ern Persia on the southern shore of the Caspian Sea 10.5.4; 10.67.3; 11.3; 11.4; 11.5.14; 11.6
Tabrīz, a city in the northern region of Persia, in the Quru River valley    15.21
Tādlā, in Morocco 13.66.3n
Tadmur `see` Palmyra
al-Ṭāʾif, town in Arabia, approx. 65 km east of
Mecca 7.1.1
Takrīt (or Tikrīt), town between Baghdad and Mosul 10.39n; 10.68.2.1n
Talavera, city in today’s province of Toledo (Spain) 13.11n
al-Ṭalīl, an unidentified locality on the way to Karak 1.11
Tall Bāshir `see` Turbessel
Tangier (Ṭanjah), city in Morocco 13.4n Taormina (Tauromenium), ancient Greek
city in Sicily 4.3.4.2n
Ṭarābulus `see` Tripoli
Tarentum (Taras), ancient Greek city of southern Italy 3.6n; 4.1.10.2n; 4.1.11.2; 4.3.4.3; 4.3.6.1
Tarsus, ancient city in south-central Anatolia 1.9n; 4.1.11.2; 4.1.11.3
Ṭārum, district of Daylam in north-western Iran 11.13.3.6
Tashkent `see` Shāsh
Tbilisi `see` Tiflis
Tehran, capital of modern Iran 1.10n; 7.1.2n Tenessos `see` Tinnīṣ
Teos, ancient Greek city on the coast of Ionia 4.6.13.2n
Thabīr, Mt., a mountain in Arabia 7.5.6(p) Thamil Lane (Darb Thamil), in Baghdad
10.81.1
al-Tharthār, a wadi in northern Mesopotamia 11.13.7.9(p)
Thasos, Greek island in northern Aegean 4.1.5n
Thrace, historical region of northern Balkan peninsula 4.6.2.1
Tiflis (Tiflīs, modern Tbilisi), capital of the modern-day republic of Georgia 10.79; 15.2n
Tigris (Dijlah), one of the two great rivers of Mesopotamia 8.26.9; 8.26.12n; 10.1.7; 10.4.6; 10.21n; 10.64.7; 10.69.3.8; 11.13.7.9(p)
Tihāmah, the Arabian coastal plain on the Red Sea 14.47.1(p)
Tikrīt `see` Takrīt
Tilimsān `see` Tlemcen
Tinnīs, town and lake of the eastern part of the Nile Delta, ancient Tenessos 5.1.21.1 Tirmidh, a town on the Oxus river
10.68.2.1(p)
Ṭīzanābādh, a town between Kufa and al-Qādisiyyah, on the pilgrim route 8.3.7
{477}
Tlemcen (Tilimsān), city in north-western Algeria 13.81.1; 13.85
Toledo (Ṭulayṭulah), city and Andalusī `ṭāʾifah` in Spain 13.11; 13.11n; 13.38.1; 13.38.2; 13.39.2; 13.45; 13.48
Tralles, ancient Greek city of south-west Anatolia 1.1n; 4.1.10.4n
Transoxiana (Mā warāʾ al-nahr) 11.5.14 Tripoli (Ṭarābulus), city in Lebanon 2.1.5n Tripoli (Ṭarābulus al-Gharb), city in Libya
2.1.5n
Troy, ancient city, the modern Hisarlık, Tur-key 1.1n; 2.1.5
Trujillo (Turjālah), city in today’s province of Cáceres (Spain) 13.65
Ṭulayṭulah `see` Toledo
Tūmā Gate `see` Bāb Tūmā
Tuesday Market (Sūq al-Thalāthāʾ), in Bagh-dad 10.76.3
Tunis (Tūnis), capital of today’s Tunisia 13.68.2
al-Ṭūr (or Ṭūr ʿAbdīn), a plateau in northern Mesopotamia 15.51.11 no. 1
Ṭūr Sīnāʾ `see` Mount Sinai
Ṭurā, a town about 10 miles (15 km) south of
Cairo 14.15n
Turbessel (Tall Bāshir; modern Tellbasar Kalesi, Turkey), a castle and town in northern Syria in the valley of the Sājūr, a tributary of the Euphrates 15.56.1
Turjālah `see` Trujillo
Ṭūs, an ancient city near Mashhad in Iran 8.3.4; 8.29.2; 11.13.2.11; 15.24; 15.24n Tustar (or Shūshtar, Shūstar, Tushtar), a town
in the Khuzestan province of Persia 11.10
Tyre (Ṣūr), a city in the south of present-day Lebanon 4.1.11.3; 4.3.4.1; 11.2; 13.4n; 15.45.1
Tyrrhenia `see` Etruria
al-ʿUdhayb (Little Sweetwater), name of sev-eral desert locations 15.49.6.1(p)
ʿUkbarā, a town located on the east bank of the Tigris, halfway between Baghdad and Samarra 8.5.2; 8.25.7n
Umayyad Mosque, in Damascus 15.19; 15.24; 15.29; 15.33; 15.34; 15.40.3; 15.57.1n
Urfa `see` al-Ruhā Ushūnah `see` Osuna
Usrūshanah, the mountainous district between Samarqand and Khujand 8.11
al-Uthayl, a place near Medina 7.1.3(p) Utrar `see` Fārāb
Valencia (Balansiyah), city in al-Andalus 13.41; 13.68.1; 13.84
Victory Castle `see` Ḥiṣn al-Faraj
Victory Gate `see` Bāb al-Fatḥ `and` Bāb al-Naṣr
Wādī Kanʿān (the Wadi of Kanaan, also known as ʿAyn Jālūt, Goliath’s Spring) the site in Palestine of the victory of the Mamluks over the Mongols in 658/1260
11.13.7.9; 15.32
Walnut Tree Gate `see` Bāb al-Jawz Warakhshah or Farakhshah, a town near
Bokhara 10.62.1n
Wāsiṭ, important mediaeval city of central Iraq 7.9.5; 8.13.3n; 10.1.6; 10.4.8; 10.62.1; 10.62.2; 10.62.3
Wheat Market (Sūq al-Qamḥ), in Damascus 15.35
Yabrūd, a large village near Saydnāyā, north of Damascus 15.3.1
Yadhbul, mountain in Arabia 11.19.3(p) Yalamlam, a mountain in Arabia 14.32.4(p) Yamama (al-Yamāmah), region in central and
eastern Arabia 10.1.1.4; 10.1.3; 14.47.1n al-Yaman `see` Yemen
Yemen (al-Yaman) 1.1; 7.1.1; 8.3.16n; 8.10.2n; 8.10.4; 10.38.4; 14.32.4n; 14.33.3; 14.57.1; 15.8.1n
Yūnān, said to be a ‘(pen)insula’, home of the Greeks (`see also` Ionia) 2.1.1 al-Yussānah `see` Lucena
Zabīd, town in Yemen 14.33.3n al-Ẓafariyyah, neighbourhood in East Bagh-dad 15.40.2n
Zagros Mountains `see` al-Jibāl
al-Zahrāʾ `see` Madīnat al-Zahrāʾ Zamakhshar, in Khwārazm 15.40.9 no. 12n Zanjān, a town and district approximately
150 kilometres west of Qazwīn 8.20.11 Zarafshān, river in Transoxiana 8.11 Zaragoza `see` Saragossa
{478}
al-Zawrāʾ, name of several locations, includ-ing a part of Baghdad 10.64.17.1(p); 15.18.2n
Zayzāʾ, a locality north of Amman, Jordan 15.32
al-Zuqāq (‘The Strait [of Gibraltar]’) 13.4n
