<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
{383}
al-Abaḥḥ `see` al-Ḥasan ibn Muḥammad al- Ṭūsī al-Tamīmī
Abba Christodulos `see` Christodulos ʿAbbād ibn ʿAbbās, unidentified physician,
addressee of Ibn Mandawayh al-Iṣfahānī 11.16.1.2.7
al-ʿAbbās, unidentified agent of Ibrāhīm ibn al-Aghlab 13.1.1 no. 9
al-ʿAbbās (ibn ʿAbd al-Muṭṭalib) – uncle of Muḥammad, ancestor of the Abbasids (d. ca. 32/653) 10.68.2.1(p)
al-ʿAbbās ibn ʿAlī ibn al-Mahdī (Abū Quraysh), grandson of al-Mahdī, nephew of Mūsā al-Hādī and Hārūn al-Rashīd 8.8.2
al-ʿAbbās ibn al-Maʾmūn, household of al-Muʿtaṣim (ca. 221/836) 8.20.5 al-ʿAbbās ibn Muḥammad, brother of al-Manṣūr 8.3.18
al-ʿAbbās ibn Saʿīd al-Jawharī `see` al-Jawharī,
al-ʿAbbās ibn Saʿīd
al-ʿAbbāsah bint al-Mahdī ibn Abī Jaʿfar al-Manṣūr, 2nd/8th-c. daughter of al-Mahdī, sister of Hārūn al-Rashīd, wife of Khālid ibn Barmak and Ibrāhīm ibn Ṣāliḥ ibn ʿAlī 8.3.22; 12.6
ʿAbd Allāh, advisor to al-Muntaṣir 8.4.3 ʿAbd Allāh Ⅰ, seventh emir of Cordova 13.15
ʿAbd Allāh (? = ʿUbayd Allāh ibn Yaḥyā ibn
Khāqān), vizier of al-Mutawakkil 8.4.3n; 8.12
ʿAbd Allāh, shaykh of Mālik clan, of Banū Hāshim (ca. 169–170/785–786) 8.10.3
ʿAbd Allāh al-Ṭayfūrī, Christian physician to al-Hādī 8.2; 8.10
ʿAbd Allāh ibn al-ʿAbbās (commonly Ibn ʿAbbās), 1st/7th-c. Qurʾanic exegete, eponymous ancestor of the Abbasid caliphs 1.5; 7.5.6
ʿAbd Allāh ibn ʿAlī, unidentified Persian-to- Arabic translator 12.2 no. 1
ʿAbd Allāh ibn ʿAlī, uncle of caliphs al-Saffāḥ and al-Manṣūr 7.6n; 8.18.2
ʿAbd Allāh ibn Aslam 10.3.6
ʿAbd Allāh ibn Badr, Cordovan vizier 13.17 ʿAbd Allāh ibn Bībī, host of Ibn Sīnā at Isfa-
han 11.13.3.9
ʿAbd Allāh ibn Isḥāq, 3rd/9th-c. patron of
translators 9.48
ʿAbd Allāh ibn al-Mubārak, transmitter 10.2.2.2
ʿAbd Allāh ibn Muḥammad ibn Dāwūd,
unidentified Abbasid (d. 199/815) 8.18.3 ʿAbd Allāh ibn Muḥammad al-Umawī, emir
of al-Andalus 13.20
ʿAbd Allāh ibn Mūsā, son of al-Hādī 8.10.3 ʿAbd Allāh ibn Nāʾilī (`or` Ibn al-Tātalī `or` Ibn
al-Bābilī), specialist in alchemy and numerology, member of the Almoravid dynasty 15.40.3
ʿAbd Allāh ibn Rajāʾ ibn Yaʿqūb, unidentified transmitter 15.3.1.6
ʿAbd Allāh ibn Ṭāhir, governor of Khorasan 7.7.2; 9.7n; 8.26.20 no. 22; 8.29.22n
ʿAbd Allāh ibn al-Ṭayyib `see` Ibn al-Ṭayyib ʿAbd Allāh ibn al-Zubayr, prominent oppon-
ent of the Umayyad caliphs 7.5.3n
{384}
ʿAbd Allāh al-Mahdī bi-Allāh, founder of the Fatimid caliphate 13.2.1; 13.2.2.1
ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz ibn Maslamah al-Bājī, Andalus- ian physician 13.78; 13.87
ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz ibn Abī Sālim, transmitter 10.2.2.2
ʿAbd al-Ḥamīd al-Kātib (ʿAbd al-Ḥamīd ibn Yaḥyā ibn Saʿd, d. 132/750), secretary to Marwān ⅠⅠ 15.31.1
ʿAbd al-Karīm, unidentified subject of a riddle epigram 15.8.10
ʿAbd al-Laṭīf ibn Yūsuf al-Baghdādī, philo- sopher and physician, also known as Ibn al-Labbād (557–629/1162–1231) 10.64.3; 10.66.4; 11.21; 14.22.5.2 no. 68n; 14.33.3n.; 15.18.1.1n; 15.31.6 no. 16; 15.37.1; 15.40; 15.45.1; 15.51.1.2
ʿAbd al-Malik al-Bājī, father of Abū Marwān al-Bājī 13.63.2
ʿAbd al-Malik ibn Abjar al-Kinānī, phys- ician of ʿUmar ibn ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz (nd􏲉. 99–101/717–720) 7.1.5; 7.3; 7.4
ʿAbd al-Malik ibn Marwān, fifth Umayyad caliph (nd􏲉. 65–86/685–705) 7.6; 8.13.2
ʿAbd al-Malik ibn ʿUmayr, unidentified 7.1.5; 7.1.6
ʿAbd al-Masīḥ ibn ʿAbd Allāh al-Ḥimṣī al-Nāʿimī `see` Ibn Nāʿimah
ʿAbd al-Muʾmin, Almohad ruler (d. 558/1163) 13.62.1; 13.62.2.1; 13.62.4 no. 2; 13.63.3; 15.40.3
ʿAbd al-Muʾmin ibn ʿAbd al-Munʿim, Dam-
ascene physician, served Ayyubid ruler
al-Malik al-Ashraf 15.11.2
ʿAbd al-Munʿim ibn ʿAbd al-Munʿim, son of
al-Jilyānī, oculist 15.11.2
ʿAbd al-Munʿim ibn ʿUmar `see` al-Jilyānī
ʿAbd al-Qādir al-Baghdādī, man of letters and
lexicographer 7.5.4n; 7.5.5n
ʿAbd al-Raḥīm ibn ʿAlī `see` al-Qāḍī al-Fāḍil ʿAbd al-Raḥmān ibn al-Ashʿath, leader of a
revolt against the Umayyad governor, al-Ḥajjāj ibn Yūsuf 7.9.4n
ʿAbd al-Raḥmān ibn Isḥāq ibn al-Haytham,
Andalusian physician 13.35; 13.36.2.3 ʿAbd al-Raḥmān ibn Khālid ibn al-Walīd, son
of commander Khālid ibn al-Walīd 7.5.2; 7.5.3; 7.5.5
ʿAbd al-Raḥmān ⅠⅠⅠ al-Nāṣir, Umayyad ruler of al-Andalus (d. 350/961) 13.15; 13.16; 13.19.1; 13.21.1; 13.21.2.2; 13.22; 13.23; 13.25; 13.26; 13.27.1; 13.28; 13.32; 13.33; 13.36.2.1; 13.36.2.2; 13.36.2.3; 13.49
ʿAbd al-Raḥmān ibn Yaḥyā ibn Khāqān (d. 262/875–876), brother of the vizier ʿUbayd Allāh ibn Yaḥyā ibn Khāqān
AⅠⅠ.2.3
ʿAbd al-Razzāq ibn Aḥmad al-ʿĀmirī `see` al-Badīʿ ʿAbd al-Razzāq
ʿAbd al-Ṣamad ibn ʿAlī ibn ʿAbd Allāh ibn al-ʿAbbās, brother of ʿAbd Allāh ibn ʿAlī ibn
ʿAbd Allāh ibn al-ʿAbbās 7.6
ʿAbd al-Wadūd al-Ṭabīb, transmitter 10.66.3 ʿAbd al-Wahhāb ibn ʿAlī, courtier of al-Muʿtaṣim 8.20.5
ʿAbd al-Wahhāb al-Thaqafī, grandfather of
Abū Mayyah 8.19.3n
ʿAbd Yashūʿ ibn Bahrīr, translator associate of
Jibrīl ibn Bukhtīshūʿ 9.35
ʿAbd Yashūʿ ibn Naṣr, physician of al-Hādī 8.2
ʿAbd Yashūʿ al-Jāthalīq, catholicos at Baghdad
(ca. 360/970) 10.8
ʿAbdān, student of Ibn al-Ṭayyib 10.37.4 al-ʿAbdī, Humām al-Dīn `see` Humām al-Dīn
al-ʿAbdī
ʿAbdishoʿ bar Bahrīz (ʿAbdīshūʿ ibn Bahrīz),
metropolitan and translator 9.35 ʿAbdūn ibn Makhlad, brother of Ṣāʿid 10.10.3n
ʿAbdūs the Physician 10.12
ʿAbdūs ibn Zayd physician 8.14; 8.29.10n al-Ābī, Abū Saʿd (`or` Saʿīd) Manṣūr ibn al-Ḥusayn, man of letters and vizier 8.20.6n; 10.8.10
ʿAbīd ibn al-Abraṣ, pre-Islamic poet 15.45.3 (p)
al-Abīwardī, poet (d. 507/1113) 10.64.19.8n Abraham `see` Ibrāhīm
al-Abrash `see` Ayyūb, known as al-Abrash Abū l-ʿAbbās Aḥmad ibn Muḥammad ibn
Thawābah `see` Ibn Thawābah
Abū l-ʿAbbās Aḥmad ibn Yaḥyā ibn Zayd `see`
Thaʿlab
Abū l-ʿAbbās ibn al-Rashīd, ?son of Hārūn
al-Rashīd 8.25.7
{385}
Abū l-ʿAbbās ibn al-Rūmiyyah `see` Ibn al- Rūmiyyah
Abū l-ʿAbbās ibn Wāḍiḥ al-Yaʿqūbī, 3rd/9th-c. polymath 4.1.9.1n; 8.3.15n; 8.3.16n
Abū l-ʿAbbās ibn Yaʿqūb ibn Isḥāq al-Kindī, son of al-Kindī 10.1.12; 10.1.14 no. 223
Abū l-ʿAbbās al-Jayyānī, physician 15.45.1 Abū l-ʿAbbās al-Kanbanārī, Aḥmad ibn Abī
ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad, Andalusian phys-
ician 13.87
Abū l-ʿAbbās al-Khaṣībī, secretary and then
vizier of al-Muntaṣir 8.4.3
Abū l-ʿAbbās Maʾmūn ibn Muḥammad
`see` Khwārazmshāh Abū l-ʿAbbās
Maʾmūn
Abū l-ʿAbbās al-Nabātī, herbalist 15.45.1n Abū l-ʿAbbās al-Qarrābī, Almohad poet 13.66.3
Abū ʿAbd Allāh al-Ḥusayn ibn Aḥmad ibn
Zakariyyā al-Dāʿī, missionary for the
Fatimid Mahdī 13.2.2.2
Abū ʿAbd Allāh ibn Aḥmad ibn Ḥamdūn,
man of letters 7.5.6n; 7.6n; 8.4.7n Abū ʿAbd Allāh ibn Hūd al-Judhāmī al-Mutawakkil (d. 635/1237–1238), ruler of
Murcia 13.81.2; 13.81.2n; 13.87; 13.87n Abū ʿAbd Allāh al-Ḥusaynī al-Qāḍī al-Sharīf,
Almohad qadi 13.64.2.1
Abū ʿAbd Allāh ibn al-Kattānī 13.29
Abū ʿAbd Allāh ibn Yazīd, Andalusian physi-
cian and poet 13.69
Abū ʿAbd Allāh ʿĪsā ibn Hibat Allāh ibn al-Naqqāsh, father of Muhadhdhab al-Dīn
ibn al-Naqqāsh 15.13
Abū ʿAbd Allāh al-Maghribī, unidentified
contemporary of ⅠAU 13.88.2
Abū ʿAbd Allāh al-Malik al-Thaqafī Andalus-
ian physician 13.32
Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad,
brother of the qadi Abū Marwān al-Bājī 13.65
Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad, grandson of ʿAbd Allāh ibn al-Ḥafīd Abū Bakr ibn Zuhr 13.63.8.2
Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad, son of Abū
Isḥāq Ibrāhīm al-Dānī 13.71
Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad ibn Abī ʿAlī al-Ḥasan ibn Abī Yūsuf Ḥajjāj al-Khaṭīb, Almohad qadi 13.63.2.1
Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad ibn Dāwūd ibn al-Jarrāḥ, secretary of several Abbāsid caliphs (d. 296/908) 8.4.12
Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad ibn al-Ḥasan ibn Muḥammad al-Kātib al-Baghdādī Ibn al-Karīm `see` Shams al-Dīn Abū ʿAbd Allāh
Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad ibn Ibrāhīm al- Mahrī al-Uṣūlī, qadi in Bougie 13.636.3 Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad ibn Masʿūd al-Bajjānī, poet who lived in Cordova (d.
ca. 400/1009–1010) 13.29.2
Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad ibn Nūr al-Dawlah Abū Shujāʿ al-Āmirī al-Maʾmūn,
Fatimid vizier 13.51.1; 13.51.4 no. 1
Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad ibn al-Wāthiq `see` al-Muhtadī bi-Allāh Abū ʿAbd Allāh
Muḥammad al-Mālaqī (of Malaga),
unidentified copyist 14.25.4 Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad Ibrāhīm,
Andalusī judge and grammarian 13.29.2 Abū ʿAbd Allāh al-Nadrūmī, Muḥammad ibn
Ṣaḥnūn, Andalusian physician 13.81 Abū ʿAbd Allāh al-Nātilī, tutor to Ibn Sīnā 11.13.2; 11.13.3; 11.13.4; 11.13.5
Abū ʿAbd Allāh Nuʿaym ibn Ḥammād ibn
Muʿāwiyah al-Khuzāʿī al-Marwazī, 3rd/10th-c. Hadith scholar 7.3n Abū ʿAbd Allāh al-Ṣiqillī 13.36.2.3
Abū Aḥmad Muḥammad ibn Ibrāhīm al-Fārisī, patron of Ibn Sīnā 11.13.8. no. 9
Abū l-ʿAlāʾ ibn Abī Jaʿfar Aḥmad ibn Ḥassān, Andalusian physician 13.75
Abū l-ʿAlāʾ ibn Nazīk 10.38.4
Abū l-ʿAlāʾ al-Maʿarrī `see` al-Maʿarrī Abū l-ʿAlāʾ Maḥfūẓ ibn al-Masīḥī (`or` al-Musabbiḥī?), physician 10.71
Abū l-ʿAlāʾ Muḥammad, physician and son
of Abū Muḥammad ibn al-Ḥafīd Abī Bakr
ibn Zuhr 13.64.2.2
Abū l-ʿAlāʾ Ṣāʿid ibn al-Ḥasan, physician in
al-Raḥbah (d, 464/1072) 10.53
Abū l-ʿAlāʾ ibn Zuhr `see` Ibn Zuhr, Abū l-ʿAlāʾ Abū ʿAlī ʿAbd al-Raḥmān ibn ʿĪsā ibn Dāʾūd
ibn al-Jarrāḥ (active 325/936), vizier of
al-Rāḍī and al-Muttaqī 10.5.3 Abū ʿAlī al-Fārandī al-Ṭūsī, transmitter 15.51.7
{386}
Abū ʿAlī al-Ḥasan ibn Aḥmad ibn Abān (Abū ʿAlī al-Fārisī), grammarian (d. 377/987) 15.40.2
Abū ʿAlī al-Ḥasan ibn ʿAlī ibn Ibrāhīm al-Juwaynī al-Kātib `see` al-Juwaynī
Abū ʿAlī al-Ḥusayn ibn Bishr al-Ramlī, poet 10.64.19.7n
Abū ʿAlī ibn ʿAbd al-Muʾmin, governor (`ṣāḥib`)
of Seville 13.80.1
Abū ʿAlī ibn Bunān ibn al-Ḥārith, `mawlā` of
al-Muqtadir 10.44.5 no. 61
Abū ʿAlī ibn Makanjā, Christian scribe 10.8.10
Abū ʿAlī ibn Mawṣilāyā, secretary of Abū l-
Qāsim al-Maghribī 10.13.3; 10.38.4 Abū ʿAlī ibn al-Samḥ, Christian Aristotelian 10.38.4
Abū ʿAlī ʿĪsā ibn Isḥāq ibn Zurʿah `see` ibn
Zurʿah
Abū ʿAlī al-Jubbāʾī, Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd al-Wahhāb (d. 303/915), Muʿtazilite from
Basra 14.22.4.3n; 14.22.5.1 no. 8
Abū ʿAlī al-Manṣūr ibn Abī l-Qāsim Aḥmad al-Mustaʿlī bi-Allāh ibn al-Mustanṣir `see`
al-Āmir bi-Aḥkām Allāh
Abū ʿAlī al-Muhandis al-Miṣrī (active 550/1155), author of an epigram attributed
to al-Badīʿ al-Asṭurlābī 10.67.4.3n Abū ʿAlī al-Nīsābūrī, contemporary of Ibn
Sīnā 11.13.8 no. 62
Abū ʿAlī al-Qiyānī, unidentified historian 8.4.12; 8.14; 8.20.12; 8.29.10
Abū ʿĀmir ibn Yannaq al-Shāṭibī, Andalusī
poet and historian 13.61.3.1
Abū ʿAmr al-Aʿjamī, courtier of Hārūn al-Rashīd 12.5
Abū ʿAmr al-Zajjājī, transmitter 15.51.7 Abū l-ʿArab Yūsuf ibn Muḥammad, Andalus-
ian physician 13.37
Abū l-Aṣbagh ʿĪsā ibn Aḥmad al-Rāzī
(d. 379/989), Andalusī historian and sec-
retary of al-Ḥakam ⅠⅠ 13.18
Abū l-Aṣbagh ʿĪsā Ibn Ḥayyawayh, contem-
porary of Ibn Juljul 13.17
Abū l-ʿAshāʾir, perhaps Abū l-ʿAshīr (Jaysh)
ibn Khumārawayh, grandson of Ibn Ṭūlūn 14.44
Abū l-ʿAskar al-Ḥusayn ibn Maʿdān, ruler of Makrān (Mukrān) 14.25.9 no. 42
Abū l-ʿAtāhiyah, poet (d. 211/826) 8.3.19n; 11.13 n.; 15.52.1.1n; AⅠⅠ.9
Abū ʿAwānah, al-Waḍḍāḥ, `muḥaddith` (d. 170/786 `or` 176/792) 7.1.5
Abū l-ʿAynāʾ al-Miṣrī, teacher of Abū l-ʿAlāʾ ibn Zuhr 13.61.3.1
Abū Ayyūb Muḥammad ibn al-Rashīd, a son of the caliph Hārūn al-Rashīd 8.26.11n
Abū Bakr, the first caliph after Muḥammad’s death 7.1.5
Abū Bakr, the son of al-Qāḍī Abū l-Ḥasan al-Zuhrī, Andalusian physician 13.62.3; 13.80
Abū Bakr Aḥmad ibn ʿAlī al-Rāzī, jurist 11.5.12
Abū Bakr Aḥmad ibn Jābir, Andalusian physi- cian 13.31
Abū Bakr ʿAlī ibn al-Ḥasan al-Quhistānī, poet (ca. 435/1043), ?author of lines ascribed to Ibn Sīnā 11.13
Abū Bakr al-Barqī, contemporary of Ibn Sīnā 11.13.2.10; 11.13.8 nos. 3, 4
Abū Bakr ibn ʿAbd al-Raḥmān ibn al-Ḥārith ibn Hishām, prominent jurist and tradi- tionist 7.5.4
Abū Bakr Ibn al-ʿArabī, Mālikī jurist 13.59.4; 13.65
Abū Bakr ibn Qārin al-Rāzī, physician, stu- dent of al-Rāzī 11.5.12
Abū Bakr al-Khālidī, 4th/10th-c. poet and man of letters, brother of Abū ʿUthmān al-Khālidī 8.26.15
Abū Bakr Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd Allāh ibn Muḥammad al-Rāzī, known as Ibn Ḥam- dūn, source of al-Tanūkhī 11.5.12
Abū Bakr Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd al-Malik al- Sarrāj, grammarian (d. ca. 330/942) 7.1.6n; 15.1.3.3
Abū Bakr Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd al-Raḥmān
ibn ʿUbayd Allāh ibn Yaḥyā al-Qaṭṭān,
transmitter 10.81.3
Abū Bakr Muḥammad ibn al-Khalīl al-Raqqī,
physician, commentator on Ḥunayn ibn
Isḥāq 10.17
Abū Bakr Muḥammad ibn ʿUbayd, patron of
Ibn Sīnā 11.13.8 no. 55
Abū Bakr Muḥammad ibn ʿUmar ibn ʿAbd
al-ʿAzīz, son of ʿUmar ibn ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz 8.19.2
{387}{!}
Abū Bakr Muḥammad ibn al-Walīd al- Ṭurṭūshī `see` al-Ṭurṭūshī
Abū Bakr Muḥammad ibn Zakariyyāʾ al-Rāzī `see` al-Rāzī
Abū Bakr al-Rāzī, son of Fakhr al-Dīn al-Rāzī, perhaps identical to Ḍiyāʾ al-Dīn al-Rāzī 11.19.6
Abū Bakrah ibn al-Ḥārith ibn Kaladah, son of
the slave-girl Sumayyah and, probably, the
physician al-Ḥārith ibn Kaladah 7.1.1 Abū l-Baqāʾ ʿAbd Allāh ibn al-Ḥusayn al-ʿUkbarī, grammarian (d. 616/1219) 10.79
Abū Barāʾ ʿĀmir ibn Mālik, tribal hero 15.8.4(p)
Abū l-Barakāt al-Baghdādī, Awḥad al-Zamān
Hibat Allāh ibn ʿAlī ibn Malkā, Jewish philosopher and physician 1.11; 10.58.4; 10.64.2; 10.66; 10.68.2.6; 10.81.4;
AⅠⅠ.5
Abū l-Barakāt ibn al-Quḍāʿī, physician
serving Saladin (d 598/1201) 14.37
Abū l-Barakāt ibn Shaʿyā, al-Muwaffaq, Jew-
ish physician of Egypt 14.41
Abū l-Bayān ibn al-Mudawwar, Karaite Jew-
ish physician of Egypt with the honorific name of al-Sadīd (the Well-Guided) 14.33
Abū Bishr, `ṭabīb` `al-ʿaẓīmiyyah`, physician in Egypt under al-Ḥākim 14.19
Abū Bishr al-Baqarī 10.29
Abū Bishr Mattā ibn Yūnān (`or` Yūnus), Chris-
tian Aristotelian translator (d. 328/940) 6.5.1; 10.18; 10.20; 10.21; 10.22.1.2; 15.1.2; 15.1.3
Abū Dāwūd Sulaymān ibn Ḥassān al- Andalusī `see` Ibn Juljul
Abū Dhiʾb, transmitter 7.5.2
Abū Dhuʾayb al-Hudhalī, poet (d. ca. 26/647) 15.50.5n
Abū Dulaf al-Qāsim ibn ʿĪsā ibn Idrīs, 2nd– 3rd/8th–9th-c. commander, poet and
musician 8.20.11
Abū l-Faḍāʾil ibn al-Nāqid, Egyptian physi-
cian known as al-Muhadhdhab 14.34; 14.43.2
Abū l-Faḍāʾil Muḥammad ibn Nāmāwar al- Khūnajī `see` al-Khūnajī
Abū l-Faḍl, transmitter, unidentified pupil of Abū l-Barakāt 10.66.3
Abū l-Faḍl Aḥmad ibn Abī Ṭāhir Ṭayfūr, liter- ary man and historian 8.10.2n; 8.26.17n Abū l-Faḍl al-ʿĀriḍ, physician 11.16 nos. 1.3, 1.13
Abū l-Faḍl Ḥasdāy ibn Yūsuf `see` Ḥasdāy ibn
Yūsuf
Abū l-Faḍl ibn ʿAbd al-Karīm al-Muhandis,
geometrician and physician 15.33
Abū l-Faḍl ibn Abī Sulaymān, Christian phys-
ician of Egypt (d. 644/1246) 14.53 Abū l-Faḍl ibn al-Milḥī, patient of Abū l-
Ḥakam 15.8.1
Abū l-Faḍl Ismāʿīl ibn Abī l-Waqqār, physi-
cian 15.12
Abū l-Faḍl al-Isrāʾīlī, teacher of Muhadhdhab
al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Raḥīm ibn ʿAlī 15.50.5 Abū l-Faḍl Kutayfāt, student of Ibn al-Ṭayyib 10.37.4
Abū l-Faḍl Sulaymān ibn Muḥammad ibn ʿAlī
al-Mawṣilī al-Ṣūfī, probably ʿAbd al-Laṭīf al-Baghdādī’s paternal uncle Sulaymān (b. 528/1133) 15.40.1
Abū l-Falāḥ, student of Aḥmad ibn Abī l- Ashʿath 10.46.2
Abū l-Faraj ʿAbd Allāh ibn al-Ṭayyib see Ibn al-Ṭayyib
Abū l-Faraj ʿAlī ibn al-Ḥusayn ibn Muḥam- mad al-Iṣfahānī (`or` al-Iṣbahānī), author of `K.` `al-Aghānī` 7.1.6n; 7.2.3; 7.5.2; 7.5.4n; 7.5.5n; 7.10; 8.3.23; 8.4.7n; 8.7n; 8.26.14n; 8.29.11n; 15.33 no. 3; 15.50.7 no.2
Abū l-Faraj al-Ḥusayn ibn Muḥammad al- Mastūr, poet 10.64.19.5n
Abū l-Faraj ibn Abī l-Faḍāʾil ibn al-Nāqid 14.34.1
Abū l-Faraj ibn Abī Saʿīd al-Yamāmī, physi- cian of Hamadan 10.35; 11.13.8 no. 88
Abū l-Faraj ibn al-Ḥadīd, transmitter 15.3.1.1 Abū l-Faraj ibn Ḥayyān, maternal uncle of
Ibn al-Muṭrān (d. 578/1191) 15.3.1.4 Abū l-Faraj ibn al-Ṭayyib `see` Ibn al-Ṭayyib,
Abū l-Faraj
Abū l-Faraj (al-Naṣrānī), Christian physician
serving under Ṣalāḥ al-Dīn and al-Malik
al-Afḍal Nūr al-Dīn ʿAlī 15.23.1.2; 15.28 Abū l-Faraj Ṣāʿid ibn Hibat Allāh ibn Tūmā,
physician (d. 620/1223) 10.77
Abū l-Faraj Yaḥyā ibn Saʿīd ibn Yaḥyā 10.36
{388}
Abū l-Faraj Yaḥyā ibn Ṣāʿid ibn Yaḥyā ibn al- Tilmīdh, physician `see` Ibn al-Tilmīdh, Muʿtamad al-Mulk
Abū l-Faraj Yaʿqūb ibn Killis, Jewish vizier of Fatimid al-ʿAzīz (318–380/930–991) 14.14
Abū l-Fatḥ ibn Muhannā al-Naṣrānī, uniden-
tified Christian 15.27
Abū l-Fatḥ Manṣūr ibn Sahlān ibn Muqash-
shir `see` Ibn Muqashshir
Abū l-Fatḥ al-Nīsābūrī 10.38.4
Abū l-Fatḥ ʿUthmān ibn Jinnī see Ibn Jinnī Abū Firās al-Ḥamdānī, poet (d. 357/968) 15.49.6.2n
Abū Ghālib al-ʿAṭṭār, protector of Ibn Sīnā 11.13.3.7
Abū Ghālib Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad ibn Sahl
ibn Bashrān al-Naḥwī al-Wāsiṭī, transmit-
ter 7.2.3; 7.5.2
Abū Ghālib Muḥammad ibn al-Mubārak ibn
Muḥammad ibn Muḥammad ibn May-
mūn, transmitter 7.2.3; 7.5.2 Abū Ghānim, father of Abū Muslim 8.10.4
Abū Ghānim al-ʿAbbās ibn Sunbāṭ, Biṭrīq al-Baṭāriqah 10.44.5 no. 11
Abū l-Ghawth ibn Niḥrīr al-Munayḥī, 4th– 5th/10th–11th-c. poet 10.64.19.5n
Abū l-Ghiṭrīf al-Biṭrīq, patriarch of Armenia 10.44.4; 10.44.5 nos. 4, 8, 9, 19
Abū Ḥafṣ al-Kirmānī, author of `Akhbār` a􏱌]
Ban􏱎kh􏲡ag 12.5n
Abū Ḥafṣ ʿUmar ibn Yaḥyā al-Hintātī (`or` Īntī),
companion of Ibn Tūmart 13.66.3 Abū l-Ḥajjāj Yūsuf ibn Yaḥyā ibn Isḥāq
al-Sabtī al-Maghribī `see` Yūsuf al-Isrāʾīlī
Abū l-Ḥajjāj Yūsuf, Shihāb al-Dīn, oculist in
Egypt, teacher of ⅠAU’s father ca. 1200 15.51.1
Abū l-Ḥajjāj Yūsuf ibn Mūrāṭīr, Andalusian physician 13.68; 13.69; 13.81.1; 13.87
Abū Ḥakam, Christian physician serving Muʿāwiyah 7.6
Abū l-Ḥakam ibn Ghalindū (son of Galindo), Andalusian physician and poet 13.73
Abū l-Ḥakam ʿUbayd Allāh ibn al-Muẓaffar ibn ʿAbd Allāh, physician and poet
(d. 549/1155) 15.8; 15.17
Abū l-Ḥākim Isḥāq ibn Yūḥannā, physician from Ahwāz, 11.16 no. 1.33
Abū Ḥāmid Muḥammad al-Ṭūsī al-Ghazālī `see` al-Ghazālī
Abū Ḥanīfah al-Dīnawarī (d. 282–283/896), author of `K.` `al-Nabāt` 13.64.1; 15.40.9
no. 34; 15.50.5
Abū l-Ḥārith al-Usquf (‘the Bishop’), contem-
porary of Ibn al-Kattānī 13.29.2
Abū l-Ḥasan, son of Ibn Muqlah 10.5.4 Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAbd al-Raḥmān ibn Khalaf ibn
ʿAsākir al-Dārimī, Andalusian physician 13.44
Abū l-Ḥasan Aḥmad ibn Muḥammad al- Ṭabarī, 4th/10th-c. physician 11.6
Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī, al-Shaykh al-Sadīd Egyp- tian physician, 14.31.1
Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn al-ʿAbbās ibn Fasānjas (`or` Fasānajis) `see` Ibn Fasānjas
Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn ʿAbd al-Raḥīm al-ʿAṣṣār (d. 576/1180), teacher of Ibn al-Muʾammil 10.78
Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Abī ʿAbd Allāh ʿĪsā ibn
Hibat Allāh al-Naqqāsh al-Baghdādī `see`
Muhadhdhab al-Dīn ibn al-Naqqāsh
Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Aḥmad (`or` Muḥammad)
ibn al-Ḥusayn ibn Maḥmawayh al-Shāfiʿī
al-Yazdī, transmitter 7.2.3; 7.5.2
Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn al-Ḥusayn al-Ḥusaynī,
patron of Ibn Sīnā 11.13.8 no. 19
Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Ibrāhīm ibn Baks `see` ʿAlī
ibn Ibrāhīm ibn Baks
Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn ʿĪsā ibn Dāʾūd ibn al-Jarrāḥ `see` ʿAlī ibn ʿĪsā
Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Muḥammad al-Madāʾinī,
transmitter 10.2.2.2
Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Riḍwān `see` Ibn Riḍwān Abū l-Ḥasan al-ʿĀmirī `see` al-ʿĀmirī, Abū l-
Ḥāsan
Abū l-Ḥasan al-Baṣrī (? = Abū l-Ḥusayn al-Baṣrī, Muʿtazilite theologian) 10.37.4; 10.38.4
Abū l-Ḥasan al-Ḥarrānī `see` Abū l-Ḥasan Thābit ibn Ibrāhīm ibn Zahrūn
Abū l-Ḥasan Hibat Allāh ibn Saʿd ibn Hibat Allāh (Rāḍī al-Dawlah Abū Naṣr ibn Hibat Allāh ibn Ṣāʾid), son of Amīn al-Dawlah Ibn al-Tilmīdh, Iraqi physi- cian 15.40
{389}{!}
Abū l-Ḥasan ibn al-Āmidī, shaykh of al-Mubashshir ibn Fātik 10.22 Abū l-Ḥasan ibn Dalīl, physician 11.16
no. 1.18
Abū l-Ḥasan ibn Ghazāl ibn Abī Saʿīd `see`
Amīn al-Dawlah Abū l-Ḥasan Ibn Ghazāl
ibn Abī Saʿīd
Abū l-Ḥasan ibn Hūd, ʿAḍūd al-Dawlah, Hūdī
ruler in Murcia and Seville 13.87n Abū l-Ḥasan ibn Nafīs, teacher of Ibrahim
ibn Baks 6.5.1; 9.37n; 9.49n
Abū l-Ḥasan ibn Saʿīd (? = Abū l-Ḥusayn
Aḥmad ibn Saʿīd), physician 11.16 no. 1.33
Abū l-Ḥasan ibn Tuffāḥ, surgeon at the ʿAḍudī Hospital 11.5.6
Abū l-Ḥasan Muḥammad ibn ʿAlī (? = Abū l-Ḥasan Muḥammad ibn ʿAlī ibn ʿUmar, 5th/11th-c. poet) 8.6 no. 3
Abū l-Ḥasan Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad, secret- ary to Abū Ghānim al-ʿAbbās 10.44.5
no. 13
Abū l-Ḥasan al-Qudūrī, Ḥanafī jurist
(d. 428/1037) 10.38.4
Abū l-Ḥasan al-Ṣābiʾī (?) 10.38.4
Abū l-Ḥasan Sahlān ibn ʿUthmān ibn Kaysān
`see` Sahlān
Abū l-Ḥasan Sufyān, unidentified collabor-
ator of Ibn Bājjah 13.59.4 no. 21
Abū l-Ḥasan Ṭāhir ibn Aḥmad ibn Bābashādh `see` Ibn Bābashādh, Abū l-Ḥasan Ṭāhir ibn
Aḥmad
Abū l-Ḥasan Thābit ibn Ibrāhīm ibn Zahrūn
al-Ḥarrānī, (d. 365/976) 10.8; 10.38.1 Abū l-Ḥasan Yūsuf (ibn Ibrāhīm al-Ḥābis ibn
al-Dāyah) 8.26.14
Abū Hāshim ʿAbd al-Salām, son of al-Jubbāʾī,
Muʿtazilite theologian (d. 321/933) 14.22.4.3 no. 20; 14.22.5.1 no. 8n
Abū Hāshim al-Masrūr the Elder (al-Kabīr), courtier of Hārūn al-Rashīd 8.3.16; 12.6
Abū Ḥātim al-Balkhī, otherwise unknown
translator, presumably from Persian into
`Bad`trian 12.3 no. 1
Abū Ḥāzim al-Qāḍī, recipient of a treatise by
al-Rāzī 11.5.25 no. 35
Abū Hilāl al-Ḥimṣī, physician, father of Hilāl
ibn Abī Hilāl al-Ḥimṣī 9.15n
Abū l-Hudhayl Muḥammad ibn al-Hudhayl al-ʿAllāf al-Baṣrī, 3rd/9th-c. Muʿtazilite theologian 4.2
Abū Ḥulayqah `see` Rashīd al-Dīn Abū Ḥulayqah
Abū l-Ḥusayn Aḥmad ibn Saʿīd, physician 11.16 no. 1.25
Abū l-Ḥusayn (`or` Abū l-Ḥasan) ʿAlī ibn Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd al-Raḥīm ibn Dīnār al-Kātib, transmitter 7.2.3; 7.5.2
Abū l-Ḥusayn al-ʿArūḍī, contemporary of Ibn Sīnā 11.13.2.10; 11.13.8 no. 6
Abū l-Ḥusayn ibn Asdūn `see` al-Maṣdūm Abū l-Ḥusayn ibn Kashkarāyā, physician and
pupil of Sinān ibn Thābit 8.5.3; 10.23.2; 10.31; 11.5.6
Abū l-Ḥusayn ibn ʿUmar ibn al-Daḥlī (al- Dakhlī?) 10.29
Abū l-Ḥusayn ʿUmar ibn ʿAbd Allāh al-Daḥlī (perhaps identical with the preceding) 10.28
Abū l-Ḥusayn (or Abū l-Ḥasan) al-Sahlī (al-Suhaylī), Aḥmad ibn Muḥammad, vizier to Maʾmūnid Khwārazm-Shāhs at Gurganj (d. 418/1027) 11.13.2.11; 11.13.8 nos. 31, 49, 52, 93
Abū l-Ḥusayn al-Wārid, physician 11.16
no. 1.6
Abū l-Ḥusayn Yūsuf, probably written in
error for Abū l-Ḥasan Yūsuf
Abū l-ʿIbar, Abū l-ʿAbbās Muḥammad ibn
Aḥmad ibn ʿAbd Allāh al-Hāshimī, known as Abū l-ʿIbar, burlesque poet (d. 252/866) 8.26.5
Abū ʿImrān ibn Abī ʿImrān al-Martalī,
unidentified jurist and ascetic who lived in Seville (perhaps Abū ʿImrān Mūsā ibn ʿAbd al-Raḥmān ibn Khalaf al-ʿAbdarī) 13.62.3; 13.63.8.1
Abū ʿĪsā Aḥmad ibn Hārūn, brother of al-Maʾmūn 8.3.5
Abū ʿĪsā Baqiyyah, physician at the ʿAḍudī
Hospital 11.5.6
Abū Isḥāq ibn Hūd Sharaf al-Dawlah, Hūdī
ruler in Murcia and Seville 13.87n
Abū Isḥāq ibn Ṭumlūs, Andalusian physician 13.84
Abū Isḥāq Ibrāhīm al-Dānī, Andalusian phys- ician 13.71
{390}
Abū Isḥāq Ibrāhīm ibn Baks `see` Ibrāhīm ibn Baks
Abū Isḥāq Ibrāhīm ibn Hilāl al-Ṣābiʾ
(d. 384/994), head of the chancery in Baghdad during the Būyid period 10.3.7; 10.4.9 no. 11; 11.13.3.13
Abū Isḥāq Ibrāhīm ibn al-Mahdī `see` Ibrāhīm
ibn al-Mahdī
Abū Isḥāq Ibrāhīm ibn Muḥammad `see` Ibn
al-Mudabbir, Abū Isḥāq Ibrāhīm
Abū Isḥāq Ibrāhīm ibn Sinān `see` Ibrāhīm ibn
Sinān ibn Thābit ibn Qurrah
Abū Isḥāq Ibrāhīm ibn Zahrūn al-Ḥarrānī,
(d. 309/921) 10.7
Abū Isḥāq Muḥammad ibn Hārūn, brother of
al-Maʾmūn `see` al-Muʿtaṣim bi-Allāh Abū Isḥāq al-Shīrāzī, author of `A Guide`` to`
`Jurisprudence` 15.21
Abū ʿIṣmah al-Shīʿī (`or` al-Shaʿbī, al-Shabīʿī,
al-Subayʿī?), captain of the guard under
al-Amīn 8.3.17
Abū l-ʿIzz al-Mawṣilī, scholar of Qurʾanic
sciences, probably Yūsuf, father of ʿAbd
al-Laṭīf al-Baghdādī 15.40.1
Abū Jābir al-Maghribī, unidentified author
quoted by Ibn al-Muṭrān 1.2
Abū Jaʿfar Aḥmad ibn Ḥassān, Andalusian
physician 13.74
Abū Jaʿfar Aḥmad ibn Ibrāhīm ibn Abī Khālid
`see` Ibn al-Jazzār
Abū Jaʿfar Aḥmad ibn Muḥammad ibn al-Ḥasan, unidentified physician 11.16 nos. 1.10, 1.11
Abū Jaʿfar Aḥmad ibn Sābiq, Andalusian physician 13.82
Abū Jaʿfar Aḥmad ibn Yūsuf ibn Ibrāhīm `see` Ibn al-Dāyah
Abū Jaʿfar ibn al-Ghazāl, Andalusian physi- cian 13.63.7; 13.79
Abū Jaʿfar ibn Hārūn al-Turjālī, Andalusian physician 13.65; 13.66.3
Abū Jaʿfar ibn Khamīs al-Ṭulayṭulī, Andalus- ian physician 13.43
Abū Jaʿfar ibn al-Qāsim ibn ʿUbayd Allāh, member of the Banū Wahb, vizier to al- Qāhir bi-Allāh (d. 321/933) 10.8.8
Abū Jaʿfar al-Dhahabī, Aḥmad ibn Jurayj, physician (d. 600/1203–1204) 13.63.3; 13.85
Abū Jaʿfar Muḥammad ibn al-ʿAbbās, poet 15.46.3.8n
Abū Jaʿfar Muḥammad ibn Jarīr ibn Yazīd al-Ṭabarī, historian and Qurʾanic scholar 7.2.3; 8.3.14n; 8.3.15n; 8.3.16n; 8.3.17n; 8.3.22n; 8.4.7n; 8.20.5n; 8.20.6n; 8.20.7n; 8.20.10n; 8.20.11n; 8.24n
Abū Jaʿfar Muḥammad ibn al-Qāsim al- Karkhī, vizier 15.1.5 no. 35
Abū Jaʿfar Yūsuf ibn Aḥmad ibn Ḥasdāy `see` Yūsuf ibn Aḥmad ibn Ḥasdāy
Abū l-Jawāʾiz al-Ḥasan ibn ʿAlī al-Wāsiṭī, poet (d. 460/1067–1068) 10.6419.7n
Abū Jurayq (the Monk), late-antique medical writer 6.5.2
Abū Kāmil Shujāʿ ibn Aslam the Astrologer, mathematician (active 3rd–4th/9th–10th c.) 10.1.7
Abū l-Karam, physician 15.3.1.1; 15.3.1.4 Abū l-Karam, possibly identical with Abū
l-Kirām 15.51.10.3
Abū Kathīr ibn al-Zaffān `see` Ifrāʾīm (Eph-
raim) ibn al-Zaffān
Abū Kathīr Ifrāʾīm ibn al-Ḥasan ibn Isḥāq ibn
Ibrāhīm ibn Yaʿqūb `see` Ifrāʾīm (Ephraim)
ibn al-Zaffān
Abū l-Khaṭṭāb Muḥammad ibn Muḥammad
ibn Abī Ṭālib, Iraqi physician 10.37.4; 10.58.2; 10.60; 11.8.3
Abū l-Khayr, blood-letter 15.3.1.1
Abū l-Khayr, surgeon at the ʿAḍudī Hospital 11.5.6
Abū l-Khayr al-Ḥasan ibn Suwār ibn Bābā `see`
Ibn al-Khammār
Abū l-Khayr ibn Abī Sulaymān Dāwūd, al-Fāris (the knight), son of Abū Sulaymān Dāwūd ibn Abī l-Munā ibn Abī Fānah 14.49.3; 14.54.3; 14.54.4; 14.54.14; 14.54.15 Abū l-Khayr al-Masīḥī, physician to caliph
al-Nāṣir li-Dīn Allāh 10.76.2; 10.76.3 Abū l-Khayr Salāmah ibn Mubārak ibn Raḥ- mūn ibn Mūsā `see` Salāmah ibn Raḥmūn
Abū Khurāsān `see` Faraj
Abū l-Kirām, unidentified 15.51.10.2(p); 15.51.10.3
Abū Lahab, nickname of one of Muḥam-
mad’s uncles 15.37.4(p)
Abū l-Maʿālī al-Sulamī, poet also known as
Shaftar 15.8.10
{391}
Abū l-Maʿālī ibn Tammām, physician of Saladin and his brother al-Malik al-ʿĀdil Abū Bakr ibn Ayyūb 14.38
Abū Māhir Mūsā ibn Yūsuf ibn Sayyār, Iraqi physician 10.24
Abū l-Majd ibn Abī l-Ḥakam, physician, astronomer, geometrician 15.8.4, 15.8.15; 15.9; 15.33
Abū Manṣūr Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad al-Azharī (d. 370/980), lexicographer 11.13.3.13
Abū Manṣūr Buwayh (`or` Būyah) ibn Bahāʾ al-Dawlah, emir of emirs, Būyid dynasty 11.10
Abū Manṣūr al-Ḥasan ibn Nūḥ al-Qumrī (`or`
al-Qamarī) `see` al-Qumrī
Abū Manṣūr ibn Zaylā, student of Ibn Sīnā 11.3.8 no. 39
Abū Manṣūr Ismāʿīl ibn al-Ḥāfiẓ al-Dīn Allāh
`see` al-Ẓāfir bi-Amr Allāh
Abū Manṣūr al-Jabbān, grammarian 11.13.3.13; 11.13.7n; 11.13.8 no. 21
Abū Manṣūr Mawhūb ibn Aḥmad `see` al-Jawālīqī
Abū Manṣūr Mumahhid al-Dawlah Saʿīd,
Marwānid Emir of Diyarbakr (nd􏲉. 997– 1011) 10.27
Abū Manṣūr al-Naṣrānī, Christian physician
under Ṣalāḥ al-Dīn 5.26; 15.26; 15.43.2 Abū Manṣūr Naṣr ibn Hārūn, companion of
ʿAḍud al-Dawlah 10.8.10
Abū Manṣūr al-Thaʿālibi `see` al-Thaʿālibi Abū Marīn al-Bajjān, unidentified contem-
porary of Ibn al-Kattānī 13.29.2
Abū Marwān ʿAbd al-Malik ibn Qablāl 13.70 Abū Marwān ʿAbd al-Malik ibn Muḥammad
ibn Zuhr `see` Ibn Zuhr, Abū Marwān ʿAbd
al-Malik
Abū Marwān ʿAbd al-Malik ibn Abī l-ʿAlāʾ ibn
Zuhr `see` Ibn Zuhr, Abū Marwān ʿAbd al-Malik ibn Abī l-ʿAlāʾ
Abū Marwān Aḥmad al-Bājī, son of the qadi
Abū Marwān Muḥammad al-Bājī 13.63.8.2
Abū Marwān ibn Zuhr `see` Ibn Zuhr, Abū Marwān
Abū Marwān Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad ibn ʿAbd al-Malik al-Lakhmī al-Bājī, Sevillian jurist and informant of ⅠAU 13.59.3; 13.62.2.3; 13.63.2; 13.63.5; 13.63.7; 13.63.8.1; 13.63.8.2; 13.64.2.1; 13.64.2.2; 13.64.2.3; 13.65; 13.66.3; 13.66.4; 13.68.2; 13.80.2
Abū Maʿshar Jaʿfar ibn Muḥammad ibn ʿUmar al-Balkhī, astronomer and astro- loger in Baghdad 2.1.1; 2.1.3; 2.1.4; 10.1.5; 10.1.6; 10.1.9; 10.1.14 no. 63; 11.3; 12.1 Abū l-Maymūn ʿAbd al-Majīd ibn al-Amīr Abī l-Qāsim Muḥammad ibn al-Imām
al-Mustanṣir bi-Allāh `see` al-Ḥāfiẓ li-Dīn
Allāh
Abū Mayyah, relative of Abū Nuwās’ mistress
Janān 8.19.3
Abū Muḥammad ʿAbd Allāh ibn Rushd, son
of Ibn Rushd 13.66.5; 13.67
Abū Muḥammad ʿAbd Allāh ibn ʿAbd al-Wāḥid, governor of Ifrīqiyah 13.66.3 Abū Muḥammad ʿAbd Allāh ibn Aḥmad al-Mālaqī al-Nabātī `see` Ibn al-Bayṭār
Abū Muḥammad ʿAbd Allāh ibn ʿAlī ibn al-Ḥusayn ibn ʿAbd al-Khāliq `see` al-Ṣāḥib
Ṣafī al-Dīn ibn Shukr
Abū Muḥammad ʿAbd Allāh ibn Isḥāq al-Madīnī, unidentified physician 11.16 nos. 1.35, 1.36, 1.37, 1.38
Abū Muḥammad ʿAbd Allāh ibn al-Mawlā Abī l-Ḥajjāj Yūsuf ibn al-Imām al-Ḥāfiẓ li-Dīn Allāh `see` al-ʿĀḍid li-Dīn Allāh
Abū Muḥammad ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz ibn Aḥmad ibn Muḥammad al-Kinānī, transmitter 10.81.3
Abū Muḥammad ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz ibn al-Nafīs
ibn Hibat Allāh ibn Wahbān al-Sulamī (= Shams al-ʿArab al-Baghdādī), patient of ⅠAU’s father 15.51.3
Abū Muḥammad ʿAbd al-Raḥmān ibn ʿUth- mān ibn Abī Naṣr, transmitter 10.81.3 Abū Muḥammad Badr ibn Abī l-Iṣbaʿ, ‘the
secretary’ 8.4.6; 8.4.7
Abū Muḥammad al-Ḥasan ibn al-Ḥusayn
[ibn ʿAlī ibn al-ʿAbbās ibn Ismāʿīl ibn Abī Sahl ibn Nawbakht] al-Nawbakhtī, scribe and traditionist (d. 402/1012) 10.8.7
Abū Muḥammad al-Ḥasan ibn Muḥammad, Chief Judge 10.44.5 no. 14
Abū Muḥammad ibn al-Ḥafīd Abī Bakr ibn Zuhr `see` Ibn Zuhr, Abū Muḥammad ibn al-Ḥafīd
{392}{!}
Abū Muḥammad ibn al-Jaʿdī, Fatimid astrolo- ger 15.51.1
Abū Muḥammad ibn Abī Jaʿfar, physician 11.16 no. 1.12
Abū Muḥammad ibn Rizq al-Ḥāfiẓ, Andalusī jurist 13.66.1
Abū Muḥammad ibn Rushd `see` Abū Muḥammad ʿAbd Allāh ibn Rushd
Abū Muḥammad al-Shadhūnī, Andalusian physician 13.62.3; 13.76
Abū Muḥammad al-Shīrāzī, patron of Ibn Sīnā at Jurjān 11.13.3.1; 11.13.8 nos. 8, 9, 10
Abū Muḥammad al-Ṣilḥī, secretary to al-Muṭīʿ li-Allāh 10.29
Abū l-Musayyab Fahd ibn Sulaymān 10.8.7
Abū Muslim, Abbasid revolutionary
murdered by al-Manṣūr 8.10.4
Abū Muslim Muḥammad ibn Baḥr, physician 11.16 no. 1.38
Abū l-Muẓaffar, unidentified 10.64.19.2(p) Abū l-Nadā Ḥassān ibn Numayr al-Kalbī `see`
ʿArqalah
Abū l-Najāʾ Sālim ibn Hūd ʿImād al-Dawlah,
Hūdī ruler of Murcia and Seville 13.81.2; 13.81.2n; 13.87
Abū l-Najīb, probably Ḍiyāʾ al-Dīn Abū l- Najīb al-Suhrawardī ʿAbd al-Qāhir ibn ʿAbd Allāh ibn al-Bakrī, Sunnī mystic (490/1097–563/1168) 15.40.3
Abū l-Najm (al-Naṣrānī), ibn Abī Ghālib ibn Fahd ibn Manṣūr ibn Wahb ibn Qays ibn Mālik. Christian physician in Damascus 15.27
Abū Naṣr ʿAbd Allāh al-Ḥusayn al-Qayrawānī, kātib al-inshāʾ with the Fatimid caliph al-ʿAzīz bi-Allāh AⅠⅠ.11
Abū Naṣr ʿAdnān ibn al-ʿAynzarbī `see` Ibn al- ʿAynzarbī
Abū Naṣr Asʿad ibn Ilyās ibn al-Muṭrān `see` Ibn al-Muṭrān
Abū Naṣr al-Fārābī `see` al-Fārābī
Abū Naṣr ibn Abī Sulaymān, 12th–13th-c.
Christian physician of Egypt 14.52 Abū Naṣr ibn al-Daḥlī, oculist at the ʿAḍudī
Hospital 11.5.6
Abū Naṣr ibn al-Masīhī `see` Abū Naṣr Saʿīd
ibn Abī l-Khayr
Abū Naṣr ibn Nārī ibn Ayyūb, translator 9.17
Abū Naṣr Ismāʿīl ibn Ḥammād al-Jawharī `see` al-Jawharī, Abū Naṣr
Abū Naṣr Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad ibn Jahīr, Kāfī al-Kufāh (d. 483/1046–1047) 10.40; 15.40.3
Abū Naṣr Muḥammad ibn Muḥammad ibn
Awzalagh ibn Ṭarkhān al-Fārābī `see` al-Fārābī
Abū Naṣr Sābūr ibn Ardashīr, 4th/10th-c. viz-
ier 8.5.3n
Abū Naṣr al-Saʿdī, poet 10.64.19.7n
Abū Naṣr Saʿīd ibn Abī l-Khayr ibn ʿĪsā ibn
al-Masīḥī, physician 10.76
Abū Naṣr Yaḥyā ibn Jarīr al-Takrītī 10.40; 10.70
Abū Nuwās al-Ḥasan ibn Hāniʾ al-Ḥakamī,
poet (d. ca. 198/813) 4.6.10n; 8.3.23; 8.19.3; 8.29.1n; 8.29.22n; 15.40.4n
Abū l-Qāsim ʿAbd al-Raḥmān ibn ʿAlī `see` Ibn Abī Ṣādiq al-Nīsābūrī
Abū l-Qāsim ʿAbd al-Raḥmān ibn al-Ḥusayn ibn ʿAlī ibn Abī l-ʿAqib, transmitter 10.81.3
Abū l-Qāsim Aḥmad ibn ʿAlī ibn Baḥr, physi-
cian 11.16 no. 1.4
Abū l-Qāsim ʿAlī ibn Sulaymān, Ibn al-Ṣayrafī, Fatimid off􏲊cial (d. 532/1147) 13.58.3.1; 13.58.3.2
Abū l-Qāsim ʿAlī ibn Ṭirād al-Zaynabī, al- Sharīf, 􏱋am􏲞b a􏱌]􏱋qmab􏱎􏱏 (d. 561/1166) 10.68.2.7n
Abū l-Qāsim ʿAlī ibn Yaʿqūb ibn Ibrāhīm ibn
Abī l-ʿAqib, transmitter 10.81.3
Abū l-Qāsim al-Balkhī, ʿAbd Allāh ibn Aḥmad ibn Maḥmūd (d. 319/931) 11.5.25. nos. 79, 81
Abū l-Qāsim Fayd ibn Najm, contemporary of
Ibn al-Kattānī 13.29.2
Abū l-Qāsim Ghānim ibn Abī l-ʿAlāʾ al-Iṣbahānī, 4th/10th `or` 5th/11th-c. poet 15.52.1.2n
Abū l-Qāsim Hibat Allāh ibn al-Faḍl (= Ibn al-Qaṭṭān), poet and physician (d. 558/1163) 10.64.19.16; 10.68; AⅠⅠ.6
Abū l-Qāsim ibn Abī Dulaf 11.5.25 no. 191 Abū l-Qāsim ibn ʿAlī ibn ʿĪsā, son of vizier of
al-Muqtadir 14.22.4.4
Abū l-Qāsim ibn Manẓūr, chief qadi of
Seville 13.61.3.2
{393}
Abū l-Qāsim ibn Sulaymān al-Ṣayrafī (d. 542/1147), Egyptian author who worked for the Fatimid chancellery 13.58.3.1; 13.58.3.2
Abū l-Qāsim ʿĪsā ibn al-Ẓāfir bi-Amr Allāh `see`
al-Fāʾiz bi-Naṣr Allāh
Abū l-Qāsim Ismāʿīl ibn Aḥmad ibn al-Samarqandī, teacher of Muhadhdhab
al-Dīn ibn Habal 10.81.1; 10.81.3 Abū l-Qāsim al-Karakānī, transmitter 15.51.7
Abū l-Qāsim al-Kirmānī, contemporary of
Ibn Sīnā 11.13.3.15
Abū l-Qāsim al-Maʿājīnī al-Andalusī,
unidentified contemporary of ⅠAU 13.62.2.1
Abū l-Qāsim al-Maghribī, al-Ḥusayn ibn ʿAlī ibn al-Ḥusayn, politician and scholar
(d. 418/1027) 10.13.3
Abū l-Qāsim Maslamah ibn Aḥmad `see` al- Majrīṭī
Abū l-Qāsim Ṣāʿid ibn Aḥmad ibn Ṣāʿid al- Andalūsī `see` Ṣāʿid al-Andalūsī
Abū l-Qāsim al-Sharīʿī, unidentified philo- sopher 15.40.3
Abū l-Qāsim Tammām ibn Muḥammad al- Rāzī, transmitter 10.81.3
Abū l-Qāsim ʿUbayd Allāh ibn Sulaymān, member of the Banū Wahb family of viz- iers (d. 288/901) 10.3.14 no. 81
Abū l-Qāsim ʿUmar ibn al-Ḥuṣayn, Hadith scholar 15.13
Abū l-Qāsim Yaḥyā ibn Thābit al-Wakīl, teacher of ʿAbd al-Laṭīf al-Baghdādī 15.40.1
Abū Qubayl al-Hindī (`or` T-w-q-sh-t-l al-Hindī), otherwise unknown Indian
medical author 12.2 no. 14
Abū Quraysh ʿĪsā al-Ṣaydalānī `see` ʿĪsā, known
as Abū Quraysh
Abū l-Rabīʿ al-Kafīf, unidentified Andalusī
scholar exiled to Lucena 13.66.3 Abū l-Rajāʾ, unidentified transmitter 15.3.1.1
Abū l-Rayḥān al-Bīrūnī `see` al-Bīrūnī
Abū l-Rāzī Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd al-Ḥamīd,
prefect of al-Baṣrah during governorship
of Hārūn al-Rashīd 8.3.15
Abū Saʿd Aḥmad ibn ʿAbd al-Jabbār ibn
Aḥmad ibn Abī l-Qāsim al-Ṣayrafī al- Baghdādī, transmitter (d. 517/1123–1124) 7.2.3; 7.5.2
Abū Sahl al-Kūhī, 4th/10th-c. astronomer 10.4.9 no. 19
Abū Sahl al-Masīḥī, Christian physician
(d. 401/1010) 10.64.20 nos. 13, 17; 11.12; 11.13.8 no. 22; 11.20
Abū Sahl ibn Nawbakht, member of the Nawbakht family of courtiers (real name Kharkhashā Damāh Ṭīmādhāh Mādhar- iyād Khusraw Abhamshād), associate of al-Manṣūr 8.9
Abū Saʿīd al-Ḥasan ibn Aḥmad ibn ʿAlī [al- Ṭabīb] 10.13.5
Abū Saʿīd ibn Abī l-Khayr [al-Ṣūfī] 11.13.6; 11.13.8 no. 85
Abū Saʿīd ibn Abī Sulaymān, al-Muhadh- dhab, Christian physician in Egypt (d.
ca. 613/1216) 14.49.2; 14.50; 14.51.1; 14.54.2; 14.54.3; 14.54.14
Abū Saʿīd ibn al-Muʿawwaj, 5th/11th-c. off􏲊cial 10.61
Abū Saʿīd ibn Muwaffaq al-Dīn Yaʿqūb `see`
Rashīd al-Dīn Abū Saʿīd ibn Muwaffaq
al-Dīn Yaʿqūb
Abū Saʿīd Mujīr al-Dīn Abaq Atabeg
Ṭughtakīn, Būrid ruler of Damascus
(d. 564/1169) 15.8.1
Abū Saʿīd ʿUthmān al-Dimashqī, translator;
perhaps identical with Abū ʿUthmān Saʿīd
ibn Yaʿqūb al-Dimashqī
Abū Saʿīd Wahb ibn Ibrāhīm, secretary to
al-Muṭīʿ li-Allāh 10.29
Abū Saʿīd al-Yamāmī 10.34; 10.38.4; 11.13.8
no. 23
Abū Salamah Sallām al-Abrash `see` Sallām
al-Abrash
Abū Ṣāliḥ Manṣūr ibn Isḥāq ibn Aḥmad ibn
Asad al-Sāmānī (d. 302/915), patron of
al-Rāzī 11.5.9; 11.5.19n; 11.5.25 no. 90 Abū Salīm, courtier of Hārūn al-Rashīd 12.6
Abū l-Ṣalt (active 10th-c.), bonesetter at the
ʿAḍudī Hospital 11.5.6
Abū l-Ṣalt Umayyah ibn ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz ibn Abī
l-Ṣalt al-Andalusī al-Ishbīlī, physician and poet (d. 528/1134) 13.58; 15.47n; 14.27.1; 14.27.2; 14.27.3
{394}{!}
Abū l-Sammāl al-Asadī, poet 7.10n Abū Ṣaqr Wahb ibn Muḥammad al-Kalwadhānī `see` Abū Ṣaqr Wahb ibn
Muḥammad
Abū l-Sarāyā al-Sarī ibn Manṣūr al-Shaybānī,
Shi’ite rebel 8.3.14n; 8.18.3
Abū Shākir ibn Abī Sulaymān, Christian
physician of Egypt (d. 613/1216) 14.51; 14.54.3; 14.54.4; 14.54.13
Abū Shās, poet 15.58.6n
Abū l-Shawk Fāris ibn Muḥammad ibn
ʿAnnāz (nd􏲉. 401–437/1010–1045) 11.13.3.4 Abū Simāk al-Asadī, poet 7.10
Abū Sufyān ibn Ḥarb ibn Umayyah, father of
Muʿāwiyah and opponent of Muḥammad 7.1.1; 7.2.1; 7.2.3
Abū Suhayl, transmitter 7.5.2
Abū Sulaym Faraj, Turkish `mawlā` of Hārūn
al-Rashīd and governor 12.6
Abū Sulaymān Dāwūd ibn Abī l-Munā ibn
Abī Fānah, Christian physician from Jeru-
salem serving Fatimids 14.49; 14.50n Abū Sulaymān ibn Bābashādh `see` Ibn
Bābashādh
Abū Sulaymān al-Manṭiqī `see` Abū Sulaymān
Muḥammad ibn Ṭāhir
Abū Sulaymān Muḥammad ibn Ṭāhir ibn
Bahrām al-Sijistānī, known as al-Manṭiqī, philosopher 1.5; 4.1.8.1n; 4.6.3.5; 2.1.1; 6.1.2; 8.29.5n; 8.30.6n; 11.7; 11.8. no. 13; 13.34.1; 15.1.3.1
Abū Ṭāhir Aḥmad ibn Muḥammad ibn
Aḥmad ibn Muḥammad ibn Ibrāhīm al- Silafī al-Iṣfahānī, teacher of Hadith 15.33
Abū Ṭāhir ibn ʿAbd al-Bāqī (known as Ibn
Qaṭramīz, ‘Son of Big Bottle’), scholar 8.6 no. 5
Abū Ṭāhir [Muḥammad] ibn Baqiyyah `see` Ibn Baqiyyah
Abū Ṭāhir ibn al-Barakhshī `see` Ibn al- Barakhshī
Abū Ṭāhir Ismāʿīl ibn Jumayʿ, son of Ibn Jumayʿ 14.32.5 no. 1n
Abū l-Ṭāhir Yaḥyā ibn Tamīm ibn Muʿizz ibn Bādīs, Zirid emir of Mahdia 13.58.4.3; 13.58.5 no. 1
Abū Ṭālib, uncle of ʿUmar ibn Maʿadd 13.3.2.1
Abū Ṭālib ibn ʿAbd al-Muṭṭalib, uncle of Muḥammad 15.46.2
Abū Ṭālib al-ʿAlawī, `al-wazīr`, unidentified vizier 11.13
Abū Tammām, poet (d. ca. 231/845) 7.2.3n; 8.29.15n; 10.68.1.4n; 15.22; 15.50.4n
Abū Tammām al-Bārid (‘the Cold One’), ʿAbd al-Wāḥid ibn al-Ḥusayn, 6th/12th-c. poet 10.68.2.5n
Abū l-Ṭayyib Azhar ibn al-Nuʿmān, uniden-
tified (? contemporary of Ibn Riḍwān
`or` = the Shi’ite theologian Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad b. Muḥammad ibn al-Nuʿmān al-Ḥārithī al-ʿUkbarī al-Mufīd) 14.25.9 no. 40
Abū l-Ṭayyib al-Ṭabarī, Shāfiʿite jurist
(d. 450/1058) 10.38.4
Abū Thughrah, Abū l-Qāsim ʿUbayd Allāh ibn
ʿAbd Allāh al-Iskāfī, 4th/10th-c. off􏲊cial 10.5.3
Abū l-Tuqā Ṣāliḥ ibn Aḥmad ibn Ibrāhīm
ibn al-Ḥasan ibn Sulaymān al-Qurashī a􏱌hao Taqī al-Dīn, teacher of ⅠAU’s paternal uncle 15.51.1
Abū ʿUbayd Allāh al-Faqīh (the Jurist), i.e. Aḥmad al-Maʿṣūmī 11.13.8 no. 98
Abū ʿUbayd al-Bakrī, ʿAbd Allāh ibn ʿAbd al- ʿAzīz, Andalusian geographer, historian (d. 487/1094) 7.1.5n; 7.5.5n; 7.5.6n; 8.3.16n; 13.53
Abū ʿUbayd al-Jūzjānī, pupil and amanuensis
of Ibn Sīnā 11.13.1; 11.13.2.11; 11.13.3.1; 11.13.8 Abū ʿUbayd al-Qāsim ibn Sallām al-Baghdādī, 8th-c. grammarian and Qurʾanic scholar 7.5.5; 15.40.3; 15.40.9
no.1
Abū ʿUthmān, relative of Abū Nuwās’ mis-
tress Janān 8.19.3
Abū ʿUthmān al-Jāḥiẓ `see` al-Jāḥiẓ
Abū ʿUthmān al-Jazzār al-Yābisah, contem-
porary of Ibn Juljul 13.36.2.3
Abū ʿUthmān al-Khālidī, 4th/10th-c. poet
and man of letters, brother of Abū Bakr
al-Khālidī 8.26.15
Abū ʿUthmān al-Maghribī, transmitter 15.51.7
Abū ʿUthmān Saʿīd ibn Ghālib `see` Saʿīd ibn
Ghālib
Abū ʿUthmān Saʿīd ibn Yaʿqūb al-Dimashqī,
{395}
translator and physician of ʿAlī ibn ʿĪsā
(active 302/924–925) 8.29.8; 9.36; 10.16 Abū l-Wafāʾ Maḥmūd al-Dawlah al-Mubash- shir ibn Fātik `see` al-Mubashshir ibn Fātik
Abū l-Walīd Hishām ibn Aḥmad ibn Hishām `see` Ibn al-Waqashī
Abū l-Walīd ibn al-Kattānī `see` Ibn al-Kattānī Abū l-Walīd Ibn Rushd `see` Ibn Rushd
Abū l-Waḥsh Wuḥaysh al-Asadī Sabʿ ibn
Khalaf, poet (d. 579/1184) 15.8.12
Abū Yaḥyā al-Marwazī, teacher of Abū Bishr
Mattā ibn Yūnus 10.20; 15.1.3.1
Abū Yaḥyā, son of Abū al-Qāsim al-Maghribī 10.13.3
Abū Yaḥyā, source of an anecdote about the
court of the caliph al-Mutawakkil 8.26.15
Abū Yaḥyā ibn Qāsim al-Ishbīlī, Andalusian physician 13.72
Abū Yaʿqūb al-Ahwāzī 10.32; 11.5.6
Abū Yaʿqūb al-Khuraymī, Isḥāq ibn Ḥassān, poet courtier of Hārūn al-Rashīd and al-Amīn (d. 214/829) 10.5
Abū Yaʿqūb ibn Yūsuf ibn ʿĪsā `see` Yūsuf al-Khūrī `or` al-Qass (the priest)
Abū Yaʿqūb Yūsuf `see` Yūsuf Ⅰ
Abū Yūsuf al-Kātib ‘the Secretary’, translator 9.29
Abū l-Ẓāhir Ismāʿīl, acquaintance of Ibn al- Muṭrān 15.23.1.3
Abū Zakariyyā Yaḥyā al-Bayyāsī `see` al-Bayyāsī Abū Zakariyyā Yaḥyā ibn ʿAdī the Logician
`see` Yaḥyā ibn ʿAdī
Abū Zakariyyā Yahūdā ibn Saʿādah `see` Ibn
Saʿādah
Abū Zakkār, singer under Hārūn al-Rashīd 8.3.16
Abū Zayd ʿAbd al-Raḥmān ibn Mūsā ibn
Yūjān, vizier of the Almohad ruler al-Manṣūr 13.63.7
Abū Zayd al-Anṣārī, 9th-c. grammarian and
lexicographer 7.1.1; 8.29.22n
Abū Zayd al-Balkhī, Aḥmad b. Sahl (d. 322/ 934), philosopher and contemporary of
al-Rāzī 11.5.9; 11.5.25 no. 125
Abū Zurʿah ʿAbd al-Raḥmān ibn ʿAmr ibn
ʿAbd Allāh ibn Ṣafwān al-Azdī al-Baṣrī,
transmitter 10.81.3
Abū Zurʿah Ṭāhir ibn Muḥammad ibn Ṭāhir
al-Maqdisī al-Hamadhānī, scholar of
Hadith (481/1088–566/1170) 15.40.1 Abuqrāṭ `see` Hippocrates
Achilles, legendary ancient Greek hero 4.4.2.3
Acratus ‘the musician’, Greek philosopher 4.1.11.3
Acron of Agrigento, prominent Empiricist
physician of antiquity 3.4
ʿĀd, legendary pre-Islamic Arabian people 7.1.1n; 14.32.4(p); 15.17(p)
Adam, first man 5.1.7; 5.1.8.1; 10.51.2(p); 14.54.16
al-ʿĀḍid bi-Allāh (Abū Muḥammad ʿAbd
Allāh ibn al-Mawlā Abī l-Ḥajjāj Yūsuf ibn al-Imām al-Ḥāfiẓ li-Dīn Allāh), last Fatimid caliph of Egypt (d. 567/1171) 14.31.6
al-ʿĀḍid li-Dīn Allāh `see` al-ʿĀḍid bi-Allāh al-ʿĀḍil `see` al-Malik al-ʿĀḍil
ʿAdnān, legendary ancestor of the northern
Arabian tribes 8.10.4n
ʿAdnān ibn Naṣr al-ʿAynzarbī `see` Ibn al-ʿAynzarbī
ʿAḍud al-Dawlah, Abū Shujāʿ Fannā Khusraw,
Būyid emir (d. 372/983) 8.5.2; 8.5.3; 10.4.9 nos. 8, 17; 10.8.3; 10.25; 10.29; 10.31; 10.32; 10.33; 10.42; 11.5.3;11.5.3; 11.5.4; 11.5.5; 11.5.6
ʿAḍud al-Dīn Abū al-Faraj ibn Raʾīs al-Ruʾasāʾ, vizier to al-Mustaḍīʾ bi-Amr Allāh 10.63.2
al-ʿAḍud ibn Munqidh, ʿAḍud al-Dīn [`or`
ʿAḍud al-Dawlah] Abū l-Fawāris Murhaf ibn Usāmah (d. 613/1216), son of Usāmah ibn Munqidh 14.51.3
Aephicianus, associate of Satyrus 5.1.25 Aeschines, Greek statesman and orator
(d. 314BC) 10.1.14 no. 205
Aetius of Amida, 6th-c. medical author 4.1.10.2n; 4.5.1n; 6.5.2
al-Afḍal `see` al-Malik al-Afḍal
Afḍal al-Dīn al-Khūnajī `see` al-Khūnajī ʿAfīf al-Dīn Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn ʿAdlān
al-Naḥwī al-Mawṣilī, grammarian
(d. 666/1267) 10.81.2
al-Afḍal ibn Amīr al-Juyūsh, Fatimid vizier 487–515/1094–1121 14.26.2; 14.31.2n; 14.31.4n
{396}{!}
ʿAfīf ibn Sukkarah, Jewish physician from Aleppo (active 584/1188) 15.16
A􏲪􏲤āṭūn `see` Plato
Afqūrshāh, pre-Islamic Persian ruler 10.4.4.2n
Afrāʾīm ibn al-Zaffān `see` Ifrāʾīm ibn al-Zaffān al-Afshīn, princely title of Ḥaydar ibn Kāwūs,
general of al-Maʾmūn and al-Muʿtaṣim 8.11
Agamemnon, Greek king and leader of the Greeks in the Trojan War 2.1.5
Agapius (Maḥbūb ibn Quṣṭanṭīn), 10th-c. bishop of Manbij and historian 5.1.8.2n
Agathias of Anazarbus, Greek philosopher 4.1.11.3; 5.1.32
Agathinus, 1st-c. physician 3.2; 3.6 Agathodaemon, Greco-Egyptian god, expert
on the occult in the Arabic tradition 2.1.3; 5.1.32
Agathon, metropolitan at al-Shawbak 5.1.32
al-Agharr `see` Dubays ibn Ṣadaqah Aghlabids 13.1 n 5
Aḥmad al-Ḥājib, possibly Abū l-ʿAbbās
Aḥmad ibn al-Furāt (d. 312/924) 10.3.6 Aḥmad ibn ʿAbd Allāh ibn Aḥmad ibn
Ibrāhīm al-Bakhtārī, great-grandson of
Ibn al-Bakhtārī 8.20.11n
Aḥmad ibn ʿAbd Allāh ibn Yūsuf, brother of
Ibn (al-)Shibl al-Baghdādī 10.51.3 Aḥmad ibn Abī l-Ashʿath `see` Ibn Abī l-
Ashʿath
Aḥmad ibn Abī Duʾād, 2nd/8th-c. Muʿtazilite 8.4.2; 8.4.5; 8.20.6n
Aḥmad ibn Abī Yaʿqūb, Abbasid client 14.14.3
Aḥmad ibn ʿAlī ibn Thābit `see` al-Khaṭīb al-Baghdādī
Aḥmad ibn Badr al-Wāsiṭī, transmitter (per-
haps = Ibn al-Wāsiṭī, q.v.) 10.62.2 Aḥmad ibn Ḥakīm ibn Ḥafṣūn, Andalusian
physician 13.30; 13.29.2
Aḥmad ibn al-Ḥārith al-Ḥazzāz, transmitter 7.5.2; 10.2.2.2
Aḥmad ibn al-Ḥusayn ibn Zayd ibn Fuḍālah
al-Baladī 10.46.4 no. 14
Aḥmad ibn Ibrāhīm ibn Ismāʿīl ibn Dāwūd
ibn Ḥamdūn `see` Ibn Ḥamdūn al-Nadīm Aḥmad ibn Ilyās al-Qāʾid, governor of Cor-
dova 13.27.1
Aḥmad ibn ʿĪsā, `ṣāḥib` a􏱌]kac􏲞􏱋ag in Cordova 13.24.2
Aḥmad ibn ʿĪsā ibn Shaykh 10.2.3.1 Aḥmad ibn Ismāʿīl ibn Aḥmad (nd􏲉. 295– 301/907–914), Samanid emir 11.5.25
nos. 75, 197
Aḥmad ibn Muḥammad ibn Yaḥyā al-Baladī,
Abū l-ʿAbbās 10.46.2; 10.46.4 no. 1; 10.48 Aḥmad ibn Muḥammad, known as Ibn
al-Mudabbir, ‘the Secretary’ `see` Ibn al-Mudabbir
Aḥmad ibn Muḥammad al-Khurāsānī,
addressee of a treatise by al-Kindī 10.1.14 no. 235
Aḥmad ibn al-Muʿtaṣim, Abū l-ʿAbbās, Abbasid prince and patron of al-Kindī 10.1.3; 10.1.4 nos. 35, 59, 246, 282 Aḥmad ibn Rashīd, `mawlā` of Sallām al-Abrash 12.6
Aḥmad ibn Saʿd, physician 11.16 nos. 1.1, 1.8 Aḥmad ibn al-Ṭayyib al-Sarakhsī `see` al-Sarakhsī, Aḥmad ibn al-Ṭayyib
Aḥmad ibn Ṭūlūn, Turkish governor of Egypt,
founder of the Ṭūlūnid dynasty (220/835– 270/884) 8.26.9; 14.2; 14.3; 14.4.1–4; 14.54.4n
Aḥmad ibn Waṣīf al-Ṣābiʾ 10.9.1
Aḥmad ibn Yūnus al-Ḥarrānī see al-Ḥarrānī,
Aḥmad ibn Yūnus
Ahrun ibn Aʿyan, 6th-c. author of a medical
compendium 6.5.1; 8.19.1; 8.19.2; 8.30.4
al-Ahzal Aḥmad ibn Isḥāq `see` al-Burjī ʿĀʾishah, wife of Muḥammad 7.5.5n; 15.46.2 al-Ajall al-Sadīd Abū l-Manṣūr ʿAbd Allāh
ibn al-Shaykh al-Sadīd Abī l-Ḥasan ʿAlī `see` al-Shaykh al-Sadīd Raʿīs al- Ṭibb
al-Ajall al-Murtaḍā,? = al-Sharīf al-Murtaḍā (d. 436/1044) 10.13.4; 10.38.4
Ajax, legendary ancient Greek hero 4.4.2.3 al-Akhṭal, Ghiyāth ibn Ghawth, Umayyad
poet (d. ca. 92/710) 11.9.2.5n al-Akhṭal, name of several minor poets 11.9.2.5n
Akhū l-Sayyidah, metropolitan (`al-muṭrān`)
in Cairo 380/991 [Arsenius, later Patriarch
of Alexandria; d. 400/1000] 14.15 Akhzam, son of a poet 14.55.2n; 15.58.1
{397}{!}
Alāʾ al-Dawlah, Abū Jaʿfar Muḥammad ibn Dushmanziyār (d. 433/1041–1042), Kāk- ūyid ruler of the Jibāl region 11.13.3.2
no. 12; 11.13.3.7–11,18,19; 11.13.8 nos. 13, 14, 53
ʿAlāʾ al-Dīn ʿAlī Khwārazm Shāh `see` ʿAlāʾ al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn Tekish Khwārazm
Shāh
ʿAlāʾ al-Dīn Kay-Qubādh, Seljuq sultan of
Rūm (nd􏲉. 616–634/1219–1237)–
ʿAlāʾ al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn Tekish Khwā-
razm Shāh, ruler of the Khwārazm-Shāh dynasty (nd􏲉. 596–617/1200–1229) 11.19.6.2 (incorrectly as ʿAlāʾ al-Dīn ʿAlī Khwārazm Shāh); `see` a􏱌ol s.v. Khwārazm Shāh
ʿAlāʾ al-Mulk al-Alawī, vizier under Sultan Khwārazm Shāh 11.19.5
ʿAlam al-Dīn Abū Naṣr, brother of Muhadhd- hab al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn Abī Ḥulayqah, physician 14.55.3
ʿAlam al-Dīn Qayṣar ibn Abī l-Qāsim ibn ʿAbd al-Ghanī ibn Musāfir al-Ḥanafī `see` Qayṣar ibn Abī l-Qāsim ibn Musāfir
al-ʿAlawī, patron of Ibn Sīnā 11.13.3.9 Albinus, Platonist and teacher of Galen 4.1.11.3; 5.1.21.1n
Alexander of Aphrodisias, 3rd-c. Aristotelian
philosopher 4.1.11.3; 5.1.26 (confused with Alexander of Damascus); 4.8; 14.25.2; 14.30; 15.1.5 no. 27; 15.40.3
Alexander of Damascus, Aristotelian philo- sopher 5.1.25
Alexander the Great, Macedonian king 1.4; 4.1.11.3; 4.6.11 nos. 46, 85, 88; 4.6.13.1 no. 120; 4.6.13.3 nos. 126, 128, 129, 141; 5.1.8.1 (era of Alexander); 10.4.4.2n
Alexander of Tralles, physician of late antiquity 4.1.11.2
Alexandrians, late-antique physicians responsible for systematizing and sum- marizing Galen 5.1.37 nos. 79; 5.2.1; 6.1.1; 6.3.1–6 (curriculum of the Sixteen Books of Galen); 10.57 no. 3; 10.64.20
no. 8
Alfonso ⅠⅠ, king of Portugal 13.71n
Alfonso 􏲫ⅠⅠⅠ, king of Castile 13.66.3; 13.71n
ʿAlī, known as al-Fayyūm, Christian patron
of translators including Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq, governor of the Egyptian district of Fayyūm 9.45
ʿAlī, son of caliph al-Nāṣir li-Dīn Allāh 10.76.2
ʿAlī ibn al-ʿAbbās al-Majūsī 10.25; 14.25.9 no. 64n
ʿAlī [ibn ʿAbd Allāh ibn Sīnā], brother of `the` Ibn Sīnā 11.13.2.1 n. 12; 11.13.3.15; 11.13.8
no. 16
ʿAlī ibn Abī Ṭālib, cousin and son-in-law
of the Prophet Muḥammad, last of the ‘Rightly Guided’ caliphs 7.1.1; 7.1.5; 7.2.3; 7.5.3n; 7.5.6; 10.1.7n; 11.13.7.9; 13.58.4.6(p); 14.22.3.1n; 14.14.3n; 15.46.2; 15.46.3.2; 15.51.7; AⅠⅠ.2.1
ʿAlī ibn Abī Ṭālib al-Qayrawānī, dream inter- preter􏲆 probably an error for Makkī ibn Abī Ṭālib al-Qayrawānī, q.v.
ʿAlī ibn ʿAyyāsh, transmitter 10.81.3
ʿAlī ibn Bulbul (`al-wazīr`) 10.13.5
ʿAlī ibn Ḥāmid, oculist, father of the physi-
cian Muhadhdhab al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Raḥīm
ibn ʿAlī 15.50.1
ʿAlī ibn al-Ḥusayn, Zayn al-ʿĀbidīn, fourth
Imam of the Twelver Shi’is 15.51.7
ʿAlī ibn Ibrāhīm ibn Baks, Abū l-Ḥasan, physi- cian at ʿAḍudī Hospital (d. 394/1003–1004) 9.38; 10.43; 11.5.6
ʿAlī ibn ʿĪsā ibn ʿAlī al-Kaḥḥāl (The Oculist) 10.50
ʿAlī ibn ʿĪsā ibn Dāʾūd ibn al-Jarrāh, Abū l- Ḥasan, twice vizier under al-Muqtadir billāh (d. 334/996) 8.29.8n; 9.36; 10.4.4.1; 10.4.4.2; 10.4.5; 10.4.9 no. 6; 10.16; 11.5.25
no. 117; 14.22.4.4
ʿAlī ibn ʿĪsā ibn Māhān, guard commander
under caliphs al-Mahdī and Hārūn al-Rashīd 8.3.17
ʿAlī ibn ʿĪsā al-Rabaʿī, Abū al-Ḥasan al-Naḥwī
(the Grammarian) (d. 420/1029) 10.38.4 ʿAlī ibn al-Jahm, poet active mainly in Bagh-
dad (d. 249/863) 13.58
ʿAlī ibn al-Mahdī, son of al-Mahdī, known as
Abū Quraysh 8.8.2
ʿAlī ibn Muḥammad ibn al-Tamīmī, son of
the physician al-Tamīmī 14.14.8 no. 1 ʿAlī ibn Mūsā, al-Riḍā, eighth imam of the
Twelver Shi’is 8.3.11n; 15.51.7
{398}{!}
ʿAlī ibn Rabban al-Ṭabarī `see` ʿAlī ibn Sahl Rabban al-Ṭabarī
ʿAlī ibn Riḍwān `see` Ibn Riḍwān
ʿAlī ibn Sahl Rabban al-Ṭabarī, 3rd/9th-c.
physician 11.3; 11.4; 11.5.1; 12.2 nos. 3n, 11n ʿAlī ibn Sulaymān, physician-astrologer under
the Fatimid 14.21
ʿAlī ibn Wahbān 11.5.25 no. 192
ʿAlī ibn Wāhsūdhān the Daylamite (d. after 304/917), governor of Rayy 11.5.14; 11.5.25 no. 192n
ʿAlī ibn Yaḥyā, known as Ibn al-Munajjim,
secretary, companion of al-Maʾmūn, pat-
ron of Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq 8.29.22 nos. 6, 7; 9.41; 10.3.14 no. 41` to`ease check punctuation
ʿAlī ibn Yūsuf ibn Tāshufīn, Almoravid ruler (reg. 500–537/1107–1142) 13.61.4 no. 9
Alīnūs al-Iskandarānī `see` (Pseudo-)Elias the
Neoplatonist
Almohads (`al-Muwaḥḥidūn`) 13.63.3
Almoravids (`al-Murābiṭūn`) 13.61.1; 13.62.1; 13.63.3
Āluh (Aluh) `see` Ibn Ḥāmid ibn Muḥammad,
Abū Naṣr al-ʿAzīz Aḥmad
Amalric (King Mārī; al-Malik Mārī), Amalric Ⅰ
of Jerusalem (nd􏲉. 558–569 /1162–1174) 14.49.2; 14.49.3
al-Aʿmash `see` Sulaymān ibn Mihrān al-Asadī Amasis, Egyptian pharaoh 4.3.4.2
Amat al-ʿAzīz, favourite slave of al-Hādī, to
whom she bore eight children 8.10.3
Ambracis, maidservant of Aristotle 4.6.6.2
Amenophis, mythical Greek king 2.2
al-ʿAmīd, vizier 8.5.4
al-ʿAmīdī, Rukn al-Dīn Abū Ḥāmid Muḥam- mad ibn Muḥammad al-Samarqandī, Ḥanafī jurist at Bukhārā (d. 615/1218) 10.83.2
al-Āmidī, Sayf al-Dīn Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Abī
ʿAlī ibn Muḥammad ibn Sālim al-Taghlibī al-Āmidī, theologian and philosopher
(d. 631/1233) 10.22.3; 14.23.1; 15.1.1.1; 15.22; 15.50.5
al-Amīn, Muḥammad, caliph (nd􏲉. 193– 198/809–13) 8.3.5; 8.3.7n; 8.3.14n; 8.3.17; 8.15.1n; 8.20.4n; 8.25.2n; 8.27.4n; 12.5n
Amīn al-Dawlah Abū l-Fatḥ ibn Abī l-Najm, Christian Physician 15.27
Amīn al-Dawlah Abū l-Ḥasan ibn Ghazāl ibn Abī Saʿīd, vizier and physician 15.20; 15.49
Amīn al-Dawlah ibn al-Tilmīdh `see` Ibn al- Tilmīdh, Amīn al-Dawlah
Amīn al-Dīn Jaʿfar, muezzin for Al-Malik al- Kāmil, patient of Abū Ḥulayqah 14.54.8 al-Āmir bi-Aḥkām Allāh (Abū ʿAlī al-Manṣūr
ibn Abī l-Qāsim Aḥmad al-Mustaʿlī bi- Allāh ibn al-Mustanṣir), tenth Fatimid caliph (d. 524/1130) 13.52.1; 13.58.2.2; 14.31.2; 14.31.4n; 14.31.6
ʿĀmir ibn Ṣaʿṣaʿah, poet 15.8.4
ʿĀmir ibn Sharāḥīl al-Shaʿbī, early `muḥaddith`
and legal expert 7.2.4
ʿĀmir ibn al-Ṭufayl, tribal hero and poet (d.
ca. 10/632) 15.8.4(p); 15.8.6(p) ʿAmīrah ibn Ḥayyān ibn Surāqah al-Asadī,
grandfather of Ṣāliḥ ibn Shaykh ibn
ʿAmīrah 8.26.13
al-ʿĀmirī, Abū l-Ḥasan Muḥammad ibn Yūsuf
(d. 381/992), philosopher 11.13.8 no. 91 ʿAmmār Dhū Kubār (nd􏲍pd Kināz), early 2nd/8th-c. poet 7.1.6n
ʿAmmār ibn ʿAlī al-Mawṣilī, oculist under al-Ḥākim 14.17
Ammonius, early 6th-c. Neoplatonist 3.3;4.1.11.3; 6.1.2
Amqat, Indian physician at court of Hārūn
al-Rashīd 12.5n
ʿAmr ibn al-ʿĀṣ, conqueror of Egypt (d. 43/ 664) 6.1.2; 14.14.7; 14.15n; 14.48.2n ʿAmr ibn Jurmūz, killer of al-Zubayr ibn al-ʿAwwām at the Battle of the Camel 7.5.4; 7.5.5
ʿAmr ibn Maʿrūf, transmitter 7.1.5
ʿAmr ibn Maymūn, unidentified, possible
confusion with ʿAmr ibn Nuhaywī AⅠⅠ.2.2
ʿAmr ibn Nuhaywī, off􏲊cial under al-Maʾmūn AⅠⅠ.2.2n
ʿAmr ibn Muḥammad al-Nāqid, transmitter 10.2.2.1
ʿAmr ibn Shaʾs (d. after 16/637), poet 15.8.5n
Amram `see` ʿImrān
Amyntas, ancient Macedonian king 4.6.2.1
Analogists, the Dogmatist school of ancient
{399}{!}
Greek physicians 1.1; 1.3.2; 1.12; 3.3; 4.1.10.4
Anas ibn Mālik, Companion of the Prophet,
traditionist 10.2.2.1
Anaxagoras, Pre-socratic philosopher 3.5; 4.1.10.1n; 5.1.26; 5.1.32 Anaximander, early Greek philosopher 4.3.4.1
Anaximenes, early Greek philosopher 4.1.11.3
Anbā Zakhariyyā ibn Thawābah, unidentified
monk in Jerusalem in the 900s 14.14.2 al-Anbārī al-Naḥwī, Kamāl al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Raḥmān ibn Muḥammad ibn ʿUbayd Allāh Abū l-Barakāt, grammarian (513/1119–577/1181) 15.40.2
ʿAnbasah ibn Isḥāq al-Ḍabbī, governor of Daybul (Sind) under al-Wāthiq 8.21.4
Ancaeus, maternal grandfather of Pythagoras 4.3.4.1
Anchialus, Empiricist physician of antiquity 3.5
Andī, otherwise unknown Indian physician and scholar 12.2
Andreas, personal physician of Ptolemy Philopator 4.1.10.2n
Androcles, governor of Samos and foster- father of Pythagoras 4.3.4.1
Andromachus the Elder, personal physician of Nero 1.8n; 3.6
Andromachus the Younger, 1st-c. physician 1.8; 4.1.10.2; 5.1.26
Andronicus, continuator of Eusebius 5.1.8.1–5.1.8.2 (dates of Roman emper- ors); 15.1.2
Andronicus, editor of the works of Aristotle 4.6.13.1n; 4.6.13.2
Anebo, Egyptian prophet and priest 11.5.25.no. 76
Ankar, otherwise unknown Indian physician and scholar 12.2
al-Ankūr, al-Malik `see` al-Malik al-Ankūr ʿAnnāz `see` Abū l-Shawk Fāris ibn Muḥam-
mad ibn ʿAnnāz
Annianus of Alexandria, late-antique chro-
nographer 5.1.8.2n
Anqīlāwus, physician of antiquity 4.1.10.2 ʿAntar(ah) ibn Shaddād al-ʿAbsī, pre-Islamic
poet, hero of popular epic 10.69.1
al-ʿAntarī `see` Ibn al-Ṣāʾigh
Antigonus, addressee of a letter attributed to
Diocles of Carystus 4.1.9.2n Antimachus, legendary physician of
antiquity 3.2
Antipater, student of Aristotle 4.6.2.2; 4.6.6.1
Antipater of Halasarna, 2nd-c. A􏲬 physician 4.1.11.2n
Antipater of Maṣṣīṣā (Mopsuestia), 2nd-c. A􏲬
physician 4.1.11.2
Antiphon, legendary physician of antiquity 3.3
Antisthenes, dedicatee of Galen 5.1.37
no. 10
Antoninus, 2nd-c. Roman emperor 5.1.8.2
(confusion between Antoninus Pius and Marcus Aurelius Antoninus,
cf. 5.1.25); 5.1.9 (his change of name); 5.1.11
Antyllus, 2nd-c. Greek physician 6.5.2 Anūshirwān `see` Kisrā Anūshirwān Apellicon of Teos, purchaser of the works of
Aristotle 4.6.13.2
Apollo, early expert on medicine and origin-
ator of Greek writing 2.1.2 (god at Rome); 2.2
Apollonius (? name uncertain), brother of Andromachus the Younger 1.8
Apollonius, pupil of Hippocrates 4.1.10.1 Apollonius (perh. of Alexandria, or of
Citium), physician of antiquity 4.1.10.3; 4.1.10.5; 4.1.11.2
Apollonius (of Perga, Greek astronomer and geometer, d. ca. 190BC) 10.3.14 no. 136
Apollonius of Tyana, Neopythagorean holy- man and philosopher of 1st-c. A􏲬, author- ity on occult in later traditions 5.1.8.2; 9.15n; 14.22.3.2n; 14.22.4.2 nos. 2, 12 Aqish (`or` Āqish), unidentified 15.51.10.3 ʿArafah, unidentified grammarian of Damas-
cus 10.69.4 no. 4
Arbad ibn Rabīʿah, brother of the pre-Islamic
poet Labīd 10.51,3
Archelaus, late-antique physician 6.1.1 Archigenes, Pneumatist physician under Tra-
jan 4.1.10.3; 4.1.11.2
Archigenes, friend of Socrates 4.4.4
no. 65
{400}{!}
Archimedes, Hellenistic Greek scientist 9.26n; 10.4.9 no. 20; 14.22.4.2 no. 25; 14.22.5.2 no. 43; 5.2 nos. 42, 43 Archipolis, disciple of Hippocrates 4.1.10.1n
Archytas, philosopher of Tarentum 4.3.6.1
Ardashīr (Artaxerxes), Persian king 4.1.5
Ardashīr ibn Bābak, founder of the Sasanid
dynasty (d. A􏲬242) 8.20.6
Aristippus the Elder, student of Socrates and
founder of the Cyrenaic school of philo-
sophy 4.3.6.2
Aristippus the Younger, grandson of Aristip-
pus the Elder 4.3.6.2
Aristomenes, friend of Aristotle 4.6.6.1
Ariston, father of Plato 4.5.2
Aristotle, Greek philosopher 4.1.11.3; 4.1.11.4; 4.6; 5.1.26; 5.1.32; 5.1.37 nos. 46, 62; 6.2 (list of works commented on by John the Grammarian); 8.29.6n; 8.29.22n; 10.1.4; 10.1.14 nos. 5, 6, 28; 10.2.4 nos. 51, 52; 10.3.14 nos. 5, 6, 8, 10, 90, 144; 10.21; 10.22.4 no. 2; 10.23.3 nos. 1, 2, 4; 10.37.2; 10.37.5 nos. 1–9; 10.46.1; 10.64.15; 11.2; 11.5.8n; 11.5.23.5; 11.5.25 nos. 5n, 7, 8, 9, 76; 11.8.6 nos. 7n, 15n; 13.39.1; 13.59.4 (Ibn Bājjah’s commentaries) nos. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5; 13.65; 13.66.6 (Ibn Rushd’s com- mentaries) nos. 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 27, 28, 31, 33, 39; 14.22.1; 14.22.4.1; 14.22.4.3 nos. 1, 2, 4, 11, 20, 22, 42; 14.22.5.1 nos. 1, 2, 16, 17; 14.22.5.2 no. 68n; 14.25.2; 14.25.5; 14.25.9 nos. 27, 76, 77n; 15.1.1.3; 15.1.2; 15.1.3.2; 15.1.3.3; 15.40.1; 15.40.8 no. 88. Treatises specified􏲆 9.13n; 9.37n; 14.21 no. 5 (doubts about `On` Vhohl􏱋); 14.22.4.1; 14.22.5.1 nos. 1, 16, 17 various
paraphrases); 14.30; 15.1.5 nos. 2, 3, 4, 5,6,7,8,24,25,26,27,28,31,41,43, 72, 74, 78, 81, 87, 97, 98, 102, 104, 108, 109; 15.40.9 nos. 40, 41; 15.51.1 Cited in poetry􏲆 8.30; 11.19; 13.58; 15.17; AⅠⅠ.1(p)
Aristoxenus, pupil of Aristotle 4.3.4.3n; 4.6.3.4
Arius, nicknamed ‘the Critic’, physician of antiquity 4.1.11.2
Armīnus, 5.1.21.1 (confusion of Herminus and Albinus)
al-ʿArqalah Abū l-Nadā Ḥassān ibn Numayr al-Kalbī, poet (6th/12th c.) 15.8.2
Arsenius `see` Akhū l-Sayyidah Artaxerxes `see` Ardashīr
Artemon, 2nd-c. grammarian from Cas-
sandreia 4.6.13.2n
al-ʿArūḍī `see` Abū l-Ḥusayn al-ʿArūḍī al-ʿArzamī, Abū Bakr Muḥammad ibn ʿUbayd
Allāh, early Abbasid poet 8.29.15n Asad al-Dīn, known as Shīrkūh, one of the
last viziers of Fatimid Egypt (d. 564/1169) 14.36.2
Asʿad al-Dīn ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz ibn Abī l-Ḥasan `see` Asʿad al-Dīn ibn Abī l-Ḥasan
Asʿad al-Dīn ibn Abī l-Ḥasan (Asʿad al- Dīn ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz ibn Abī l-Ḥasan) (570–635/1174–1237), one of a family of Egyptian physicians, acquainted with ⅠAU 4.31.3; 14.54.6, 10; 14.54.6,10; 14.57
al-Asʿad al-Maḥallī, Asʿad al-Dīn Yaʿqūb ibn Isḥāq, 13th-c. Jewish physician 14.42; 15.47.3 no. 6
Aṣbagh ibn Yaḥyā al-Ṭabīb, Andalusian physi-
cian 13.26
Asclepiades, late 2nd/early 1st-c. BC physician
at Rome 4.1.11.2; 5.1.37 no. 108 Asclepiades the Second, physician of
antiquity 4.1.11.2
Asclepiads, ancient Greek physicians
claiming descent from or adherence to
Asclepius 1.1
Asclepius, Greek god of healing 1.6; 2.1; 2.1.2
(temple at Rome and divinity); 5.1.9
(temple at Rome); 11.5.2 Asclepius the Second, legendary ancient
Greek physician 3.2; 3.5; 3.6 al-Asfizārī `see` Najm al-Dīn Yūsuf ibn Sharaf
al-Dīn
al-Aʿshā `see` Maymūn ibn Qays ibn Thaʿlabah al-Aʿshā, name of several poets 11.9.2.5n al-Ashʿath ibn Qays ibn Maʿdī Karib, chieftain
of clan Kindah (d. 40/661) 10.1.2 al-Ashtar `see` Mālik ibn al-Hārith al-Nakhaʿi ʿĀṣim ibn Thābit ibn Abi l-A􏲪􏲤aḥ al-Anṣārī,
one of the Anṣār 7.2.3
ʿĀṣim ibn ʿUmar ibn Qatādah, transmitter 7.2.3
al-ʿAskarī, Abū Aḥmad, philologist, lexico-
grapher (d. 382/993) 10.1.13 al-ʿAskarī, Abū Hilāl, philologist (d. after
{401}{!} 395/1005) 7.1.6n; 7.5.5n; 8.3.19n; 8.29.22n; 15.40.9 no. 30
al-Aṣmaʿī, philologist (d. 213/828) 14.55.2n
al-Asṭurlābī `see` al-Badīʿ al-Asṭurlābī
ʿĀtikah bint Zayd ibn ʿAmr ibn Nufayl, wife of
al-Zubayr ibn al-ʿAwwām, poet 7.5.5 Atsiz ibn Muḥammad ibn Anūshtigīn, foun-
ded dynasty of the Khwārazm-Shāhs (nd􏲉. 521–551/1127–1172), great-grandfather of ʿAlāʾ al-Dīn Muḥammad 11.19.6.2
Atsiz ibn Uvak, Turkoman chief 14.50n Augustus (formerly Octavian), Roman
emperor 5.1.8.1; 5.1.21.2; 15.1.2 Aulinus, physician of late antiquity 4.1.11.2
Autolycus, author of Mlrh􏱋􏲉 S􏲤gdnd 14.22.3.2n; 15.31.6n Avicenna `see` Ibn Sīnā
ʿAwānah ibn al-Ḥakam, 2nd/8th-c. historian 7.5.6
ʿAwf, of the tribe of Jaʿfar ibn Kilāb 15.8.4(p) Awḥad al-Zamān `see` Abū l-Barakāt al-Baghdādī
ʿAwn Allāh ibn Mūsā ibn al-ʿĀzār al-Israʾīlī,
physician in the service of al-Muʿizz li-
Dīn Allāh (d. 363/973) 14.9
ʿAwn al-ʿIbādī al-Jawharī, governor of al- Ḥīrah under Hārūn al-Rashīd 8.3.7; 8.3.16
Aws ibn Rabīʿah ibn Muʿattib, one of the
ancestors of the Banū Kunnah subtribe 7.1.6n
Aʿyan ibn Aʿyan, Egyptian physician (d. 385/995) 14.13
Aybak `see` al-Malik al-Muʿizz ʿIzz al-Dīn Aybak
al-ʿAynzarbī `see` Ibn al-ʿAynzarbī
Ayyūb, known as al-Abrash `see` Ayyūb al-Ruhāwī al-Abrash
Ayyūb ibn al-Ḥakam al-Baṣrī, known as al-Kasrawī, unidentified source 8.19.3; 8.19.4; 8.19.5
Ayyūb al-Ruhāwī (Job of Edessa) al-Abrash, Syriac polymath, Christian physician and translator of Galen (d. ca. 835) 5.1.37
no. 115; 8.22; 9.7; 9.25; 10.22 al-Azdī, Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad Abū l-
Muṭahhar, 4th–5th/10th–11th-c. author 4.26.8n; 7.9.2n
al-ʿAzīz or al-ʿAzīz bi-Allāh, fifth Fatimid
caliph (nd􏲉. 364–385/975–96) 4.10; 8.5.3; 10.48; 14.10; 14.13; 14.14.3; 14.15; 14.16; 14.21; 14.40.1n; 14.47.2n; 14.54.3n; AⅠⅠ.11
al-ʿAzīz ibn al-Nāṣir Ṣalāḥ al-Dīn (nd􏲉. 589– 595/1193–1198), son of Ṣalāḥ al-Dīn 14.37; 14.44.2; 15.40.4; 15.51.1; 15.51.9 no. 123n;
AⅠⅠ.11
al-Azraq, secretary of Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq 8.29.6
ʿAzūr ibn al-Ṭayyib al-Baladī al-Yahūdī 10.46.4 no. 14
Bābak, head of the Persian Khurramī reli- gious and social movement, rebel against caliphs al-Maʾmūn and al-Muʿtaṣim
(d. 223/838) 8.11; 8.20.11n
al-Badīʿ ʿAbd al-Razzāq ibn Aḥmad ibn al- Khiḍr al-ʿĀmirī, Abū l-Qāsim, poet of unknown date 15.23.4.2
Badīʿ al-Dīn Abū l-Fatḥ Manṣūr ibn Abī l- Qāsim ibn ʿAbd Allāh ibn ʿAbd al-Dāʾim al-Wāsiṭī, known as Ibn Sawād al-ʿAyn, transmitter 10.68.2.1; 10.68.2.2; 10.68.2.3
al-Badīʿ (`or` Badīʿ al-Zamān) al-Asṭurlābī, Abū l-Qāsim Hibat Allāh ibn al-Ḥusayn ibn Aḥmad, physician and poet (d. 534/1139) 10.64.2n, 10.67; 10.68.2.4; 10.68.4
Badīʿ al-Zamān al-Hamadhānī (d. 398/1008),
originator of the genre of `maqāmah` 10.67
al-Badīhī, Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Muḥammad, 4th/10th-c. poet 11.7
Badr al-Dīn Abū l-ʿIzz Yūsuf ibn Makkī, known as Ibn al-Sinjārī 10.66.8; 10.81.3
Badr al-Dīn ibn Qāḍī Baʿlabakk, physician, transmitter 15.37.1, 15.50.6; 15.52
Badr al-Dīn Luʾluʾ (Badr al-Dīn Abū l-Faḍāʾil al-Malik al-Raḥīm), freedman who became regent of Mosul in 607/1210–1211 (d. 657/1259) 10.81.2; 10.83.3
Badr al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn Bahrām al- Samarqandī `see` al-Samarqandī, Badr al-Dīn
Badr al-Muʿtaḍidī, commander-in-chief of al-Muʿtaḍid 10.2.3.1; 10.3.6; 10.4.5
al-Bahāʾ, musician 15.51.1
Bahāʾ al-Dawlah `see` Manṣūr ibn Dubays Bahāʾ al-Dīn 11.19.7 no. 22
Bahāʾ al-Dīn Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn al-Sāʿātī,
{402}
poet, brother of physician Fakhr al-Dīn
Riḍwān 15.29
Bahāʾ al-Dīn Abū l-Thanāʾ Maḥmūd ibn Abī
l-Faḍl Manṣūr ibn al-Ḥasan ibn Ismāʿīl al-Ṭabarī al-Makhzūmī, judge and physi- cian – 15.39 (601/1204–1205) 1.9
Bahāʾ al-Dīn Ibn Shaddād (d. 632/1234– 1235), military judge and biographer of Ṣalāḥ al-Dīn 15.40.3
Bahāʾ al-Dīn ibn Nafādah? = `adīb` and poet Aḥmad ibn ʿAbd al-Raḥmān Ibn Nafādah
Bahlawān, House of, Ildegizid `or` Eldig􏱮zid dynasty in Azerbaijan 11.21
Bahmanyār (Abū l-Ḥasan Bahmanyār ibn al-Marzubān), pupil of Ibn Sīnā (d. 456/1067) 11.13.8 no. 41; 15.40.3
Bahrām Gūr (Bahrām 􏲫) (nd􏲉. 420–438), fif- teenth Sasanid king of Persia 11.1 al-Bājī `see` ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz ibn Maslamah
Bajkam, Abū l-Ḥasan (nd􏲍pd Abū l-Ḥusayn), military commander (d. 319/941) 10.4.8; 10.4.9 no. 4; 10.5.4
Bākahr, an otherwise unrecorded Indian
physician and scholar 12.2
Bakhtiyār `see` ʿIzz al-Dawlah Bakhtiyār al-Bakrī, Abū ʿUbayd ʿAbd Allāh ibn ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz `see` Abū ʿUbayd al-Bakrī al-Balādhurī, Aḥmad ibn Yaḥyā, historian 7.5.6n; 7.6n
Baldwin, Prince, son of Amalric, Baldwin Ⅰ􏲫
of Jerusalem, leprous (nd􏲉. 1174–1183) 14.49.3
Baldwin 􏲫 of Jerusalem, son of Baldwin Ⅰ􏲫 14.49.3n
al-Bālisī, physician during Ikshidid dynasty (active 355/966) 14.8
Balīṭīyān `see` Politianus
al-Balkhī, Abū Zayd Aḥmad b. Sahl `see` Abū
Zayd al-Balkhī
Balmuẓaffar ibn Muʿarrif `see` Bulmuẓaffar ibn
Muʿarrif
al-Bandahī, unidentified singer 15.23.4.2(p) Bānū, a sister of the caliph Hārūn al-Rashīd 8.25.6
Banū ʿAbd al-Dār, a subclan of Quraysh, to
which al-Naḍr ibn al-Ḥārith ibn Kaladah
al-Thaqafī belonged 7.2.1n; 7.2.3 Banū Awd, tribe of Zaynab 7.10
Banū Fazārūn. A secretarial family under the early Abbasids 8.21
Banū l-Ḥārith 14.30n
Banū l-Ḥārith al-Aṣghar ibn Muʿāwiyah 10.1.3
Banū Hāshim, Hāshimites (descendants of
Hāshim ibn ʿAbd Manāf; the Abbasids) 10.1.4; 10.4.5
Banū Ḥayyūn, mentioned as students of Abū l-Faraj ibn al-Ṭayyib 10.37.4
Banū Hūd, rulers in Saragossa, Murcia and Seville 13.57; 13.63.8.2n
Banū l-ʿIbād, the Christian Arab community of al-Ḥīrah 8.29.1
Banū Jaʿfar ibn Kilāb 15.8.4n
Banū Khālid, family of Umayyad clients in
Cordova 13.12
Banū Khāqān 10.8.7
Banū Kunnah, a clan of the tribe Thaqīf 7.1.6
Banū Makhzūm, an important clan of
Quraysh 7.5.3
Banū l-Munajjim, Zoroastrian family,
courtiers al-Manṣūr (nd􏲉. 136–158/754– 75), sponsors of translation movement 9.41n
Banū l-Mundhir, pre-Islamic Lakhmid dyn-
asty of al-Ḥīrah 8.3.16
Banū Munqidh, clan of Syria who` to`ayed a
significant political role during the Ayyu-
bid period 14.33.3n
Banū Mūsā ibn Shākir, three brothers
(Muḥammad, Aḥmad, al-Ḥasan) prom- inent in the intellectual life of Baghdad 3rd/9th-c. 9.15n; 9.27n; 9.40; 10.1.7; 10.3.14 no. 83; 14.22.5.2 no. 73; 15.46.1 Banū Shākir, relatives of Abū Shākīr ibn
Abī Sulayman and Rashīd al-Dīn Abū
Ḥulayqah 8.29.5; 14.51.1n; 14.54.4; 14.54.13 Banū l-Ṣūfī 15.8.1; 15.8.4; 15.8.5(p)
Banū Umayyah, a clan of the tribe Quraysh,
the first Muslim dynasty after the time of
the four ‘rightly guided’ caliphs 7.2.1 Banū Yanāqī, Sevillian family 13.63.4 Bāqil, figure proverbial for his inarticulate-
ness 15.31.2n
Baqiyyah ibn al-Walīd, transmitter 10.2.2.1 Baqqah (‘Bug’), Abū Mūsā the Physician
known as 10.8.5
{403}{!}
Bar Bahlūl, author of Syriac lexicon and translator 6.5.1; 8.29.22n
Bar Hebraeus (Abū l-Faraj ibn al-ʿIbrī), Syr- iac Orthodox historian, philosopher and translator (d. 685/1286) 4.5.4n; 8.11n; 8.24n; 8.26.6n; 8.29.1n; 8.29.12n; 8.29.17n; 9.16n; AⅠⅠ.5
Barak the Judge, ancient Hebrew hero 2.2
Barmakids, Iranian family of secretaries and
viziers under early Abbasid caliphs 8.2n; 8.3.2n; 8.3.9n; 8.3.22; 8.8.2n; 8.20.4n; 8.25.7n; 8.29.2n; 8.29.22n; 12.2n; 12.3; 12.5; 12.6n
al-Barqī `see` Abū Bakr al-Barqī
Barzawayh (Barzūyah, Barz􏲭􏱭), Physician to
Chosro􏲮s Ⅰ Anūsharwān 11.2
Bashīr ibn al-Samaydaʿ, brother of Bishr ibn
al-Samaydaʿ al-Azdī 8.20.10 al-Basbāsī `see` al-Shabānisī
Basīl al-Muṭrān, translator 9.18 al-Battānī, Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad ibn
Jābir ibn Sinān (d. 317/929), astrologer
and mathematician 13.5.1; 13.5.1 no. 2 al-Battī, Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Aḥmad, trans-
mitter 15.46.2
Baybars `see` al-Malik al-Ẓāhir Rukn al-Dīn
Baybars
Bayḍ al-Baghl (Mule’s Balls) `see` Isḥāq ibn
Ibrāhīm ibn Muḥammad ibn Ismāʿīl al-Bayhaqī, Ẓahīr al-Dīn Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī
ibn Zayd ibn Funduq, Persian author of `Tatimmat Ṣiwān al-Ḥikmah` (d. 565/1169– 1170) 5.1.5; 8.3.9n; 8.4.7n
al-Bayyāsī (`or` al-Bayāsī), Amīn al-Dīn Abū Zakariyyā Yaḥyā ibn Ismāʿīl al-Andalusī, Egyptian physician in Damascus, teacher of Asʿad al-Dīn ibn Abī l-Ḥasan 14.57.1; 15.8.4; 15.14; 15.17
Bhela, author of a Sanskrit medical compen-
dium (Sa􏲯hitā) 12.6n
Binyāmīn, teacher of Abū Bishr Mattā ibn
Yūnān 10.21
al-Bīrūnī, Abū l-Rayḥān, polymath (d.
ca. 442/1050) 4.1.2n; 4.3.4.3n; 4.5.1n; 8.4.11; 11.13.8 nos. 42, 42; 11.15
Bishr ibn ʿAbd Allāh al-Kātib, unidentified 10.69.3.7
Bishr ibn Bīshī, known as Ibn ʿAnāyā al-Isrāʾīlī 10.23.3
Bishr ibn Ḥaḍram al-Kalāʿī (?Bishr ibn Ḥiẓrim al-Kalbī) 15.25
Bishr ibn al-Samaydaʿ al-Azdī, governor of Balad under al-Muʿtaṣim 8.20.10
al-Biṭrīq, Christian translator under al- Manṣūr 8.29.8; 9.31
Boethus, Flavius – 2nd-c. Roman senator 5.1.10.1; 5.1.25; 5.1.37 nos. 27, 28, 37
Bonus, disciple of Hippocrates 4.1.10.1n Bradua, Ti. Claudius Bradua Regillus Atticus,
Roman consul 5.1.12.2
al-Buḥturī, poet (d. 284/897) 10.68.1.4n;
AⅠⅠ.3.1
al-Buḥturī `see` a􏱌ol al-Walīd
al-Bukhārī, Muḥammad, compiler of one of
the canonical collections of Hadith (a􏱌]
Ṣa􏲛􏲞􏲛) 8.13.4n; 8.26.8n
Bukhtīshūʿ ibn Jibrīl, member of family of
Christian physicians (d. 257/870) 8.3.6; 8.3.22; 8.4; 8.5.2n; 8.8.6n; 8.12.2n; 8.26.8; 8.29.10n; 8.29.13; 8.29.16; 9.30n; 9.49
Bukhtīshūʿ ibn Jūrjis, physician to Hārūn al- Rashīd 5.1.16.5; 8.2; 8.3.2n
Bukhtīshūʿ ibn Yūḥannā, physician to al- Muqtadir bi-Allāh and al-Rāḍī bi-Allāh 8.33
Bulmuẓaffar ibn Muʿarrif (Bulmuẓaffar Naṣr ibn Maḥmūd ibn al-Muʿarrif), Egyptian physician and poet (active 534/1140) 11.5.15; 11.5.21; 14.30
Būlus ibn Ḥanūn, physician in entourage of
Abū Dulaf 8.20.10; 8.20.11
Bunān al-Raṣāṣī, chief servant of al-Muʿtaḍid 10.5.3; 10.10.5
al-Bundahī, Badīʿ al-Dīn, poet known to ⅠAU 11.19.6.2
Buqrāṭ `see` Hippocrates
Burhān al-Dīn, vizier of Ayyubid emir ʿIzz al-Dīn al-Muʿaẓẓamī 15.49.6.2
Burhān al-Dīn Abū l-Faḍl Sulaymān `see` al- Sharīf al-Kaḥḥāl
al-Burhān al-Munajjim, father of ibn al-Khiḍr al-Ḥalabī 10.67.3
al-Burjī, al-Ahzal Aḥmad ibn Isḥāq, named by Ibn Mandawayh al-Iṣfahānī 11.16
no. 1.39
Buskhunnar, Khorasanian chieftain and rebel
(active 141/758–759) 8.10.3
{404}{!}
Byzantines (`Rūm, Banū l-Aṣfar`) 11.13.7.9(p); 13.21.1; 13.58.4.3; 13.58.4.6(p)

Caesar `see` Julius Gaius Caesar Callisthenes, ancient Greek historian 4.6.2.1
Cambyses, Persian Emperor, son of Cyrus 4.3.4.3
Cā􏲹akya `see` Shānāq
Caraka (also Sharak, Sīrk, or Jarak)– Indian
physician, author of `Carakasaṃhitā` 12.2
no.1
Cassius the Egyptian, 5th-c. A􏲬 physician 4.1.11.2
Chaldaeans (al-Kaldāniyyūn), part of the Nabataeans (Nabaṭ) of pre-Islamic Iraq 1.1; 1.2; 1.5; 4.3.4.1; 8.29.6 Chosroes `see` Kisrā
Christ `see` al-Masīḥ Christians/Christianity 4.6.3.3; 4.6.7.1; 4.8.1; 5.1.8.2; 5.1.12.3 (continence); 5.1.13
(‘double bliss’); 5.1.14 (intransigence); 5.1.21.2; 6.1.2–3 (Trinitarian disputes); 6.5.1; 7.2.1; 7.4; 7.5.1; 7.5.2; 7.6; 8.1.2; 8.3.17; 8.6; 8.7; 8.15.2; 8.20.1; 8.20.5; 8.25.2; 8.26.3; 8.26.8; 8.29.1; 8.29.3; 8.29.6; 8.29.9; 8.29.12; 8.29.15; 8.29.16; 8.29.17; 9.42; 10.8.10; 10.10.3; 10.21; 10.22; 10.23.1; 10.37.1; 10.37.3; 10.38.1; 10.44.1; 10.54.1; 10.58.3; 10.59.1; 10.63.1; 10.63.2; 10.64.13; 10.64.16; 10.77.1; 10.78; 11.1; 11.8.2; 11.8.6 no. 2; 11.12; 11.13.7.7; 11.13.7.9; 13.13; 13.14; 13.15; 13.20; 13.21.1; 13.21.2.2; 13.36.2.1; 13.36.2.2; 13.36.2.3; 13.65; 14.1; 14.4.1; 14.6; 14.7; 14.11; 14.12; 14.15; 14.16; 14.49.1; 14.49.3; 14.54.9; 14.56.1; 15.1.2; 15.1.3.1; 15.3.1; 15.15; 15.23.1; 15.23.1.2; 15.23.2; 15.23.2.2; 15.26;15.27; 15.28; 15.40. 9 nos. 93, 94; 15.43.1; 15.43.3; 15.60.1; `see` a􏱌ol al-Masīḥ
Christodulos of Caesarea, Christodulos ⅠⅠ ibn Sahl (?) 14.10n
Chrysermus, physician of antiquity 4.1.11.2 Chrysippus, 3rd-c. BC Stoic philosopher 4.1.11.3
Claudius, 1st-c. Roman emperor 5.1.8.1 Cleinias of Tarentum, Pythagorean philo-
sopher 4.3.6.2n
Cleomyttades, ancestor of Hippocrates 4.1.1
Cleopatra, Ptolemaic queen of Egypt
(d. 30BC), supposed author on cosmet- ics and medical/alchemical matters 4.1.11.2; 5.1.21.1 (teacher of Galen); 15.1.2
(‘the woman’)
Commodus, 2nd-c. Roman emperor 5.1.9; 5.1.12.2
Conius Megillus, fabricator of works
allegedly by Pythagoras 4.3.6.2 Constantius, Emperor 14.25.2n Coronis, mother of Asclepius by the god
Apollo 2.1.6.1n
Creophylus, ancestor of Hermodamus 4.3.4.2
Crisamis, Greek king of antiquity, ancestor of
Hippocrates 4.1.1
Crito, court physician of the emperor Trajan 4.1.10.5
Crito, friend of Socrates 4.4.2.3
Cronus, father of the younger generation of
gods in Greek mythology 4.5.2n Cylon, enemy of Pythagoras 4.3.4.3 Cyrus, founder of the Persian Empire 4.3.4.3
Ḍaḥḥāk (Arabic form of the Persian Dahhāk, Zahhāk, `or` Zuhāk), tyrannical king from Persian mythology 11.19.6.2
Dahīn al-Lawz, daughter of Damascene singer 15.56.1
Dāhir, otherwise unknown Indian physician and scholar 12.2
Dahishtak, superintendent of the Gond􏱭- shāpūr hospital in the reign of the caliph Hārūn al-Rashīd 8.25.8
al-Dakhwār `see` Muhadhdhab al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Raḥīm ibn ʿAlī
Damascius, 5th–6th-c. A􏲬 Neoplatonist philosopher 4.1.11.3n
Damon the Logician, 5th–4th-c. BC Sophist 4.1.11.3
al-Dānī `see` Abū Isḥāq Ibrāhīm al-Dānī
Dānīl and Saʿdūn, brothers-in-law of Saʿīd ibn
Ghālib, physician to al-Muʿtaḍid 10.10.5
Dāniyāl the Physician, physician in service of Muʿīzz al-Dawlah 10.27
Dāniyal, brother-in-law of the physician Yūḥannā ibn Māsawayh 8.26.8
{405}{!}
Daqyūs (Decius), pupil of Abū l-Ḥakam al- Maghribī 15.8.15
Dārā (Darius), Arabic name of several Achae- menid rulers 1.4; 4.1.5; 4.5.1; 11.19
Dārā ibn Sām, Darius ⅠⅠⅠ, last Achaemenid king of Persia (nd􏲉. 336–330BC) 5.1.8.1, 11.19.6.2
al-Dārimī `see` Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAbd al-Raḥmān
ibn Khalaf
Darius `see` Dārā
al-Darkazīnī, ʿImād al-Dīn Abū l-Barakāt ibn
Salamah, vizier under the Seljuq ruler Maḥmūd ibn Muḥammad ibn Malikshāh (d. 521/1127) 10.64.19.2
Dāʾūd `see` Dāwūd
David, King, father of Solomon 1.4
al-Dawlaʿī `see` al-Khaṭīb al-Dawlaʿī
Dāwūd ibn Daylam, physician 10.12.2; 10.15 Dāwūd ibn Ḥunayn, physician son of Ḥunayn
ibn Isḥāq 8.29.8
Dāwūd ibn Rushayd, `muḥaddith` 7.1.5 Dāwūd ibn Sarābiyūn (`or` Sarāfīyūn), acc. to
ⅠAU brother of the physician Yūḥannā ibn Sarābiyūn, but probably courtier of al-Hādī (late 2nd/8th-c.) 8.2; 8.3.10n; 8.29.3n; 9.49n
Dāwūd al-Mutaṭabbib `see` Dāwūd ibn Sar-
ābiyūn
Dāwūd Shāh `see` al-Malik ʿAlāʾ al-Dīn Dāwūd
ibn Bahrām
Dāwūd al-Ṭāʾī, traditionist 15.51.7
Daylam, physician 10.14
Daylamites, Iranian people originally from
the Gīlān region 8.5.2; 8.5.3; 8.5.4; 8.5.5; 10.4.9 no. 8
Demeter, in Greek mythology, the goddess of harvests 2.1.6.3; 4.3.2
Demetrius, devout man of Croton 4.3.4.3 Democrates the Second, physician of
antiquity 4.1.10.5
Democritus of Abdera, late-5th-c. founder of
Atomist philosophy 4.1.2; 4.1.11.3; 4.7n Demophilus, Athenian hierophant 4.6.2.1n Dexippus, disciple of Hippocrates 4.1.10.1n al-Dhahabī `see` Abū Jaʿfar al-Dhahabī
Dhū l-Ki􏲪􏲤, mentioned in the Qurʾan 15.17(p)
Dhū l-Rummah, poet (d. 117/735–736) AⅠⅠ.10
Dhū Yazan, pre-islamic Yemenite maker of spears 15.8.5n
Diocles, Dogmatic physician of late antiquity 3.4; 4.1.9.2n
Diocles, 3rd–2nd-c. BC mathematician and geometer 4.1.11.3
Diogenes, Greek Cynic philosopher 4.1.11.3; 5.1.32
Diogenes, nutritionist of antiquity 4.1.11.2 Diogenes La􏲮rtius, 3rd-c. A􏲬 biographer of Greek philosophers 4.6.2.1n; 4.6.6.1n; 4.6.6.2n; 4.6.13.1n
Dionysius, tyrant of Sicily 4.5.2
Dionysus – Greek god of the grape harvest,
winemaking and wine 2.1.6.2 Diophantus 14.22.5.2 no. 91
Dioscorides, Greek pharmacologist (d. ca. 90) 1.7n; 1.11; 2.1.6.2; 3.2; 3.3; 4.1.11.1 (sum- mary of book); 9.19n; 5.1.32; 5.1.37 no. 44n; 13.36.1; 13.36.2.1; 13.36.2.3; 13.36.2.4; 13.36.3 nos. 1, 2; 13.86.3 no. 1; 14.25.2; 14.58.1; 14.58.2; 14.58.4 no. 2; 15.10; 15.40.9 nos. 113, 114
Dioscorides the Oculist, late-antique physi- cian 5.2.1
Dioscorides the Younger, 2nd-c. A􏲬 gram- marian 4.1.10.4
Dioscorus, mid-5th-c. Patriarch of Alexandria 6.1.3
Dioteles, friend of Aristotle 4.6.6.1
Ḍiyāʾ al-Dīn ibn al-Athīr (558–559/1163–636– 637/1239), literary critic 15.31.6n
Ḍiyāʾ al-Dīn ibn al-Bayṭār `see` Ibn al-Bayṭār Ḍiyāʾ al-Dīn ibn Ṣaqar (`or` Ṣaqr) – unidenti-
fied transmitter 15.18
Ḍiyāʾ al-Dīn ʿUmar al-Rāzī, father of Fakhr
al-Dīn al-Rāzī, authority on Islamic law 11.19.4
Dogmatists `see` Analogists
Domitian, 1st-c. Roman emperor 5.1.8.2 Dracon, son of Hippocrates 4.1.2; 4.1.10.1 Dubays ibn Ṣadaqah, Mazyadid ruler (nd􏲉. 501–529/1108–1135) 10.65 al-Dunaysirī `see` ʿImād al-Dīn al-Dunaysirī Durrī, a slave `or` servant 15.47.2.1(p)
Egyptians, Ancient 1.1; 1.5; 2.1.3; 2.1.4; 4.3.1; 4.3.4.1; 4.3.4.2; 4.5.2
Elias, Jewish prophet 15.51.7
{406}{!}
Elias, Christian priest `see` Iliyyāʾ
Elias of Nisibis, 11th c., brother of Zāhid
al-ʿUlamāʾ, metropolitan of Nisibis, chro- nographer 5.1.7; 9.16n
Elijah of Nisibis 9.16n
Elishaʿ `see` al-Yasaʿ
Empedocles of Agrigentum, Presocratic
philosopher 4.1.11.3; 4.1.11.4; 4.2; 4.3.1 Empiricists, school of ancient Greek physi-
cians 1.1; 1.8; 3.1–3; 4.1; 10.4
Ephorus, Greek historian 4.6.4.1 Epicurus, Athenian philosopher 4.6.3.1
Epicurus, physician of antiquity 3.3; 3.4
Epigenes, addressee of Galen’s `On` `Prognosis` 5.1.28
Erasistratus, 3rd-c. BC anatomist 3.2; 4. 5.1.10.1; 5.1.37 no. 20 (with note); 5.1.37
no. 28
Eubulus of Bithynia, 4th-c. BC ruler of lands
in Asia Minor 4.6.2.1n
Euclid, Greek geometrician 4.1.11.3;4.5.1n; 9.12; 10.1.14 nos. 85, 95; 10.3.14 nos. 59, 60, 87; 10.67.4.1(p); 11.5.25 no. 18; 11.13.2.5; 11.13.3.2 no. 29; 11.13.3.10; 11.13.8 no. 65; 11.19.7 no. 41; 13.6.1.1; 14.22.2; 14.22.3.2; 14.22.4.2 nos. 1, 2, 4, 5, 24; 14.22.5.1 no. 18; 14.22.5.2 nos. 2, 39, 40, 55, 56; 14.22.5.2 no. 85n; 15.1.5 no. 52; 15.7(p); 15.31.6 nos. 7, 8; 15.33; 15.60.1
Eudemus, 2nd-c. Peripatetic philosopher 5.1.25
Eudemus of Rhodes, pupil of Aristotle 4.1.11.3; 4.6.3.4; 4.6.13.1 no. 36; 14.25.5
no. 7
Eudemus, 1st-c. A􏲬 ophthalmologist 4.1.11.2; 4.1.11.3
Eugenianus, dedicatee of Galen 5.1.37
no. 20
Eumenes, pupil of Aristotle 4.6.3.4 Eunostus, brother of Pythagoras 4.3.4.1 Euphanes, Greek philosopher 4.1.11.3 Eurymedon, Athenian hierophant 4.6.2.1 Eusebius of Caesarea, 4th-c. bishop, chrono-
grapher and apologist 5.1.8.1; 4.6.2.1n Eusebius of Dorylaeum, 5th-c. bishop 6.1.3 Eustathius, pupil of Hippocrates 4.1.10.1; 4.1.10.1n
Eustathius, circle of al-Kindī, `see` Usṭāth Eutyches, 5th-c. Constantinopolitan archi-
mandrite misidentified with John Philo-
ponus/John the Grammarian 6.1.3 Eutychius `see` Saʿīd ibn al-Biṭrīq
al-Faḍl ibn Jarīr al-Takrītī 10.39
al-Faḍl ibn al-Rabīʿ, vizier of caliphs Hārūn
al-Rashīd and al-Amīn 8.3.4; 8.3.22; 8.25.2; 8.25.3; 8.25.4; 8.25.5
al-Faḍl ibn Sahl, vizier under the caliph al- Maʿmūn 8.20.7n
al-Faḍl ibn Yaḥyā ibn Khālid ibn Barmak, son of Yaḥyā ibn Khālid ibn Barmak 8.3.22; 8.25.7
al-Fāʾiz bi-Naṣr Allāh (Abū l-Qāsim ʿĪsā ibn
al-Ẓāfir bi-Amr Allāh), ninth Fatimid
caliph of Egypt 14.31.6
Fakhr al-Dawlah ibn al-Muṭṭalib, founder of
Dār al-Dhahab law-college 15.40.2 Fakhr al-Dīn al-Māridīnī `see` al-Māridīnī,
Fakhr al-Dīn
Fakhr al-Dīn al-Rāzī, Ibn Khaṭīb al-Rayy (‘The
Son of the Preacher of Rayy’), philosopher and theologian, author of the monu- mental Qurʾanic commentary `Mafātīḥ al-ghayb` 11.11 no. 1; 11.19; 11.20; 11.23; 15.1
no. 44; 15.19; 15.21; 15.30 no. 2; 15.31.6 nos. 5, 19; 15.40.9 nos. 19, 85; 15.52.1.1; 15.59 no. 1
Fakhr al-Dīn Riḍwān ibn Muḥammad ibn ʿAlī ibn Rustam al-Khurāsānī al-Sāʿātī, physi- cian, clock-maker and litt􏲰rateur 15.29
Fakhr al-Quḍāt ibn Buṣāqah `see` Ibn Buṣāqah
Fakhr al-Kuttāb Ḥasan ibn ʿAlī Ibrāhīm al- Juwaynī al-kātib, Ibn al-Luʿaybah `see` al-Juwaynī
Fannūn, Abū Naṣr, the Physician 10.30 al-Faʾr, al-Fār `see` Mouse
al-Fārābī, Abū Naṣr Muḥammad ibn Ūzlūgh
ibn Ṭarkhān, philosopher and scholar of music (ca. 256–338/870–950) 4.6.5.1; 4.6.13.1n; 10.22.1.2; 11.13.2.8; 13.59.2.3; 13.59.4 no. 14; 13.66.6 nos. 33, 46 14.22.4.1n; 14.25.2; 14.29.4 no. 3; 15.1; 15.17(p); 15.40.3; 15.40.9 no. 98, 119n; 141; 142; 15.51.4
Faraj, known as Abū Khurāsān, `mawlā` of Ṣāliḥ ibn al-Rashīd 8.3.15
{407}{!}
al-Farazdaq (Hammām ibn Ghālib), Umayyad poet (d. 110/728) 14.55.2(p)
al-Farghānī, Abū l-ʿAbbās Aḥmad ibn Muḥammad ibn Kathīr, (d. after 247/861) 10.1.7
Farīd al-Dīn Dāmādh, scholar in Nishapur 15.19n
al-Fāriqī, Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd al-Malik, poet
(d. after 561/1166) 15.1n
al-Fāris `see` Abū l-Khayr ibn Abī Sulaymān
Dāwūd, al-Fāris (the knight)
Fāris al-Dīn Maymūn al-Qaṣrī, Ayyubid emir
(d. 611/1214) 15.23.2.2
al-Fārisī, Abū ʿAlī `see` Abū ʿAlī al-Ḥasan ibn
Aḥmad
Fasānjas [or Fasānajis] `see` Ibn Fasānjas al-Fatḥ ibn Khāqān, held various posts under
al-Muʿtaṣim, al-Wāthiq, al-Mutawakkil (d. 247/861) 7.1.5n; 8.4.7; 8.4.8n; 8.26.9; 8.26.12
Fatḥ al-Dīn ibn Jamāl al-Dīn ibn Abī l-
Ḥawāfir, Egyptian physician 14.44.1n; 14.45; 14.46
Fathyūn al-Turjumān `see` Pethion the Trans- lator
Fāṭimah Umm Muḥammad, daughter of Ghaḍīḍ 7.8, 8.3
Fatimids 13.2.2.1; 13.3.2.3
Favorinus of Arelate, 2nd-c. A􏲬 Roman philo-
sopher 4.6.2.1n
Fayrūz (var. Fahrūn, Fahrūz) 10.8.10
Filio, disciple of Hippocrates 4.1.10.1n
al-Fīrūzābādī, Abū Ṭāhir Majīd al-Dīn
Muḥammad ibn Yaʿqūb, 8th/14th-c. lex-
icographer 8.29.1n; 8.32.2n
Flavian, archbishop of Constantinople 446– 449 6.1.3
Franks 10.83.3; 13.58.4.4; 14.49.2; 14.49.3; 15.11.2; 15.11.2.1; 13.58.4.4; 15.40.3; 15.45.2; 15.51.5
Frederick ⅠⅠ (Emperor, ‘king of the Franks’) 10.83.3; 13.63.8.1n
Furāt ibn Shaḥāthā, Jewish physician serving
ʿĪsā ibn Mūsā ibn Muḥammad 8.18.1; 8.18.2; 8.18.3; 8.18.4
Furius, physician of antiquity, pupil of Plato the Physician 3.5
Furnus, physician of antiquity, pupil of Plato the Physician 3.5
Gabriel (Archangel) AⅠⅠ.3.3(p) Gaius (Gaius Julius Caesar known as
Caligula), 1st-c. Roman emperor 5.1.8.1 Galba, 1st-c. Roman emperor 5.1.8.2 Galen/Jālīnūs, physician to emperors Marcus
Aurelius, Commodus, Septimius Severus 1.5n; 1.9; 4.8.1; 5.1; 5.1.2 (Seal of Physi- cians, rescues medicine from Meth- odism); 5.1.3–5.1.15 (rejection of John the Grammarian’s chronology); 5.1.3 (education, cf. 5.1.23–5.1.24.1–2); 5.1.4–5.1.5 (not contemporary with Christ); 5.1.5 (uncle of Paul); 5.1.12.3 (Christian continence); 5.1.14 (on Jews and Christians); 5.1.16.1–5 (house at Smyrna); 5.1.17 (under Nero acc. to Ibn Juljul); 5.1.18.1 (gladiatorial sur- geon);5.1.19 (deals with charlatan); 5.1.21.1 (taught by Cleopatra; death,
cf. 5.1.21.2); 5.1.22 (alleged cause of death); 5.1.30 (no fees); 5.1.31 (appear- ance); 5.1.32 (name); 5.1.34–5.1.36 (sayings); 5.1.37 (works); 5.1.38–39 (attributed); 6.2 (list of works com- mented on by John the Grammarian); 6.3.1–4 (works forming the Alexan- drian curriculum); 8.29.14n; 9.1; 9.31n; 10.2.4 no. 45; 10.3.14 no. 22; 10.37.2; 10.46.1; 10.57; 10.66.1; 10.66.9 no. 3; 11.5.10; 11.5.23 no. 5; 11.5.25 nos. 17, 72, 92, 11.8.4; 11.8.6 no. 12; 11.12; 11.17; 13.1.3 nos. 10, 11, 12; 13.19.1; 13.24.3(p); 13.38.2; 13.39.1; 13.43; 13.44; 13.51.1; 13.51.4 nos. 4, 5; 13.54; 13.59.4 no. 20; 13.61.3.2(p); 13.61.4 no. 4; 13.66.6 nos. 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23; 14.21 no. 2; 14.22.5.1 no. 21; 14.22.1; 14.22.4.1; 14.22.4.3 no. 44; 14.22.4.4; 14.22.4.3 no. 44.4(?); 14.22.4.3 no. 44.30; 14.25.2; 14.25.9 nos. 14, 50, 51; 14.27.1; 14.27.2; 14.32.4(p); 14.39.3(p); 14.43.1; 14.54.6; 14.54.12 (`On` `Prognosis` 􏲲); 14.55.2(p); 14.56.1; 14.58.2; 15.1
nos. 41, 78; 15.17 no. 1; 15.40.8n; 15.40.9 nos. 88, 101, 112; 15.43.1; 15.50.3; 15.51.1; 15.52.1.1
Treatises (Arabic titles), significant dis- cussion or citation
`Abundance` 10.3.14 no. 19 `Acute` `Diseases` 10.3.14 no. 18
{408}
`Affected` `Locations``/Parts` 5.1.37 no. 15; 10.3.14. no. 115; 11.5.25 no. 43
`Anatomical` `Procedures` 5.1.37 no. 21 `Anatomy` le `the` `Womb` 10.3.14 no. 20 `Art` `of Medicine` 14.29.4 no. 2 `Avoiding` `Distress` 5.1.26; 5.1.37 no. 120 `Bad` `Mixture` 10.3.14 no. 17
`Birth` `at Seven` `Months` 10.3.14 no. 21 `Black` `Bile` 10.3.14 no. 16
`Blood` `Vessels` 5.1.37 no. 10
`Bones` 5.1.37 no. 7
`Causes` `and` `Symptoms` 5.1.37 no. 14; 10.37.5 no. 22; 11.5.25 no. 142; 14.43.3 no. 2; 15.39 no. 2; 15.43.1
`Character` `Traits` 5.1.6; 5.1.12.2; 10.16 nos. 1, 2
`Classification of` `Diseases` `of Internal` `Parts` 10.37.5 no. 23
`Commentary on` `Hippocrates’` `Aphorisms` 5.1.37.no. 88; 10.56 no. 2; 10.64.20 no. 6; 11.5.25 no. 163
`Commentary on` `Hippocrates’` `Nature` le `the`
`Embryo` 5.1.37 no. 101 `Commentary on` `Hippocrates’` `Oath` 1.1; 1.6; 2.1.6.1; 4.1.1; 4.1.2; 4.1.9.2 no. 26; 5.1.36 no. 11; 13.51.2 1.1;
`Commentary on` `Hippocrates’` `Prognosis` 10.64.20 no. 7
`Composition of` `Drugs` (‘by Groups and
Varieties’, ‘by Places’) 5.1.37 no. 79; 10.57 no. 2; 14.25.9 nos. 48, 49 `Critical` `Days/Crises` 10.3.14 no. 110; 10.37.5 no. 27
`Elements` 5.1.37 no. 11; 10.3.14 no. 111; 10.37.5 no. 18; 14.25.9 no. 7
`Examinations` `by Which` `the` `Best` `Physicians` and `Recognized` 5.1.18.1–3; 5.1.29.1–3; 15.51.3
`Fevers` 10.37.5 no. 25
`Glaucon` 5.1.37 no. 6; 10.37.2; 10.37.5
no. 17; 10.57 no. 3; 13.51.4 no. 4; 14.25.9
nos. 4, 5, 6
`Good` `and` `Bad` `Juices` 5.1.24.1–2
`Great` `Book` le `the` `Pulse` 5.1.37 nos. 16, 66; 11.5.25 no. 141; 10.3.14 no. 80; 10.37.5
no. 24; 14.22.4.3 no. 44.13 `Hippocratic` `commentaries` 5.1.37
nos. 87–102, 155–157; 10.3.14 no. 29; 14.25.9 no. 26
`Method of` `Healing` 5.1.37 no. 20; 10.3.14 no. 89; 10.37.5 no. 28; 10.64.20 no. 8; 11.5.25 no. 140; 14.22.4.1; 14.25.9 no. 43; 15.43.1
`Mixture`o 10.37.5 no. 19; 14.25.9 no. 8 Mqo􏲍􏱌do 5.1.37 no. 8
Napqna􏱌 Fa􏲍q􏱌phdo 10.37.5 no. 20; 5.1.37
no. 13
Nqpnhphrd Pnl􏲤dnphdo 10.3.14 no. 84 O􏲤h􏱋hl􏱋o le Hh􏲤􏲤l􏲍napdo `and` P􏱌apl
Os􏱋 `Book`o (Ph􏱋at) 5.1.9; 5.1.10.1–2; 5.1.37
nos. 1, 92; 5.1.40; 11.5.25 no. 92 Pg􏱌dblplku 10.3.14 no. 28; 14.25.9 no. 46 P􏱌dpglna 14.25.9 no. 45
Pnlle 5.1.37 no. 115
Pqn􏲉aphrdo 10.3.14 no. 114
Rd􏲉hkd􏱋 le Hda􏱌pg 10.37.5 no. 29; 14.25.9
no. 44
Sd􏲍po 5.1.37 no. 3; 10.37.5 no. 14; 10.46.4
nos. 17, 18; 10.57 no. 3; 14.25.9 no. 1 Sd􏲍ndp Rdkdchdo 5.1.39 no. 167
Shk􏲤􏱌d `Drugs` 5.1.37 no. 53; 10.1.14 no. 157; 10.3.14 no. 15; 14.25.9 no. 47 Shtpdd􏱋 `Book`o 6.3–4; 10.37.5 no. 30; 15.40.3; 14.39.4; 15.51.1
Ska􏱌􏱌 a􏱋aplku 10.37.5 no. 21
Ska􏱌􏱌 `Art` 5.1.37 no. 4; 10.37.5 no. 15; 10.57
no. 3; 14.25.9 nos. 2, 55
Ska􏱌􏱌 `Pulse` 5.1.37 no. 5; 10.3.14 no. 38; 10.37.5 no. 16; 10.57 no. 3; 14.25.9 no. 3 Sqbophpqpd `Drugs` 10.64.20. no. 18 Sqkkanhdo le P􏱌apl􏲼o `Book`o 5.1.37 no. 124 Uod le `the` `Parts` 5.1.37 no. 49; 10.37.5
no. 41; 11.17 no. 5; 15.40.9 no. 43; 15.57.1
Cited in poetry􏲆 5.1.33; 8.30; 13.24.3; 13.61; 14.32; 14.39; 14.55; 15.10; 15.17; 15.45.3; 15.50.6; 15.52.1.2; AⅠⅠ.1
‘Galen of the Arabs’ i.e. Abū Bakr al-Rāzī 11.5.2
Gallus of Emesa, physician of antiquity 3.6; 4.1.10.2; 4.1.11.2
Gay􏲭mart, grandfather of Hermes in Persian
tradition, identified with Adam 2.1.4 Geber `see` Jābir ibn Ḥayyān
Genghis Khan, Mongol ruler 11.19.5 Germans, enemy of Rome 5.1.9 Gessius, late-antique physician 4.1.11.3; 5.1.37 no. 101; 5.2.1; 6.1.1
{409}
al-Ghaḍanfar, Abū Taghlib Faḍl Allāh
(d. 369/979), Ḥamdānid emir 15.3.1.3
Ghaḍīḍ, known as Umm Jaʿfar, favourite con- cubine of Hārūn al-Rashīd 7.3; 7.8; 8.3.10; 8.3.22n; 8.4.11; 8.25.8 al-Ghāfiqī, Abū Jaʿfar Aḥmad b. Muḥammad
al-Ghāfiqī, (d.ca. 560/1165), botanist and pharmacologist from al-Andalus 13.54; 14.58.2
Ghālib, physician of al-Muʿtaḍid (active 289/900) 8.32.2; 10.10
Ghassān ibn ʿAbbād, governor of Khorasan
under al-Maʾmūn 8.21.1; 8.21.2; 8.21.3 Ghaṭafān, confederation of ancient Arabian
tribes 8.13.2n
al-Ghazālī, Abū Ḥāmid Muḥammad al-Ṭūsī
(d. 505/1111), philosopher and theolo- gian 11.19.7 no. 3; 13.59.2.3; 13.81.2; 15.40.3
Ghiyāth al-Dīn, Muḥammad ibn Malik-Shāh
Abū Shujāʿ Ghiyāth al-Dunyā wa-l-Dīn, Seljuq ruler (498–511/1105–1118) 10.64 .19.16; 10.66.9 no. 2; 11.19.7 no. 23
Ghūrus, the second great physician of antiquity (after Asclepius) 2.2
Glaucon, philosopher friend and dedicatee of Galen 4.1.11.3; 5.1.32; 5.1.37 no. 6; 10.37.2
Glaucias of Tarentum, commentator on Hip- pocrates 4.1.10.1n
Gnosidicus, ancestor of Hippocrates 4.4.1 Gorgias, a physician of antiquity, pupil of
Ghūrus 3.2
Greeks 2.1.1 (a􏱌]Y􏱊􏱋􏱎􏱋huu􏱊􏱋); 5.1.15 (R􏱊k ao
a􏱌]Ggan􏲞mhuu􏱊􏱋)
Gregorius, Methodist physician of antiquity 3.5
Gregory (of Nyssa) `see` Nemesius
Ḥabbūs ibn Māksan ibn Zīrī ibn Manād al- Ṣanhājī, first emir of the Zirid dynasty in Granada 13.6.1.2
al-Hādī, Abū Muḥammad Mūsā ibn al- Mahdī, Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 169–170/785– 86) 8.2; 8.8.1; 8.8.2; 8.15.1n; 8.26.12n
Habīb al-ʿAjamī, traditionist 15.51.7 Hadrian, 2nd-c. Roman emperor 5.1.8.2; 5.1.25
al-Ḥafīd Abū Bakr ibn Zuhr `see` Ibn Zuhr, al-Ḥafīd Abū Bakr
al-Ḥāfiẓ li-Dīn Allāh (Abū l-Maymūn ʿAbd al-Majīd ibn al-Amīr Abī l-Qāsim Muḥammad ibn al-Imām al-Mustanṣir bi-Allāh), Fatimid caliph (d. 544/1149) 14.31.4;14.31.6
al-Ḥāfiẓ ibn ʿAsākir `see` Ibn ʿAsākir al-Ḥāfiẓī, Zayn al-Dīn, `see` Zayn al-Dīn al-Ḥāfiẓī
al-Ḥajjāj ibn Maṭar (al-Ḥajjāj ibn Yūsuf ibn
Maṭar), translator of Euclid (active 169– 218/786–833) 8.29.5; 9.12
al-Ḥajjāj ibn Yūsuf ibn Maṭar `see` al-Ḥajjāj ibn
Maṭar
al-Ḥajjāj ibn Yūsuf al-Thaqafī, Umayyad gov-
ernor (ca. 41–95/661–714) loyal to caliphs ʿAbd al-Malik and al-Walīd 7.9.1; 7.9.2; 8.8.6n; 8.13.3n; 8.18.1; 8.18.4 al-Ḥakam ibn Muḥammad ibn Qanbar (`or`
Qunbur) al-Māzinī, 3rd/9th-c. poet from
Basra 8.7
Ḥakam al-Dimashqī, personal physician to
Muʿāwiyah 7.7
al-Ḥakam ⅠⅠ, al-Mustanṣir bi-Allāh, second
Umayyad caliph of al-Andalus (nd􏲉. 350– 366/961–76), 8.29; 13.5; 13.6.1.1; 13.18; 13.19.1; 13.19.2.1;13.19.3; 13.27.1; 13.28; 13.30; 13.31; 13.32; 13.33; 13.34.1; 13.36.2.4; 13.49; 13.59.2.1
al-Ḥākim, sixth Fatimid caliph (nd􏲉. 385– 411/996–1021) 14.7; 14.16; 14.17; 14.18; 14;19; 14;20; 14.21; 14.22.3.1; 14.25.3 Ḥakīm al-Zamān `see` al-Jilyānī al-Ḥallājī `see` Yaḥyā ibn Abī Ḥakīm Ḥamdīn ibn Ubbā 13.12; 13.18 Ḥamdūn, Ibrāhīm, called Ḥamdūn (Ibn
Ismāʿīl ibn Dāwūd ibn Ḥamdūn), courtier
of caliphs al-Maʿmūn, al-Muʿtaṣim 8.4.7 Ḥāmid ibn al-ʿAbbās, vizier under al-Muqtadir 10.4.4.1
Ḥāmid ibn ʿAlī. Oculist. Brother of the fam-
ous physician Muhadhdhab al-Dīn ʿAbd
al-Raḥīm ibn ʿAlī 15.50.1
Ḥammād ibn Isḥāq, musician (150–235/767– 850) 7.10
Hammām ibn Ghālib, `see` al-Farazdaq al-Ḥammār `see` Saʿīd ibn Fatḥūn al-Saraqusṭī Ḥamzah ibn al-Ḥasan, unidentified physician 11.16 nos. 1.5, 1.21, 1.28, 1.29, 1.31
al-Ḥaqīr al-Nāfiʿ, Egyptian Jewish wound spe-
cialist ( 􏲳an􏱎􏱏h􏲛􏲞) under al-Ḥākim 14.18
{410}{!}
al-Ḥarastānī `see` Jamāl al-Dīn al-Ḥarastānī al-Harawī, student of Ibn al-Ṭayyib 10.37.4 Ḥarb ibn Muḥammad, unidentified 7.1.5 al-Ḥarīrī, author of Mam􏱎k􏱎p (d. 516/1122) 15.40; 15.40n; 15.40.9 no. 26
al-Ḥarīsh, physician at the court of the caliph
al-Muʿtaṣim (active 221/836) 8.26.10 al-Ḥārith al-Akbar, ancestor of al-Kindī 10.1.3
al-Ḥārith ibn Kaladah al-Thaqafī, legendary
Arab physician, contemporary of the
prophet Muḥammad 7.1; 15.46.6n al-Ḥārith ibn Buskhunnār, Khorasanian
prince (141/758–759) 8.10.3 al-Ḥārithī, unidentified poet 15.37.2n al-Ḥarrānī, Aḥmad ibn Yūnus ibn Aḥmad 10.9.1; 13.19
al-Ḥarrānī, ʿUmar ibn Yūnus ibn Aḥmad 13.19; 13.29.2
al-Ḥarrānī, Yūnus ibn Aḥmad 13.18; 13.19
Ḥarrānians `see` Ṣābiʾans
al-Ḥarsūn, administrator under al-Muqtadir 8.5.2
Harthamah ibn Aʿyan, surnamed ‘the unfor-
tunate’ (a􏱌]kaog􏱏􏱊k), commander under
al-Manṣūr 8.3.16; 8.10.3; 8.15.1
Hārūn ibn ʿAzūz ‘the Monk’, chronographer 5.1.7 (translation of the Torah into
Greek)
Harūn ibn Mūsā al-Ushūnī, Andalusian phys-
ician 13.33
Hārūn ibn Sulaymān ibn al-Manṣūr, friend of
the physician Yūḥannā ibn Māsawayh 8.26
Hārūn ibn Suwāratagin, Turkish off􏲊cer 8.20.5n
Hārūn, a minor physician of Baghdad 11.5.25 no. 93
Hārūn al-Rashīd, Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 170– 193/786–809) 5.1.16.2; 8.2; 8.3.15n 8.15.1n; 8.20.4n; 8.26.12n; 8.27.2n; 8.29.2n; 9.12n; 12.1n; 12.2 no. 3n; 12.5; 12.6; 14.1
Hārūt, mentioned with Mārūt in the Qurʾan (al-Baqarah 2􏲆102) as fallen angels 10.68.2.2(p); 10.69.3.7(p); 15.56.1n Ḥasan the physician 10.37.4
al-Ḥasan, physician to al-Muqtadir (295/908– 320/932) 11.5.25 no. 93
al-Ḥasan al-Baṣrī, famous preacher (d. 110/ 728) 15.51.7
al-Ḥasan al-Fasawī, physician under the Būyid dynasty 11.10
al-Ḥasan ibn al-ʿAbbās, known as al-Ṣanādīqī, unidentified historian 8.29.5
al-Ḥasan ibn ʿAlī Abū l-Jawāʾiz al-Wāsiṭī (d. 460/1067–1068), poet 10.64.19.7n
al-Ḥasan ibn ʿAlī ibn Abī Ṭālib, grandson of Muḥammad (d. ca. 49/669–670) 7.5.6
al-Ḥasan ibn al-Bahlūl al-Awānī l-Ṭīrhānī `see`
Bar Bahlūl
al-Ḥasan ibn Bishr al-Dimashqī, satiric poet
at the court of the Fatimid caliph al-ʿAzīz
bi-Allāh AⅠⅠ.11
al-Ḥasan ibn al-Ḥusayn al-Azdī, a source
used by Ibn Juljul 7.1.6
al-Ḥasan ibn Isḥāq ibn Muḥārib al-Qummī 11.5.25 no. 122
al-Ḥasan ibn Makhlad ibn al-Jarrāḥ, vizier
under al-Muʿtamid (d. 269/882) 8.4.7; 10.14.1; 10.14.2.1; 10.14.2.2; 10.44.5 nos. 3, 20
al-Ḥasan ibn Muḥammad ibn al-Ḥusayn ibn Yaḥyā, student of al-Kirmānī 13.9
al-Ḥasan ibn Muḥammad al-Ṭūsī al-Tamīmī, known as a􏱌]Aba􏲛􏲛 (‘the hoarse’), astrolo- ger favoured by Ghaḍīḍ 7.8.2; 8.3.10
al-Ḥasan ibn Quraysh, early 3rd/9th-c. physi- cian 8.15.1
al-Ḥasan ibn Sahl, governor of Iraq under al-Maʾmūn 8.3.5; 9.32
al-Ḥasan ibn Sahl, unidentified (4th/10th c.) 10.54.3 no. 2
al-Ḥasan ibn Ṣāliḥ ibn Bahlah al-Hindī 8.20.11
al-Ḥasan ibn Zīrak `see` Ibn Zīrak, al-Ḥasan al-Ḥasan ibn Suwar `see` Ibn al-Khammār al-Ḥasan ibn Zīrak `see` Ibn Zīrak al-Ḥasanī `see` al-Sharīf Muḥammad ibn
Muḥammad al-Ḥasanī
Ḥasanwayh, unidentified student of al-Kindī 10.1.9
Ḥasdāy ibn Isḥāq, Andalusian physician 13.36.2.3; 13.36.2.4; 13.49
Ḥasdāy ibn Yūsuf ibn Ḥasdāy, Abū l-Faḍl,
Andalusian physician 13.9; 13.50 Ḥasdāy ibn Shaprūṭ `see` Ḥasdāy ibn Isḥāq
{411}
Hāshim, assistant to Saʿīd ibn Tawfīl 14.4.3– 4
Hāshim, branch of the tribe of Quraysh 15.46.2
Ḥasnūn, Banū, physicians at the ʿAḍudī Hos- pital 11.5.6
Ḥassān ibn al-Ḥubāb ibn al-Walīd al- Qushayrī, 5th/11th-c. poet 15.43.3n
Ḥātim ibn Saʿīd, Andalusī poet 13.63.8.2n Ḥātim al-Ṭāʾī – pre-Islamic poet proverbial for his generosity 15.45.3(p); 15.58.1
Hawāzin, Arab tribe 15.8.4(p)
Ḥaydar ibn Kāwūs `see` al-Afshīn
Ḥayrūn ibn Rābiṭah `see` Khayrūn ibn Rābiṭah (al-)Ḥayṣ Bayṣ (‘Pell-Mell’) Abū l-Fawāris
Saʿd b. Muḥammad al-Tamīmī, poet
(d. 574/1179) 10.64n; 10.68.1.1; 10.68.1.2; 10.68.1.3; 10.68.1.4; 10.68.2.3 Ḥayzūn ibn Rābiṭah see Khayrūn ibn
Rābiṭahal-Ḥaẓīrī, ʿAlī ibn Yūsuf ibn Abī l-Maʿālī Saʿd ibn ʿAlī – known as Dallāl al-Kutub (‘the Book Hawker’); poet and anthologist 10.65.3
Heracleides, physician of antiquity, father of Hippocrates 3.6; 4.1.1
Heracleides of Tarentum, 1st-c. BC Empiricist 4.1.11.2
Heracles, divine hero in Greek mythology 2.1.6.2; 4.3.2; 4.4.2.3
Heraclitus, Presocratic Greek philosopher 4.5.2
Hermann of Carinthia, Istrian scholar and translator 4.6.13.3n
Hermes, legendary Egyptian-Greek sage, Hermes Trismegistus (Thrice-Great), identified with the Islamic Idrīs/Hermes the Second/Hermes the Third 1.1; 1.4; 2.1.4; 4.1.10.5; 10.4.9 no. 14; 14.21n; 14.23.4n
Hermias ‘the Slave’, ruler of Atarneus Herminus, teacher of Alexander of Aphrodis-
ias 4.1.11.3n; 5.1.21.1n
Hermodamus, descendant of the Homeric
Cryophylus of Samos 4.3.4.2 Hero, late-antique physician 5.2.1 Herodotus, 5th-c. BC Greek historian
(ca. 485–424BC) 1.8n
Herodotus, 1st–2nd-c. physician at Rome 1.8
Herophilus of Chalcedon, physician of antiquity 4.1.10.5
Herpyllis, Aristotle’s maid/concubine 4.6.6.1; 4.6.6.2
Hibat Allāh ibn ʿAlī Majd al-Dīn Ibn al-Ṣāḥib, qop􏱎cg D􏱎n a􏱌]Kgh􏱌􏱎eag (d. 583/1187) 10.64.16
Hibat Allāh ibn al-Faḍl ibn Ṣāʿid, Jamāl
al-Ruʾasāʾ Abū l-Fatḥ, family of Ibn al-Tilmīdh 10.64.19.17
Hibat Allāh ibn Ilyās, physician 15.23.4.2 Hibat Allāh, al-Raʾīs `see` al-Raʾīs Hibat Allāh Hieron, dedicatee of Galen 5.1.37 no. 20
hierophants, priests at Athens 4.6.2.1 Hilāl ibn Abī Hilāl al-Ḥimṣī, mathematician
(d. 218/833), translator of Apollonius’ `K.`
a􏱌]Ma􏲡gn􏱊􏲝􏱎p 9.15
Hilāl ibn Badr ibn Ḥasanwayh, Kurdish chief-
tain in the Jibāl region (d. 405/1014) 11.13.3.3
Hilāl ibn al-Muḥassin ibn Ibrāhīm al-Ṣābiʾ, secretary and historian under the Būyids (d. 448/1056) 10.3.8; 10.5.5; 10.8.7
Himerius, detractor of Aristotle 4.6.2.2 Hind, unidentified woman 13.61.3.2(p) Hipparchus, student of Aristotle 4.6.6.1 Hippocrates, Greek physician 1.1; 1.9; 2.1.5; 4.1; 4.5.3n; 5.1.37 no. 46; 9.31n; 10.1.14 no. 129; 10.37.2; 10.37.5 nos. 10–13; 11.5.10; 11.5.25 nos. 117, 163; 11.6; 11.8.4; 11.17 no. 3; 13.1.3 nos. 10, 12; 13.24.3(p); 13.51.1; 13.51.2; 14.21 no. 2; 14.25.2; 14.25.7; 14.25.9 nos. 21, 26, 28, 29, 50; 14.32.4; 14.54.6
Hippocratic works specified􏲆 3.3; 4.9.1 (list of twelve main works); 4.9.1.2 (list of other works); 9.11; 10.64.20 no. 6; 11.16 no. 3 (`Aphorisms`); 10.64.20 no. 7 (`Prognosis`); 11.5.25 no. 16311.17 nos. 3, 4; 11.18 no. 3; 13.51.4 no. 1 (`Oath`); 11.17 no. 3; 13.51.4 no. 2 (`Aphorisms`); 11.17 no. 4; 14.21 no. 2; 14.22.4.3 no. 44.7; 14.22.4.3 no. 44.14; 14.22.4.3 nos. 44.7, 44.30; 14.25.9 nos. 26, 28, 29; 14.54.9 (`Prognosis`); 15.1 no. 53; 15.10 nos. 1, 2; 11.17 no. 3; 14.54.3 (`Aphorisms` and `Prognosis`) 15.30 no. 4; 15.40.9 nos. 37
( `Aphorisms`), 38, 39 ( `Acute` `Diseases`);
{412} 15.47.3 no. 4; 15.58.8 no. 4; 15.60.1 (A􏲤g]
lnhoko and `Prognosis`); AⅠ.1 no. 1 Cited in poetry􏲆 5.1 (al-Maʿarrī), 8.30
(Isḥāq ibn Ḥunayn), 13.24.3 (Saʿīd
ibn ʿAbd Rabbih and Aḥmad ibn ʿAbd Rabbih), 13.58 (Abū l-Ṣalt Umayyah), 14.32.4 (Yūsuf ibn Hibat Allāh), 14.51.3 (ʿAḍud al-Dīn ibn Munqidh), 15.8 (Abū l-Faḍl ibn al-Milḥī), 15.10 (Ibn al-Budhūkh), 15.17 (Abū l-Ḥakam al- Maghribī), 15.37.4 (ⅠAU), 15.52.1. (ⅠAU, two poems); AⅠⅠ.1 (Anon); AⅠⅠ.15 (Ibn ʿUnayn)
Hippocrates of Gerasa, physician of antiquity 4.1.11.2
Hippolytus, 3rd-c. theologian 4.3.4.1n Hishām I al-Riḍā, emir of al-Andalus in 172– 180/788–796 13.24.1
Hishām ⅠⅠ al-Muʾayyad bi-Allāh, caliph in
al-Andalus in 365–399/976–1009 and 400–403/1010–1013 13.19.3; 13.31; 13.34.1; 13.36.1; 13.36.3 nos. 1, 3
Homer 4.1.11.3; 5.1.38 no. 139
Ḥubaysh al-Aʿsam `see` Ḥubaysh ibn Ḥasan
al-Dimashqī
Ḥubaysh ibn Ḥasan al-Dimashqī, translator
nephew of Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq 1.2; 5.1.37 no. 114; 8.29.5; 8.31; 9.4; 9.49; 10.3.14 nos. 27, 126
Hūd, pre-Islamic Arab prophet 15.17(p) Ḥujjat al-Dīn Marwān ibn ʿAlī ibn Salāmah
al-Fanakī, vizier (d. after 550/1155) 10.69.3.10; 10.69.4 no. 5
Hūlākū (Hūlāgū, H􏱮leg􏱮), Mongol conqueror, grandson of Genghis Khan (d. 663/1265) 15.32
Humām al-Dīn al-ʿAbdī, Abū ʿAlī al-Ḥasan
ibn ʿAlī ibn Naṣr, poet (d. 596/1199) 10.74 Ḥumayd al-Ṭāʾī, known as al-Ṭūsī, Abbasid
general of al-Maʾmūn 8.10.4
Ḥunayn ibn Balūʿ al-ʿIbādī, a composer and
singer of the Umayyad era 8.29.11 Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq, Abū Zayd Ḥunayn ibn
Isḥāq al-ʿIbādī, Christian physician and translator (192– 260/808–873) 4.1.8.1n; 4.1.9.1n; 4.3.5n; 4.4.3; 4.4.4n; 4.5.2; 4.5.4n; 4.6.3.5; 4.6.7.1; 4.6.7.2; 4.6.8; 4.6.9; 4.6.13.3n; 5.1.37; 5.1.37 nos. 7, 34, 35, 65, 66, 115 (his searches for
manuscripts), 117, 118, 124, 129; 5.1.38; 5.1.39; 7.8.3n; 8.1.2; 8.3.7n; 8.4.1; 8.20.3n; 8.29; 8.30; 8.31; 8.35; 9.2; 9.3; 9.4; 9.5; 9.7; 9.10n; 9.12n; 9.19; 9.20; 9.24; 9.26n; 9.27n; 9.28n; 9.30n; 9.31; 9.33; 9.34n; 9.40; 9.41n; 9.42n; 9.44n; 9.45n; 9.46n; 9.47n; 9.48n; 9.49n; 10.1.5; 10.2.4 no. 17; 10.17; 10.34 no. 1; 10.37.5 no. 31; 10.53 no. 1; 10.55 no. 2; 11.3; 11.5.25
no. 92; 11.8.6 no. 12; 14.22.4.3 no. 44.30; 14.22.4.1n; 14.25.2n 14.25.5; 14.25.9 no. 12 Treatises specified􏲆 8.16 no. 3; 9.30n; 9.41n; 9.49n; 11.8.6 no. 11; 13.36.2.1 (transla- tion of Dd Mapdnha Mdch􏲍a); 10.56
no. 1; 10.64.20 no. 9; 10.74; 11.17 nos. 1, 2; 13.58.5 no. 3 (Mao􏱎􏱏h􏱌); 13.61.4 no. 3 (`K.` a􏱌]kqc􏲡ga􏱌 h􏱌􏱎 􏱌]􏲝hbb); 14.25.9 no. 12; 15.30 no. 5; 15.31.6 no. 2; 15.36.2 no. 2; 15.37 no. 3; 15.39 no. 9; 15.46.4 no. 1; 15.50.7 no. 6; 15.60.1
Āc􏱎b a􏱌]ea􏱌􏱎oaeag 5.1.34
al-Hurthī `see` Najm al-Dīn Abū l-Ghanāʾim
Muḥammad
Ḥusām al-Dawlah, Ḥamdanid prince ruling
Mosul, 4th/10th-c. 8.5.4
Ḥusām al-Dīn Timurtāsh ibn Ilghāzī ibn
Artuq `see` Timurtāsh ibn Ilghāzī al-Ḥusayn ibn ʿAbd Allāh, grandfather of Abū
ʿAlī al-Qiyānī 8.20.12
al-Ḥusayn ibn ʿAlī ibn Abī Ṭalib 15.51.7 al-Ḥusayn ibn Fahm, a source for the histor-
ian Aḥmad ibn ʿAlī ibn Thābit al-Khaṭīb
al-Baghdādī 8.26.17
Ḥusayn ibn Kharmīn, known as Ibn Kharmīl,
ruler of Herat 11.19.3
al-Ḥusayn al-Khādim, eunuch serving al-Maʾmūn 8.24
al-Ḥuwayzī, Aḥmad ibn Muḥammad ibn
Muḥammad Abū l-ʿAbbās ‘al-ʿAbbāsī’, administrator in Baghdad of uncertain date 10.68.2.1(p)
al-Huzaymī al-Abīwardī, Abū Naṣr, 4th/10th- c. poet 15.1.4n
Hypsicles, Greek mathematician and astro- nomer (d. 120BC) 10.1.14 no. 97
Iamblichus, Syrian Neoplatonist philosopher 4.3.6.2n; 4.3.6.2 no. 20
Ibn ʿAbbād, Abū l-Qāsim Ismāʿīl ibn ʿAbbād,
{413}
known as Kāfī l-Kufāh `or` al-Ṣāḥib, Būyid vizier (d. 385/995) 8.5.2; 8.5.3; 8.5.6
nos. 1, 2; 11.5.22; 11.13.3.13; 11.13.7n
Ibn al-Abbār, Abū Jaʿfar Aḥmad ibn Muḥam- mad al-Khawlānī, Andalusian scholar 8.29.8n
Ibn ʿAbbās `see` ʿAbd Allāh ibn al-ʿAbbās Ibn ʿAbd al-Ḥakam, Egyptian historian,
author of Fqp􏱊􏲛 Mh􏲚n (d. 257/871) 14.15n
Ibn ʿAbd Rabbih, Abū ʿUmar Aḥmad ibn Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd al-Raḥmān, Andalusian litt􏲰rateur, author of a􏱌]􏱉Imc a􏱌]ean􏲞c (d. 328/940) 7.1.2n; 7.5.5n; 7.10n; 13.24.1; 13.24.3
Ibn ʿAbd Rabbih, Abū ʿUthmān Saʿīd ibn ʿAbd
al-Raḥmān, nephew of Abū ʿUmar ibn ʿAbd Rabbih, Andalusian physician 13.24
Ibn ʿAbd Rabbih, Muḥammad Raʾs al-Baghl, litt􏲰rateur 7.1.5n
Ibn Abī l-Ashʿath, Abū Jaʿfar Aḥmad ibn Muḥammad, Persian physician active in Mosul (d. ca. 360/970) 10.46; 10.48; 15.3.1.3; 15.3.1.3n; 15.4; 15.40.9 nos. 154, 155
Ibn Abī l-Bayān, al-Shaykh al-Sadīd ibn Abī-l-
Bayān (i.e. Sadīd al-Dīn Abū l-Faḍl Dāwūd ibn Abī l-Bayān Sulaymān ibn Abī l-Faraj Isrāʾīl ibn Abī l-Ṭayyib Sulaymān ibn Mubārak), Jewish physician from Egypt 14.15n; 14.32.1; 14.43
Ibn Abī Dāʾūd 8.20.6, probably an error for
Ibn Abī Duʾād
Ibn Abī Duʾād, chief qadi under al-Muʿtaṣim 8.4.2; 8.4.5; 8.20.6n
Ibn Abī l-Ḥawāfir, Jamāl al-Dīn (al-Shaykh
al-Imām al-ʿĀlim Abū ʿAmr ʿUthmān ibn Hibat Allāh ibn Aḥmad ibn ʿAqīl al-Qaysī, also known as Ibn Abī l-Ḥawāfir), Egyp- tian physician and author 14.44; 14.45; 14.46; 15.51.1
Ibn Abī l-Ḥawāfir `see` a􏱌ol Fatḥ al-Dīn ibn
Jamāl al-Dīn `and` Shihāb al-Dīn ibn Fatḥ
al-Dīn
ibn Abī Ḥulayqah `see` Muhadhdhab al-Dīn
Abū Saʿīd Muḥammad ibn Abī Ḥulayqah Ibn Abī Rimthah (`or` Ramthah) al-Tamīmī
(also known as Abū Rimthah `or` Ram-
thah), physician contemporary of
Muḥammad 7.3
Ibn Abī Ṣādiq al-Nīsābūrī, Abū l-Qāsim ʿAbd
al-Raḥmān ibn ʿAlī, 5th/11th-c. Persian physician 8.29.22; 11.17; 15.37.6 no. 3; 15.50 no. 6; 15.57.1
Ibn Abī l-Sāj 11.5.25 no. 193
Ibn Abī Shaybah, Mālikī traditionist and his-
torian 13.63.2
Ibn Abī Uṣaybiʿah, Muwaffaq al-Dīn Abū l-
ʿAbbās Aḥmad ibn al-Qāsim ibn Khalīfah, the author of the present book 􏲤aoohk treatises specified􏲆 Preface `K.` Ma􏱉􏱎􏱌hk
a􏱌]qkak sa]a􏲡gb􏱎n cgas􏲞 􏱌]􏲛h􏲡ak 􏲽Tgd Oqpop`and`h􏱋􏲉 Pdnol􏱋a􏱌hphdo le A􏱌􏱌 Naphl􏱋o); 5.1.27 (intention to write a monograph on Galen); 10.67.3 I􏲚􏱎b􏱎p a􏱌]kq􏱋a􏲳􏲳hk􏲞􏱋 (Tgd Pndch􏲍phl􏱋o le `the` Aopnl􏱌l􏲉dno); 11.5.13 Ḥh􏲡􏱎u􏱎p a􏱌]a􏲝hbb􏱎􏱏 e􏲞 􏱉h􏱌􏱎􏲳􏱎p a􏱌]acs􏱎􏱏 (A􏱋d􏲍clpdo le Pguo] h􏲍ha􏱋o l􏱋 `the` Tndapkd􏱋p le I􏱌􏱌􏱋doodo); 15.42 `K.` a􏱌]pa􏲳􏱎nhb sa]􏱌]eas􏱎􏱏hc (Et􏲤dnh] d􏱋􏲍do `and` Uodeq􏱌 Ldool􏱋o)
poetry by ⅠAU􏲆 15.20; 15.32; 15.37.4; 15.45.3; 15.49.6.1; 15.52.1.1; 15.52.1.2; 15.54
Ibn Abī Uways, Ismāʿīl, transmitter 15.46.2 Ibn Abī ʿUyaynah, name of two 2nd/9th-c.
poet brothers 7.3
Ibn Abī l-Waqqār, Abū l-Faḍl Ismāʿīl, physi-
cian 15.12; 15.17
Ibn al-ʿAdīm, Kamāl al-Dīn ʿUmar ibn
Aḥmad, 7th/13th-c. historian 8.26.17n; 8.29.6n
Ibn A􏲪􏲤aḥ, Abū l-Qāsim ʿAlī ibn A􏲪􏲤aḥ al-kātib, poet (d. 535/1141) 10.62; 10.64.19.14; 10.64.19.18; AⅠⅠ.5
Ibn al-Aḥmar, poet from the 1st/7th c. 13.63.8.2
Ibn al-ʿAmīd, Abū l-Faḍl Muḥammad ibn al-Ḥusayn ibn Muḥammad (d. 360/970), vizier and man of letters 11.5.22; 11.13.3.13
Ibn al-Āmidī `see` Abū l-Ḥasan ibn al-Āmidī Ibn ʿAnāyā al-Isrāʾīlī `see` Bishr ibn Bīshī
Ibn al-Anbārī, Sadīd al-Dawlah Muḥammad
ibn ʿAbd al-Karīm, 􏲡􏱎phb a􏱌]h􏱋og􏱎􏱏 in Baghdad chancery (d. 558/1162– 1163) 10.68.2.2
{414}{!}
Ibn ʿArabī, Muḥyī l-Dīn (d. 638/1240), Andalusī mystic and poet 13.62.2.2; 13.63.8.1
Ibn ʿAsākir, author of Ta􏱏n􏲞􏲡g Dhkaogm
(d. 571/1176) 15.49.6
Ibn al-Aṣamm 13.88
Ibn al-Aṭṭār, Ẓahīr al-Dīn Abū Bakr Manṣūr
ibn Naṣr (d. 575/1179), vizier under al-Mustanjid 15.40.3
Ibn al-ʿAynzarbī, Muwaffaq al-Dīn Abū Naṣr
ʿAdnān ibn Manṣūr, Egyptian physician 14.28n; 14.29; 14.30; 14.31.6; 14.32.1
Ibn Bābashādh, Abū l-Ḥasan Ṭāhir b. Aḥmad al-Miṣrī, grammarian 14.25.9 no. 93n; 15.40.3; 15.40.9 no. 14
Ibn Bābashādh, Abū Sulaymān, addressee of
Ibn Riḍwān 14.25.9 no. 93
Ibn Badraj probably an error for Ibn Barzaj Ibn al-Baghūnish, Abū ʿUthmān Saʿīd ibn
Muḥammad al-Ṭulayṭulī 13.34.2; 13.37; 13.38; 13.44
Ibn Bājjah, Abū Bakr Muḥammad ibn Yaḥyā ibn al-Ṣāʾigh, Andalusian philosopher and physician (d. 533/1139) 13.51.2; 13.59
Ibn al-Bakhtārī 8.20.11n
Ibn Bakhtawayh, Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAbd Allāh ibn
ʿĪsā, 11th c. physician from Wāsiṭ, active
ca. 420/1030 5.1.22; 10.1.12; 10.52
Ibn Bakkalārish (also Baklārish and Biklār-
ish), Andalusian physician 13.57 Ibn Baks (Bakūs) `see` ʿAlī ibn Ibrāhīm ibn
Baks `and` Ibrāhīm ibn Baks
Ibn al-Baladī, Sharaf al-Dīn, vizier under al-Mustanjid 10.63.2
Ibn Baqiyyah, Abū Ṭāhir [Muḥammad],
vizier of ʿIzz al-Dawlah Bakhtiyār
(d. 367/978) 10.8.2
Ibn al-Barakhshī, Abū Ṭāhir Muwaffaq al-Dīn
Aḥmad ibn Muḥammad ibn al-ʿAbbās, physician and litt􏲰rateur from Wāsiṭ (d. after 560/1165) 10.62
Ibn Barhān, Abū l-Fatḥ Aḥmad ibn ʿAlī ibn Muḥammad, grammarian and jurist (d. 520//1126) 15.40.2
Ibn Barrī, grammarian 15.40.9 no. 26 Ibn Barzaj, Abū Naṣr Muḥammad ibn ʿAlī,
student of Ibn al-Ṭayyib 10.37.4; 10.37.5
no. 40
Ibn Bassām, 3rd/9th-c. poet 8.20.5n
Ibn al-Baṭṭī, Abū l-Fatḥ Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd al-Bāqī ibn Muḥammad ibn Sulay- mān al-Baghdādī, Hadith scholar, chief traditionist of Iraq (kqo􏱋hc a􏱌]􏱉In􏱎m) (477/1084–564/1169) 15.40.1
Ibn al-Bawwāb, famous calligrapher (d. 413/1022) 15.57.1
Ibn al-Bayṭār, Ḍiyāʾ al-Dīn Abū Muḥammad ʿAbd Allāh ibn Aḥmad al-Mālaqī al- Nabātī, Andalusian pharmacologist
(d. 646/1248) 1.3.2n; 8.26.6n; 14.54.11n; 14.58
Ibn al-Biṭrīq, translator of Greek into Arabic under al-Maʾmūn 4.5.4n; 8.29.5; 9.32
Ibn al-Budhūkh al-Qalaʿī, Abū Jaʿfar ʿUmar ibn ʿAlī, Maghribī physician working in Damascus 15.10
Ibn Bundar (probably Abū l-Qāsim Yaḥyā ibn Thābit al-Wakīl) (d. 566/1170) 15.40
Ibn al-Būrī, Muwaffaq al-Dīn, Christian scribe 15.23.2.2
Ibn Buṣāqah, al-Ṣāḥib Fakhr al-Quḍāh Abū l- Fatḥ Naṣr Allāh ibn Hibat Allāh al-Ḥanafī, poet (d. 650/1252–1253) 15.22
Ibn Buṭlān, al-Mukhtār ibn al-Ḥasan ibn ʿAbdūn, Christian physician (d. 458/1066) 4.1.10.2n; 6.1.1; 8.3.23n; 8.6; 8.26.16; 8.30.5; 10.8.2; 10.13.2; 10.13.4; 10.23.2; 10.36; 10.37.4; 10.38; 10.69.3.1; 14.25.1n; 14.25.3 (quoted); 14.25.5; 14.25.9
nos. 22n, 56, 58, 59, 60, 61, 62, 102; 15.23.5n
Ibn al-Dahhān, Fakhr al-Dīn (also Abū
Shujāʿ), Muḥammad ibn ʿAlī al-Baghdādī,
astronomer (d. 590/1194) 10.66.4; 15.24 Ibn al-Dahhān `see` a􏱌ol Wajīh al-Dīn al-Wāsiṭī Ibn Dahn (`or` Ibn Dhan) the Indian, trans-
lator of Sanskrit medical texts and head of
Baghdad hospital 12.2 nos. 4n, 7n
Ibn al-Dakhwār, ʿAlī, `see` Muhadhdhab al-Dīn
ʿAbd al-Raḥīm ibn ʿAlī (d. 628/1230) Ibn al-Darrī, Yūsuf ibn Durrah, poet
(d. 545/1151) 10.64.19.11n
Ibn Dāwūd ibn Sarābīyūn, physician son of
Dāwūd ibn Sarābīyūn 8.3.10
Ibn al-Dāyah, Abū Jaʿfar Aḥmad ibn Yūsuf
ibn Ibrāhīm (d. between 330/941 and 340/951), Ṭūlūnid historian and son of Yūsuf ibn Ibrāhīm ibn al-Dāyah 7.6
{415}{!}
(quote from unidentified source); 8.3.6n; 8.29.13 (quote from R􏲠 e􏲞 􏱌] kq􏲡􏱎ea􏱏ag); 10.1.7 (quote from `K.` Ḥqo􏱋 a􏱌]􏱉qmb􏱎); in Ch. 14 he is paraphrased or quoted without attribution in 14.3; 14.4.1–14.4.4
Ibn al-Dāyah, Abū l-Ḥasan Yūsuf ibn Ibrāhīm al-Ḥāsib, courtier and assistant to Ibrāhīm ibn al-Mahdī, author of `Akhbār` a􏱌]aphbb􏱎􏱏 (d. ca. 265/878) 5.1.16.1–5 (Galen’s
status); 7.7.2; 7.8.2; 7.8.3; 8.3.6; 8.3.7; 8.3.10; 8.3.11; 8.3.12; 8.3.14; 8.3.15; 8.3.16; 8.3.17; 8.3.18; 8.3.19; 8.8.2; 8.8.3; 8.8.4; 8.8.5; 8.8.6; 8.9; 8.10.2; 8.10.4; 8.11; 8.13.2; 8.13.4; 8.15.2; 8.18.1; 8.18.3; 8.18.4; 8.19.3; 8.19.4; 8.19.5; 8.20.4; 8.20.5; 8.20.7; 8.20.8; 8.20.9; 8.20.10; 8.10.11; 8.21.2; 8.21.3; 8.21.4; 8.25.7; 8.26.5; 8.26.6; 8.26.7; 8.26.8; 8.26.9; 8.26.10; 8.26.11; 8.26.11; 8.26.12; 8.26.13; 8.26.14; 8.27.2; 8.27.3; 8.27.4; 8.29.2; 8.29.3; 12.6 (these are all quotations from the `Akhbār` a􏱌] a􏲝hbb􏱎􏱏)
Ibn al-Dayjūr, Egyptian teacher of music 15.51.1
Ibn al-Dhahabī, Abū Muḥammad ʿAbd Allāh ibn Muḥammad al-Azdī, 5th/11th- c. Andalusian physician 13.41
Ibn Dhan `see` Ibn Dahn
Ibn Diḥyah (d. 633/1235), Andalusian poet
and anthologist AⅠⅠ.10
Ibn Dīnār, 5th/11th-c. physician in Mayyāfār-
iqīn 10.41
Ibn al-Dubaythī al-Wāsiṭī, al-Ḥāfiẓ Abū ʿAbd
Allāh Muḥammad ibn Saʿīd ibn Yaḥyā,
historian (d. 637/1239) 10.80
Ibn Duminj [Domingo?], Abū Jaʿfar Aḥmad
ibn Khamīs ibn ʿĀmir 13.11
Ibn Durayd, grammarian (d. 321/933) 7.1.6n; 8.3.16n
Ibn Durustawayh ibn al-Marzubān al-Fasawī,
Abū Muḥammad ʿAbd Allāh ibn Jaʿfar,
grammarian (d. 347/958) 15.40.2 Ibn Faḍl Allāh al-ʿUmarī, encyclopaedist
(d. 749/1349) 4.4.4n; 7.1.6n; 7.8.1n; 7.10n; 8.3.23n; 8.30.5n
Ibn Faḍlān (Jamāl al-Dīn Abū l-Qasim Yaḥyā ibn ʿAlī ibn Hibat Allāh al-ʿAllāmah al-Baghdādī) – (513/1121–595/1199), professor
of Shāfiʿī law in Baghdad 15.40.2
Ibn Fāris al-Qazwīnī (d. 395/1004), philologist 15.50.5
Ibn Fasānjas [or Fasānajis], Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī
ibn al-ʿAbbās, unidentified 11th-c. critic of astrologers and enemy of Ibn al-Haytham 14.22.4.3 nos. 13, 14
Ibn Fatḥ Ṭamlūn, Muḥammad 13.17 Ibn Fātik `see` al-Mubashshir ibn Fātik Ibn al-Fawwāl `see` Munaḥḥim ibn al-Fawwāl􏲾
Ibn al-Furāt, Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Muḥam-
mad ibn Mūsā ibn al-Ḥasan (d. 312/924),
vizier to al-Muqtadir 10.5.2
Ibn Ghalindū `see` Abū l-Ḥakam ibn Ghalindū Ibn al-Ghazāl `see` Abū Jaʿfar ibn al-Ghazāl Ibn Habal (`or` Hubal), Muhadhdhab al-Dīn
Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Aḥmad ibn ʿAlī al- Baghdādī, also known as al-Khilāṭī 10.66.8; 10.81
Ibn Habal (`or` Hubal), Shams al-Dīn Abū l-
ʿAbbās Aḥmad ibn Muhadhdhab al-Dīn Abī l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Aḥmad ibn ʿAlī, physi- cian (b. 548/1153) 10.82
Ibn al-Habbāriyyah, al-Sharīf Abū Yaʿlā Muḥammad b. Ṣāliḥ, poet (d. 504/1110– 1111 `or` 509/1116) 10.64.17.2, 10.64.19.2n; 10.65.2; 10.68.2.4n 15.8.7n
Ibn Ḥafṣūn `see` Aḥmad ibn Ḥakīm ibn Ḥafṣūn Ibn al-Ḥājib, Muhadhdhab al-Dīn Aḥmad,
Damascene physician 15.24
Ibn al-Ḥajjāj, Abū ʿAbd Allāh al-Ḥusayn, poet
(d. 391/1001) 10.67.5 no. 1
Ibn al-Ḥallāʾ al-Mursī, Andalusian physician 13.83
Ibn Ḥamawayh, Abū l-Fāḍl Muḥammad, judge 11.18 no. 1
Ibn Ḥamawayh (`or` Ibn Ḥammūyah), Muʿīn al-Dīn Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad 15.51.7
Ibn Ḥamawayh (`or` Ibn Ḥammūyah), Ṣadr
al-Dīn. Shāfīʿī eamhg 15.51.7
Ibn Ḥamdān, surgeon at the al-Nūrī hospital
in Damascus 15.23.4.2
Ibn Ḥamdān, Naṣīr al-Dawlah Abū ʿAlī
l-Ḥusayn ibn Abī ʿAlī al-Ḥasan ibn Ḥamdān, 11th-c. commander under al- Mustanṣir 14.26.3 no. 2
{416}{!}
Ibn Ḥamdūn al-Nadīm (Aḥmad ibn Ibrāhīm ibn Ismāʿīl ibn Ḥamdūn), litt􏲰rateur
and companion of caliphs al-Maʾmūn, al-Muʿtaṣim, al-Mutawakkil (d. 264/877– 878) 8.4; 8.26.16
Ibn Ḥāmid ibn Muḥammad, Abū Naṣr al- ʿAzīz Aḥmad, nicknamed Āluh `or` Aluh, kqopase􏲞 (‘accountant–general’) under the Seljuq Maḥmūd ibn Muḥammad ibn Malikshāh (d. 525/1131) 10.64.19.19
Ibn Ḥammūyah `see` Ibn Ḥamawayh
Ibn Hāniʾ al-Andalusī, poet (d. ca. 362/973) 10.51; AⅠⅠ.4
Ibn Hawqal, 4th/10th-c. geographer 4.6.3.3n Ibn al-Haytham, Abū ʿAlī al-Ḥasan ibn al-Ḥasan ibn al-Haytham, mathematician, writer on optics (d. 430/1039) 10.38.4; 12.1n; 14.22; 14.23.1; 14.25.9 nos. 45n, 63; 15.40.9 no. 158
Ibn Ḥayyawayh `see` Abū l-Aṣbagh ʿĪsā Ibn
Ḥayyawayh
Ibn Ḥazm (d. 456/1064), Andalusī polymath 13.59.2.1; 13.86.1
Ibn Ḥibbān, traditionist 7.5.6n
Ibn Hindū, Abū l-Faraj ʿAlī ibn al-Ḥusayn,
poet and physician author of `K.` Mhep􏱎􏲛 a􏱌]􏲝hbb (d. 420/1029) 6.4 (discussion of
Alexandrian curriculum); 10.64.19.4n; 10.64.19.7n; 11.8.5; 11.9
Ibn Hishām, Abū Muḥammad ʿAbd al-Malik,
author of a biography of Muḥammad 7.2.3n
Ibn Hubal `see` Ibn Habal
Ibn Hubayrah, Abū l-Muẓaffar ʿAwn al-Dīn Yaḥyā ibn Muḥammad, Ḥanbalī scholar, vizier to caliphs al-Muqtafī and al-Mustanjid (d. 560/1165) 10.63.2, 10.68.2.5
Ibn Hubayrah, ʿIzz al-Dīn, vizier, patronized
by Saladin (d. 560/1165) 15.40.3; 10.68.2.3n
Ibn Ḥumayd, transmitter 7.2.3
Ibn al-ʿIbrī `see` Bar Hebraeus
Ibn al-Imām, Abū l-ḤasanʿAlī ibn ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz 13.59.2.1; 13.59.3
Ibn Isḥāq, vizier of the Umayyad emirs in
Cordova 13.20
Ibn Isḥāq, Abū Isḥāq Ismāʿīl, transmitter 15.46.2
Ibn al-Jabbāb, al-Qāḍī al-Jalīs ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz ibn al-Ḥusayn, poet (d. 561/1166) 15.47.2.1(n)
Ibn Jahīr `see` Abū Naṣr Muḥammad ibn
Aḥmad
Ibn Jahwar, Abū Marwān ʿAbd al-Malik, vizier
under ʿAbd al-Raḥmān ⅠⅠⅠ 13.21.2.1 Ibn Jakkīnā (Jakīnā, Ḥakīnā), al-Ḥasan
b. Aḥmad b. Muḥammad, 6th/12th-c. poet 10.64.17.3; 10.64.19.6n; 10.67.4.1n; 10.67.4.3n
Ibn al-Jammālah, copyist of Ibn al-Muṭrān 15.23.4; 15.23.4.1 Ibn Jamīʿ `see` Ibn Jumayʿ
Ibn Janāḥ `see` Marwān ibn Janāḥ
Ibn al-Jarrāḥ `see` Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad
ibn al-Jarrāḥ ibn Dāwūd `and` `see` Abū ʿAlī ʿAbd al-Raḥmān ibn ʿĪsā ibn Dāʾūd `and` `see` ʿAlī ibn ʿĪsā ibn Dāʾūd ibn al-Jarrāḥ `and` `see` al-Ḥasan ibn Makhlad ibn al-Jarrāḥ `and` `see` ʿĪsā ibn ʿAlī ibn ʿĪsā ibn Dāwūd ibn al-Jarrāḥ
Ibn Jazlah, Yaḥyā ibn ʿĪsā ibn ʿAlī, 5th/11th-c. physician 10.59; 14.58.4 no. 1n
Ibn al-Jazzār, Abū Jaʿfar Aḥmad ibn Ibrāhīm ibn Abī Khālid, 4th/10th-c. physician 4.1.10.2n; 13.2.2.1; 13.3; 13.25; 13.35
no. 2
Ibn Jinnī, Abū l-Fatḥ ʿUthmān al-Mawṣilī,
grammarian (d. 392/1002) 15.40.9 no. 25 Ibn Jubayr (d. 614/1217), Andalusī traveller
and writer 13.74
Ibn Juljul, Abū Dāwūd Sulaymān ibn Ḥassān
al-Andalusī, physician, author of Ṭabam􏱎p a􏱌]a􏲝hbb􏱎􏱏 sa]􏱌]􏲛q􏲡ak􏱎􏱏 (d. after 384/954) 4.5.1; 4.1.1n; 4.1.8.1n; 4.1.11.1n; 4.6.13.3n; 5.1.15; 5.1.17; 7.1.1n; 7.1.6; 7.3; 7.5n; 8.19.2; 8.26.3; 8.29.9; 8.29.12; 9.32n; 10.1.4; 10.9.1; 10.44.1; 11.5.7; 11.5.19n; 13.1.2, 13.3.2.1, 13.3.2.2; 13.3.2.3; 13.17; 13.19.23; 13.21.2.1; 13.23n; 13.23.2; 13.25n; 13.27.2n; 13.32n; 13.36; 13.38.1
Ibn Jumayʿ `or` Ibn Jamīʿ, Al-Shaykh al- Muwaffaq Shams al-Riyāsah Abū l-ʿAshāʾir Hibat Allāh ibn Zayn ibn Ḥasan ibn Ifrāʾīm ibn Yaʿqūb ibn Ismāʿīl ibn Jumayʿ al-Isrāʾīlī, Jewish physician 13.61.2.1; 14.32; 14.36.3; 14.43.2; 15.40.9 no. 87
Ibn al-Jundī, al-Qāḍī Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad
{417}{!}
ibn Hārūn al-Ghassānī, transmitter 10.81.3
Ibn al-Kalbī, Hishām, 2nd/8th-c. historian 7.9.4n; 7.10n; 8.26.13n
Ibn al-Karīm `see` Shams al-Dīn Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad ibn al-Ḥasan ibn Muḥammad al-Kātib al-Baghdādī ibn al-Karīm
Ibn Karnīb (or Kurnayb), Abū Aḥmad al- Ḥusayn ibn Abī al-Ḥusayn Isḥāq ibn Ibrāhīm ibn Zayd 10.3.14 no. 27; 10.19; 10.21
Ibn Kashkarāyā `see` Abū l-Ḥusayn
Ibn al-Kattānī (`or` al-Kitānī), prefect of Dam-
ascus in time of al-Yabrūdī 15.3.1.6 Ibn al-Kattānī, Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad ibn al-Ḥusayn, Andalusian physician (d.
ca. 420/1029) 13.29
Ibn al-Kattānī Abū l-Walīd Muḥammad ibn
al-Ḥusayn, Andalusian physician 13.28; 13.29.1
Ibn Kazūrā 10.23.2
Ibn al-Khaḍir al-Ḥalabī, Muhadhdhab al-Dīn
Abū Naṣr Muḥammad ibn Muḥammad ibn Ibrāhīm, known as al-Suṭayl, poet
(d. 655/1257) 10.64.19.1; 10.67.2; 10.67.4.2; 10.76.3; 10.67.4.1; 10.67.3; 45.3; 15.50.6 Ibn Khaldūn, historian (d. 808/1406) 8.3.22n
Ibn Khaldūn al-Ḥaḍramī, Abū Muslim ʿUmar
ibn Aḥmad (d. 449/1057) 13.5.1; 13.10 Ibn Khallikān, biographer (d. 681/1282) 8.3.16n; 8.29.11n; 8.30.5n; AⅠⅠ.8.1; AⅠⅠ.10 Ibn al-Khammār, Abū l-Khayr al-Ḥasan ibn
Suwār ibn Bābā ibn Bihrām (Bihnām), teacher of Ibn al-Ṭayyib and Ibn Hindū 6.4; 10.37.4; 11.5.20; 11.8; 11.9.1
Ibn Khanbash al-Yūnānī, Ibrāhīm (name occurs also as Ibn Ḥanbash, Ibn al-Ḥabashī, Ibn Ḥubaysh), commander of
the Fatimid army 13.2.2.1
Ibn Kharūf, ʿAlī ibn Muḥammad ibn ʿAlī
ibn Kharūf, poet, grammarian (d.
ca. 609/1212) 15.50.6
Ibn al-Khashshāb, Abū Muḥammad (or Abū
Aḥmad) ʿAbd Allāh ibn Aḥmad Ibn al- Khashshāb al-Baghdādī, grammarian
(d. 567/1172) 11.21; 15.40.2; 15.40.9 no. 26; 10.78; 10.81.4
Ibn al-Khayyāṭ, Abū Bakr Yaḥyā ibn Aḥmad, Andalusian physician (d. 447/1055–1056) 13.45
Ibn al-Khayyāṭ, Zayn al-Mulk Abū Ṭālib, unidentified (6th/12th c.) 15.8.3
Ibn Khaṭīb al-Rayy `see` Fakhr al-Dīn al-Rāzī Ibn al-Khaybarī, servant of al-Mutawakkil 8.12.2
Ibn al-Khiḍr al-Ḥalabī `see` Ibn al-Khaḍir al-Ḥalabī
Ibn Khudūd, addressee of al-Samawʾal ibn
Yaḥyā 11.21 no. 2
Ibn Killis, Abū l-Faraj Yaʿqūb, vizier of
Fatimid caliph al-ʿAzīz (318–380/930–91) 10.48; 14.14.3; 14.14.8 no. 4; AⅠⅠ.11
Ibn al-Kitānī `see` Ibn al-Kattānī
Ibn Kunāsah, Iraqi poet and scholar (123–207
`or` 208/ 741– 823 `or` 824) 7.10
Ibn al-Kuraydī `see` Najm al-Dīn ʿUmar ibn
Muḥammad al-Kuraydī
Ibn Kurnayb `see` Ibn Karnīb
Ibn al-Labbād `see` ʿAbd al-Laṭīf ibn Yūsuf al-Baghdādī
Ibn al-Lajlāj, personal physician to al-Manṣūr 8.9; 8.20.11
Ibn al-Luʿaybah `see` al-Juwaynī
Ibn al-Lubūdī `see` Najm al-Dīn ibn al-Lubūdī
`and` `see` Shams al-Dīn ibn al-Lubūdī Ibn Mākūlā, al-amīr Abū Naṣr ʿAlī ibn
Hibat Allāh, Hadith scholar and poet
(d. 485/1092) 11.9n
Ibn Maʿn `see` al-Muʿtaṣim bi-Allāh, Ibn
Ṣumādiḥ
Ibn Maʿdān `see` Abū l-ʿAskar al-Ḥusayn ibn
Maʿdān
Ibn Māhān, see Yaʿqūb al-Ṣīrāfī
Ibn Mājah, compiler of a canonical collec-
tion of hadiths 7.1.5n
Ibn Mandawayh, ʿAbd al-Raḥmān, poet,
father of Ibn Mandawayh al-Iṣfahānī 11.16
Ibn Mandawayh al-Iṣfahānī, Abū ʿAlī ibn ʿAbd al-Raḥmān, physician of Persia 11.16
Ibn Manẓūr, Abū l-Qāsim Aḥmad ibn al-Qāḍī Abī Bakr Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad ibn
Muḥammad al-Qaysī al-Mālikī al-Ishbīlī, chief qadi of Seville (d. 520/1126) 13.61.3.2
Ibn Manẓūr, Muḥammad ibn Mukarram ibn
{418}{!}
ʿAlī, 7th/13th-c. lexicographer 7.1.6n; 8.29.1n
Ibn Marʾah also known as Sharaf al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn ʿUmar ibn Abī l-Futūḥ al-Baghdādī 15.52.2n
Ibn al-Māristāniyyah, Abū Bakr ʿUbayd Allāh ibn Abī l-Faraj ʿAlī ibn Naṣr ibn Ḥamzah, physician (d. 599/1203) 10.79
Ibn Masarrah, Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd Allāh, Esotericist (Bāṭinī) philosopher from Cor- doba (d. 319/931) 4.2
Ibn Māsawayh `see` Mīkhāʾīl ibn Māsawayh `and` Yūḥannā ibn Māsawayh
Ibn Maʿshar a􏱌]`ṭabīb`, physician to al-Ḥākim in Egypt 14.20
Ibn Mashghūf `see` Muḥammad ibn Sulaymān ibn al-Hādī
Ibn al-Masīḥī `see` Abū Naṣr Saʿīd ibn Abī l- Khayr
Ibn Maṣūṣā, student of Ibn al-Ṭayyib 10.37.4
Ibn Maṭrūḥ, Abū l-Ḥasan Yaḥyā ibn ʿĪsā
ibn Ibrāhīm ibn al-Ḥusayn Jamāl al-Dīn, poet and high off􏲊cial under Ayyubids, vizier of Damascus (592–649/1196–1251) 10.64.19.7n; 14.32.2; 14.32.4n; 15.49.2; 15.50; 15.56.1
Ibn Maymūn `see` Abū Ghālib Muḥammad ibn
al-Mubārak
Ibn Maymūn (Maimonides) `see` Mūsā ibn
Maymūn
Ibn Miknasah al-Iskandarī, poet 15.58.3n Ibn al-Milḥī, Abū l-Faḍl, poet (6th/12th c.) 15.8.1
Ibn al-Minfākh `see` Najm al-Dīn ibn al-Minfākh
Ibn Muʾahhal (?Mūhal), poet (?= ‘Ibn Mūhad
al-Shāṭibī’) 13.68n
Ibn al-Muʿallim al-Hurthī, Najm al-Dīn Abū l-
Ghanāʾim Muḥammad ibn ʿAlī, poet from
Wāsiṭ (501–1108/592–1196) 10.62.3 Ibn al-Muʾammil, Abū l-Ḥusayn Ṣāʿid ibn
Hibat Allāh, physician (d. 591/1195) 10.78
Ibn al-Mudabbir, Abū Isḥāq Ibrāhīm ibn Muḥammad, courtier and man of letters (d. 279/892) 10.44.5 no. 5
Ibn al-Mudabbir, Aḥmad ibn Muḥammad, known as a􏱌]K􏱎phb, high off􏲊cial under
al-Wāthiq and al-Mutawakkil (d. 270 `or` 271/883 `or` 84) 8.4.10; 9.46
Ibn Muhājir, founder of law-college in Mosul 15.40.3
Ibn Mulsāqah, Muḥammad ibn Saʿīd
ibn Hishām al-Ḥajarī, known as Ibn Mulsāqah, copyist in Fatimid Egypt 14.26.1
Ibn Mulūkah al-Naṣrānī 13.15
Ibn al-Munajjim, Abū Aḥmad Yaḥyā ibn ʿAlī,
Abbasid litt􏲰rateur (d. 300/912) 10.3.11 Ibn al-Munajjim, Abū ʿĪsā 10.44.2
Ibn al-Munajjim, ʿAlī ibn Yaḥyā `see` ʿAlī ibn
Yaḥyā, known as Ibn al-MunajjimIbn al- Munajjim al-Miṣrī, Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Mufarrij, poet (d. 616/1219–1220) 14.32.4
Ibn Munqidh, ʿAḍud al-Dīn (`or` ʿAḍud al- Dawlah) Abū l-Fawāris Murhaf ibn Usāmah (d. 613/1216), poet, son of Usāmah ibn Munqidh 14.51
Ibn Munqidh, Muʾayyid al-Dawlah Abū l-Muẓaffar Usāmah `see` Usāmah ibn Mun- qidh
Ibn Munqidh, al-Mubārak ibn Kāmil ibn ʿAlī, high off􏲊cial under Saladin 14.33, 14.33.3
Ibn al-Muqaffaʿ, ʿAbd Allāh, translator of
Ka􏱌􏲞􏱌ag sa]Dhk􏱋ag (d. ca. 137/755) 11.2; 4.6.11n
Ibn Muqashshir Abū l-Fatḥ Manṣūr ibn Sah- lān, Christian physician 14.15; 14.16; 14.18; 14.20n
Ibn Muqlah, Abbasid vizier, famous calli-
grapher (d. 328/940) 10.5.3; 10.5.4; 14.29.3n
Ibn al-Murakhkhim, Abū l-Wafāʾ Yaḥyā ibn Saʿīd, physician and chief qadi under al- Muqtafī (d. 555/1160) 10.68.2.4
Ibn Mūrāṭīr `see` Abū l-Ḥajjāj Yūsuf ibn Mūr- āṭīr
Ibn Mus􏲿hir, Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Saʿīd ibn ʿAlī ibn ʿAbd al-Wāḥid, poet (d. 543/1148 `or` 546/1151) 10.69.3.12
Ibn al-Muʿtazz, ʿAbd Allāh, Abbasid prince and poet (d. 296/908) 8.3.19n; 13.63.8.2n
Ibn al-Muṭrān, Muwaffaq al-Dīn, Abū Naṣr Asʿad ibn Ilyās, personal physician of Saladin, teacher of al-Dakhwār, author of Bqop􏱎􏱋 a􏱌]a􏲝hbb􏱎􏱏 sa]nas􏳀ap a􏱌]a􏱌hbb􏱎􏱏
{419}
(d. 578/1191) 1.2; 5.1.14;10.64.4; 15.3.1.1; 15.3.1.4; 15.3.1.6; 15.23; 15.34; 15.36.1; 15.50.1; AⅠⅠ.15; AⅠⅠ.15(p)
Ibn al-Muwaffaqī, unidentified physician 15.3.2 no. 2
Ibn al-Nabbāsh, Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd Allāh ibn Ḥāmid al-Bijāʾī, Andalusian physician 13.42
Ibn al-Nadīm, Abū l-Faraj Muḥammad ibn Abī Yaʿqūb Ishāq, known as al-Warrāq al- Baghdādī, author of the Fhgnhop 4.1.5n; 4.1.9.1n; 4.1.10.2n; 4.1.11.1n; 4.1.11.3n; 4.5.2n; 4.5.4n; 4.6.2.3n; 4.6.3.5; 4.6.13.3n; 4.7n; 4.8n; 6.1.2; 7.1.5n; 8.2n; 8.15.1n; 8.16n; 8.26.4; 8.26.16n; 8.26.20n; 8.28n; 8.29.2n; 8.29.5n; 8.29.9 n; 8.29.11n; 8.36n; 8.37n; 8.38n; 10.1.6; 10.1.9; 10.1.12; 10.4.2; 10.22.2; 10.44.2; 11.4; 11.5.9
Ibn Nafādah `see` Bahāʾ al-Dīn ibn Nafādah Ibn Nafīs, Abū l-Ḥasan `see` Abū l-Ḥasan ibn
Nafīs
Ibn al-Nafīs, ʿAlāʾ al-Dīn ʿAlī ibn Abī l-Ḥazm
al-Qurashī (or al-Qarashī) (d. 687/1288),
physician AⅠ
Ibn al-Naḥḥās, Muwaffaq al-Dīn Hibat Allāh
Abū l-Qāsim ibn ʿAbd al-Wahhāb ibn Muḥammad ibn ʿAlī al-Kātib, poet 15.49.6.2
Ibn Nāʿimah (ʿAbd al-Masīḥ ibn ʿAbd Allāh
al-Ḥimṣī al-Nāʿimī), translator of Greek
philosophy 9.13; 9.37n
Ibn al-Nāqid `see` Abū l-Faḍāʾil ibn al-Nāqid Ibn al-Naqqāsh, `see` Muhadhdhab al-Dīn ibn
al-Naqqāsh
Ibn Nubātah al-Khaṭīb, orator and preacher,
author of a􏱌]Kgq􏲝ab a􏱌]􏱋qb􏱎phuuag
(d. 374/984–985) 15.40.9 no. 15
Ibn al-Qabīḍī, Muḥammad ibn Abī l-Wafāʾ ibn Aḥmad al-ʿUmarī (active 610/1213),
poet 10.68.2.4n
Ibn Qablāl `see` Abū Marwān ʿAbd al-Malik ibn
Qablāl
Ibn Qāḍī l-Yaman, Sharaf al-Dīn Ismāʿīl ibn
ʿAbd Allāh ibn ʿUmar al-Kātib, poet (b. 589/1193) 15.49.6.2
Ibn Qamāniṣ al-Hindī, unidentified Indian
king 12.3 no. 4
Ibn al-Qāsim, son of Abū Dulaf and tax-
collector under al-Muʿtaṣim 8.20.11
Ibn Qaṭramīz `see` Abū Ṭāhir ibn ʿAbd al- Bāqī
Ibn al-Qaṭṭān al-Baghdādī `see` Abū l-Qāsim Hibat Allāh ibn al-Faḍl
Ibn Qawsayn (Qūsīn), physician in Mosul 10.49
Ibn al-Qaysarānī, Muḥammad ibn Naṣr ibn Dāghir, poet (d. 548/1154) 10.67.4.2 Ibn Qayyim al-Jawziyyah, writer on law and
theology (d. 751/1350) 7.9.2n
Ibn al-Qifṭī, Jamāl al-Dīn Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn
Yūsuf ibn Ibrāhīm ibn ʿAbd al-Wāḥid al- Shaybānī, vizier and biographer author of I􏲡gb􏱎n a􏱌]􏱉q􏱌ak􏱎􏱏 bh]a􏲡gb􏱎n a􏱌]􏲛q􏲡ak􏱎􏱏 commonly referred to as T􏱎n􏲞􏲡g a􏱌] 􏲛q􏲡ak􏱎􏱏 (d. 646/1248) 4.1.5n; 4.1.9.1n; 4.1.10.2n; 4.1.11.1n; 4.3.1n; 4.4.2.1n; 4.4.4n; 4.5.2n; 4.5.4n; 4.6.3.2n; 4.6.13.1n; 4.8n; 4.8.2n; 7.1.1n; 7.5n; 7.8.1n; 8.1.1n; 8.1.2n; 8.3.6n; 8.4.10n; 8.6n; 8.10n; 8.11n; 8.12n; 8.13n; 8.14n; 8.15.1n; 8.16n; 8.18n; 8.20.3n; 8.20.12n; 8.21n; 8.24n; 8.26.5n; 8.26.6n; 8.26.8n; 8.26.9n; 8.26.13n; 8.26.14n; 8.26.20n; 8.27n; 8.27.4n; 8.28n; 8.29.2n; 8.29.6n; 8.29.11n; 8.29.12n; 10.77.3; 11.3; 11.21; 13.3.4 no. 5; 14.14.3; 14.14.4n; 14.14.6; 14.22.3.1–2; 14.39.2n; 15.23.2; 15.23.2.1; 15.36.1.1
Ibn al-Quff, Muwaffaq al-Dīn Yaʿqūb ibn Isḥāq, Christian physician (d. 685/1286) 10.3; 10.37.3; 15.60
Ibn Qusaym, unidentified 15.47.2.2(p)
Ibn Qūsīn `see` Ibn Qawsayn
Ibn Qutaybah al-Dīnawarī, Islamic polymath
(213–276/828–89) 7.1.6n; 8.29.22n; 10.1.10; 15.40.2; 15.40.9 no. 1
Ibn Raḥmūn `see` Salāmah ibn Raḥmūn
Ibn Rāʾiq, military commander (d. 330/942) 10.4.9 no. 5
Ibn Raqīqah, Abū l-Thanāʾ Maḥmūd ibn
ʿUmar ibn Muḥammad al-Ṭabīb ibn Ibrāhīm ibn Shujāʿ al-Shaybānī al- Ḥanawī, Sadīd al-Dīn, physician author of `K.` M􏱊􏳀h􏲛ap a􏱌]hogphb􏱎g e􏲞 acshuap a􏱌]b􏱎g (565/1169–636/1238) 10.54.2; 10.64.10; 10.64.18; 10.69.1; 10.69.3.1; 10.75.1; 10.75.2; 14.23.2; 14.30; 15.18.1; 15.18.1.4; 15.33; 15.46; 15.51.1; `see` a􏱌ol Sadīd al-Dīn al-Manṭiqī
{420}
Ibn Rashīq, author of the `K.` a􏱌]􏱉qkcag 15.40.9 no. 31
Ibn al-Rāwandī, Abū l-Ḥusayn Aḥmad ibn Yaḥyā b. Isḥāq, b. start 3rd/9th-c., follower then critic of Muʿtazilism and the proph- ecy of Muḥammad 10.1.14 no. 187; 14.22.5.1 no. 8; 15.1.5 no. 42
Ibn Riḍwān, Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī, Egyptian
physician at court of Fāṭimid caliph al- Mustanṣir (d. 453/1061 `or` 460/1068) 1.5; 4.1.2; 4.1.8.1n; 4.1.9.1n; 5.1.4n (Galen’s dates); 6.3.1–4 (account of the Alex- andrian medical curriculum); 8.26.9n; 10.38.2; 10.38.3; 10.38.6 no. 6; 11.5.25
no. 166; 11.8.4; 14.7; 13.2.3 no. 1; 13.51.4 no. 4; 13.58.5 no. 3; 13.61.4 no. 3; 14.14.8n; 14.22.4.3 no. 44n; 14.23.1; 14.25; 14.26.1; 14.27.2; 14.32.2; 15.3.1.2; 15.40.9 no. 88
Specific treatises
Rdol􏱌qphl􏱋 a􏱌]R􏱎v􏲞􏲼o Dlqbpo nd􏲉anch􏱋􏲉 Ga􏱌d􏱋 11.8.4
Uodeq􏱌 `Book` 6.3.1–4
Ibn Rūmān al-Naṣrānī, Khālid ibn Yazīd 13.14
Ibn al-Rūmiyyah, Abū l-ʿAbbās Aḥmad ibn Muḥammad ibn Mufarrij al-Nabātī, expert in botany 13.63.6; 13.86
Ibn Rushd, Abū Muḥammad ʿAbd Allāh `see` Abū Muḥammad ʿAbd Allāh ibn Rushd
Ibn Rushd (Averroes), Abū l-Walīd Muḥam- mad ibn Aḥmad, philosopher (d. 595/ 1198) 13.59.3; 13.62.4 no. 1; 13.65; 13.66; 13.81.1; 13.82; 14.58.4 no. 1n
Ibn Ruzzīk `see` Ṭalāʾiʿ ibn Ruzzīk
Ibn Saʿādah, Abū Zakariyyā Yahūdhā, 11th-c.
Jewish Egyptian physician 14.25.9 nos. 17, 18, 55
Ibn al-Sāʿātī `see` Fakhr al-Dīn Riḍwān and Bahāʾ al-Dīn Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī
Ibn Ṣadāqah, Ibrāhīm ibn Abī l-Faḍl, physi- cian of Aleppo 15.18.1.1
Ibn Ṣadaqah, (probably Jalāl al-Dīn Muḥam- mad ibn Aḥmad ibn Ṣadaqah), vizier and friend of Amīn al-Dawlah Ibn al-Tilmīdh (d. 556/1161) 10.64.19.15; 10.68.2.5
Ibn Ṣādiq `see` Ibn Abī Ṣādiq
Ibn Sadīr, Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Muḥammad
ibn ʿAbd Allāh, physician (d. 6060/1210) 10.80
Ibn al-Ṣaffār, Abū l-Qāsim Aḥmad ibn ʿAbd Allāh 13.7
Ibn al-Ṣaffār al-Mutaṭabbib, Abū Jaʿfar ibn ʿAbd Allāh, student of Ibn Khaldūn 13.5.1; 13.10
Ibn Ṣafiyyah, Abū Ghālib al-Ṭabīb al-Naṣrānī, physician during the reign of al-Mustanjid (566–575/1170–1180) 10.63;
AⅠⅠ.9
Ibn Ṣāḥib al-Ṣalāh, Abū al-Qāsim Hishām
ibn Ismāʿīl ibn Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad,
unidentified Sevillian physician 13.61.3.1 Ibn Sahlān, probably Zayn al-Dīn ʿUmar ibn Sahlān al-Sāwī `or` al-Sāwajī, author of a􏱌]
Tab􏲚hnag (= `K.` a􏱌]Ba􏲚􏱎􏱏hn a􏱌]Na􏲚􏲞nhuuag e􏲞
􏱉h􏱌k a􏱌]ka􏱋􏲝hm) 15.19; 15.30
Ibn al-Sāʿī, Tāj al-Dīn ʿAlī ibn Anjab, 7th/13th-
c. historian 8.23.1n
Ibn Ṣāʿid al-Qurṭubī ([al-Qāḍī] Abī l-Qāsim
Ṣāʿid ibn Aḥmad ibn Ṣāʿid al-Andalusī) `see`
Ṣāʿid al-Andalusī
Ibn al-Ṣāʾigh al-ʿAntarī, Abū l-Muʾayyad
Muḥammad ibn al-Mujallī (d. ca. 560/ 1165) 10.69
Ibn al-Ṣalāḥ, Najm al-Dīn Abū l-Futūḥ
Aḥmad ibn Muḥammad ibn al-Sarī, philo- sopher, astronomer, physician (d. 540/1145 `or` 548/1153) 10.75.1; 15.17
Ibn al-Ṣalāḥ al-Shahrazūrī (d. 643/1225), Hadith scholar 15.17n
Ibn Samajūn, Abū Bakr Ḥāmid, author of a `K.` a􏱌]acshuag a􏱌]kqenacag 13.52; 15.40.9
no. 80
Ibn al-Samḥ al-Baghdādī, Abū l-Qāsim
Aṣbagh ibn Muḥammad, Christian com- mentator on Aristotle (d. 418/1027) 13.5.1; 13.6; 14.22.4.3 no. 43; 14.22.5.2
no. 91n; 14.24
Ibn al-Samīnah `see` Yaḥyā ibn Yaḥyā Ibn Sanāʾ al-Mulk, al-Qāḍī l-Saʿīd Abū l-
Qāsim Hibat Allāh ibn Abī l-Faḍl Jaʿfar ibn al-Muʿtamid, Ayyubid qadi and writer of kqsaogoga􏲛􏱎p (550–608/1155–1211) 14.33.3; 14.39.3 (poem on Maimonides); 15.40.3
Ibn Sarābiyūn, Dāwūd `see` Dāwūd ibn Sar-
ābīyūn
{421}
Ibn Sarābiyūn, Yūḥannā `see` Yūḥannā ibn Sarābiyūn
Ibn al-Sarrāj, author of `K.` a􏱌]U􏲚􏱊􏱌 15.40.2 Ibn Sawād al-ʿAyn `see` Badīʿ al-Dīn Abū l-Fatḥ
Manṣūr
Ibn al-Ṣayrafī `see` Abū l-Qāsim ʿAlī ibn Sulay-
mān
Ibn Sayyid al-Muhandis, Abu Zayd ʿAbd ar-
Rahman, Andalusī geometer 13.59.4 no. 19
Ibn Shahdā al-Karkhī, Syriac-to-Arabic trans- lator 9.11
Ibn al-Shajarī, scholar, teacher of al-Khaṭīb al-Tibrīzī 15.40.2
Ibn Shākir al-Kutubī, Muḥammad (d. 764/ 1363), Syrian historian and anthologist
AⅠⅠ.2.2
Ibn Shamʿūn, Yūsuf `see` Yūsuf al-Isrāʾīlī 15.41 Ibn al-Shanāʿah, unidentified Andalusī math-
ematician 13.38.1
Ibn Shaprūṭ `see` Ḥasdāy ibn Isḥāq
Ibn al-Sharīf al-Jalīl, al-Sayyid al-Naqīb al-Kāmil, author of panegyric on Amīn
al-Dawlah Ibn al-Tilmīdh 10.64 Ibn al-Shaṭajayrī, Ḥabīb ibn Aḥmad,
Andalusī poet 13.14
Ibn Shaʿyā see Abū l-Barakāt ibn Shaʿyā Ibn (al-)Shibl al-Baghdādī, Abū ʿAlī al-Ḥusayn (`or` Muḥammad ibn al-Ḥusayn) ibn ʿAbd Allāh, physician and poet from Baghdad (d. 474/1081–1082) 10.51;
AⅠⅠ.3.1; AⅠⅠ.3.2; AⅠⅠ.3.3
Ibn al-Shiḥnah, Muhadhdhab al-Dīn Abū
Ḥafṣ ʿUmar ibn Muḥammad al-Mawṣilī,
poet (d. 608/1211 `or` 606/1209) 14.55.2n Ibn Shūʿah `see` al-Muwaffaq ibn Shūʿah
Ibn Shukr `see` al-Ṣaḥib Ṣafī al-Dīn ibn Shukr Ibn al-Sikkīt, philologist and lexicographer
(d. ca. 243/857) 7.2.4n
Ibn Sīnā, Abū ʿAlī al-Ḥusayn ibn ʿAbd Allāh
al-Shaykh al-Raʾīs (d. 428/1037) 1.2n; 8.26.6n; 10.35; 10.37.2; 10.51.2; 10.64.20 no. 12; 10.69.3.1; 10.75.1; 10.75.2; 10.75.4 no. 1; 10.83.7 no. 3; 11.11; 11.12; 11.13; 11.14; 11.15; 11.17; 11.19.7 nos. 34n, 35n, 62; 11.20; 11.23; 13.59.2.3; 13.61.2.1; 13.61.4 no. 6; 13.66.6 nos. 5, 37, 40; 14.29.4 no. 3; 14.32.5 no. 2n; 14.48.2; 14.48.3 no. 1; 15.10; 15.10 no. 4; 15.20 no. 2; 15.21 no. 2; 15.29; 15.29 nos. 1, 2; 15.31.6 nos. 1, 3, 4; 15.37.5 no. 2; 15.40.1; 15.40.3; 15.40.4; 15.40.9 nos. 87, 144, 147; 15.45.3(p); 15.46.4 no. 1; 15.49.6; 15.50.1; 15.57.1; 15.50.6(p); 15.52.1.1(p); 15.60.2 no. 2; AⅠ.1; AⅠ.2; AⅠ.3; AⅠⅠ.1(p); AⅠⅠ.8.1; AⅠⅠ.8.2
Ibn al-Sinjārī `see` Badr al-Dīn Abū l-ʿIzz Yūsuf ibn Makkī
Ibn Siqlāb, Muwaffaq al-Dīn Yaʿqūb, Christian physician of Ayyubid emir Fāris al-Dīn Maymūn al-Qaṣrī (d. 624/1227) 15. 23.2.2; 15.43; 15.44
Ibn al-Ṣūfī `see` Muʾayyid al-Dīn Abū l-Fawāris Ibn Sukaynah (probably Ḍiyāʾ al-Dīn Abū
Aḥmad ʿAbd al-Wahhāb ibn al-Amīn al-Baghdādī), (d. 607/1210), pupil of Ibn Khashshāb 15.40.3
Ibn Sukkarah al-Hāshimī (d. 385/995), poet 15.52.1.2n
Ibn al-Ṣūrī `see` Rashīd al-Dīn ibn al-Ṣūrī Ibn al-Suwaydī, ʿIzz al-Dīn Abū Isḥāq
Ibrāhīm ibn Muḥammad, Damascene
physician (d. 690/1291) 15.23.3; 15.57 Ibn Ṭabāṭabā al-ʿAlawī, Abū l-Ḥāsan
Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad (d. 322/934) 10.1.10n; AⅠⅠ.2.1n
Ibn al-Tabbān, Ṣafī al-Dīn Abū ʿAlī, teacher of music 15.51.1
Ibn Ṭalḥah al-Kātib al-Baghdādī, Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Ḥamzah, secretary to the Ḥājib of the Bāb al-Nūbī (d. 599/1202–1203) 15.40.3
Ibn Tammām `see` Abū l-Maʿālī ibn Tammām Ibn al-Tammār, Abū Bakr al-Ḥusayn 11.5.25
no. 60
Ibn Tāshufīn (`or` Tāshfīn), Almoravid ruler
(nd􏲉. 453–500/1061–1106) 13.59.2.1n; 13.61.4 no. 9
Ibn Tātalī, itinerant scholar 15.40.3; 15.40.3n
Ibn al-Ṭayyib, Abū l-Faraj ʿAbd Allāh, Christian physician and philosopher
(d. 435/1043) 10.37; 10.38.1; 10.38.4; 11.13.8
no. 97; 14.22.5.1 nos. 3, 21; 14.25.5; 14.25.9
no. 22; 15.3.1; 15.4; 15.36.2 no. 1
Ibn al-Thallāj `see` Muḥammad ibn Thawāb Ibn Thawābah, Abū l-ʿAbbās Aḥmad ibn
Muḥammad, jurist (d. 277/890–891) 10.2.4 no. 46
{422}{!}
Ibn al-Tilmīdh, Abū l-ʿAlāʾ Ṣāʿid ibn Ibrāhīm, physician, father of Amīn al-Dawlah Ibn al-Tilmīdh 10.58.2; 10.64.1
Ibn al-Tilmīdh, Amīn al-Dawlah Abū l-Ḥasan Hibat Allāh ibn Ṣaʿīd, Christian court physician of al-Mustaḍī bi-Amr Allāh, author of a􏱌]Amn􏱎b􏱎cg􏲞􏱋 a􏱌]􏲡ab􏲞n, intellec- tual (466/1073–561/1165) 8.16 no. 1; 10.63.3; 10.64; 10.66.7; 10.67.1; 10.68.1.3; 10.68.2.4; 10.75.1; 10.76.3; 11.5.25 no. 93; 11.12 no. 1; 15.13; 15.23.1; 15.40.3
Ibn al-Tilmīdh, Muʿtamad al-Mulk Abū l- Faraj Yaḥyā ibn Ṣāʿid ibn Yaḥyā, physician and poet (d. 559/1164 according to Yāqūt, but Ibn al-Qifṭī has ca. 502/1108) 10.65
Ibn al-Tilmīdh, Raḍī al-Dawlah Abū Naṣr ibn Hibat Allāh (ibn) Ṣāʿid, physician son of (Amīn al-Dawlah) ibn al-Tilmīdh 10.64.15; 10.64.16; 15.40.3n
Ibn Ṭufayl (d. 581/1185–1186), Andalusī philo-
sopher 13.66.6 no. 36
Ibn Tuffāḥ, contemporary of Ibn al-Tayyib 10.37.4
Ibn Ṭughj, founder of the Ikshīdid dynasty
(nd􏲉. 323–334/935–46) 14.6; 14.8n; 14.14.3 Ibn Ṭūlūn `see` Aḥmad ibn Ṭūlūn
Ibn Ṭūmār al-Hāshimī `see` Ibrāhīm ibn al-ʿAbbās
Ibn Tūmart (d. 524/1130), Almohad Mahdī 13.62.1; 13.66.3n
Ibn Ṭumlūs `see` Abū Isḥāq ibn Ṭumlūs Ibn ʿUbaydah al-Karkhī, grammarian
(d. 605/1208) 15.40.2
Ibn ʿUkāshah, unidentified surgeon in al-Karkh 10.76.2; 10.76.3
Ibn al-ʿUlayq (`or` al-ʿUlayyiq), student of Ibn
al-Ṭayyib 10.37.4
Ibn ʿUlaymah, `see` Nāṣir al-Dīn Zikrī `or`
Zakarī
Ibn ʿUmar, Companion of the Prophet, trans-
mitter 10.81.3
Ibn Umm al-Banīn al-Aʿraf, physician in Cor-
dova (active 310/922) 13.23
Ibn ʿUnayn, Sharaf al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn
Naṣr (`or` Naṣr Allāh) ibn al-Ḥasan, Damas-
cene poet (d. 630/1233) 11.19.3; 15.3.1; 15.25; AⅠⅠ.15
Ibn ʿUrwah, unidentified 15.33 no. 3
Ibn ʿUrwah, Hishām, transmitter 15.46.2
Ibn Uthāl, Christian of Damascus, personal physician to Muʿāwiyah 7.5
Ibn Uthrudī, Abū ʿAlī al-Ḥasan ibn ʿAlī, physi- cian 10.73
Ibn Uthrudī, Abū l-Ghanāʾim Hibat Allāh ibn ʿAlī ibn al-Ḥusayn, physician 10.70
Ibn Uthrudī, Abū l-Ghanāʾim Saʿīd ibn ʿAlī ibn Hibat Allāh, physician 10.72
Ibn Uthrudī, Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Hibat Allāh ibn ʿAlī, physician 10.71
Ibn Uthrudī, ʿAlī ibn Hibat Allāh, physician 10.37.4; 10.64.20. no. 14
Ibn Uthrudī, Jamāl al-Dīn Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Abī l-Ghanāʾim Saʿīd ibn ʿAlī ibn Hibat Allāh ibn ʿAlī, physician 10.74
Ibn Waḥshiyyah, Abū Bakr Aḥmad (`or` Muḥammad) ibn ʿAlī al-Nabaṭī, alchemist and astronomer, author of `K.` a􏱌]􏲌􏲻􏱌􏱎􏲛ag a􏱌]􏱋aba􏲝huuag (d. ca. 190/800) 1.1; 15.23.5
no. 4; 15.40.3
Ibn Wāfid, ʿAbd al-Raḥīm ibn Muḥammad
ibn ʿAbd al-Karīm, author of a `K.` a􏱌] acshuag a􏱌]kqenacag (d. 460/1068) 13.29.2; 13.37; 13.39; 13.59.4 no. 20; 15.40.9 no. 79
Ibn Wakīʿ al-Tinnīsī, ʿAlī ibn Wakīʿ al-Tinnīsī,
poet and critic (d. 393/1003) 10.64.19.7n Ibn al-Waqashī, Abū al-Walīd Hishām ibn
Aḥmād ibn Hishām, qadi of Talavera
(Toledo) 13.11; 13.11n
Ibn al-Waṣīf al-Ṣābiʾ 10.9; 13.19.1
Ibn al-Wāsiṭī, physician to al-Mustaẓhir bi-
Allāh 10.61; 10.62.2 (?)
Ibn al-Yasaʿ, Abū Yaḥyā al-Yasaʿ ibn ʿĪsā ibn
Ḥazm, Fatimid historian 13.40; 13.52; 13.61.2.2
Ibn Yūnus `see` Kamāl al-Dīn ibn Yūnus Ibn al-Zaffān `see` Ifrāʾīm (Ephraim) ibn al-Zaffān
Ibn Zahrūn `see` Abū Isḥāq Ibrāhīm ibn
Zahrūn
Ibn Zaylā `see` Abū Manṣūr ibn Zaylā
Ibn Zayrak, `see` Ibn Zīrak, al-Ḥasan
Ibn al-Zayyāt, Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd al-Malik,
Abbasid vizier and poet (d. 243/847) 8.4.2; 8.20.11; 9.49
Ibn Zīrak, al-Ḥasan, Egyptian physician dur- ing governorship of Aḥmad ibn Ṭūlūn 14.3; 14.4.1n
{423}
Ibn al-Zubayr, al-Qāḍī al-Muhadhdhab al- Ḥasan ibn ʿAlī ibn Ibrāhīm ibn al-Zubayr, poet (d. 561/1166) 14.47
Ibn al-Zubayr, al-Qāḍī Nafīs al-Dīn `see` Nafīs al-Dīn ibn al-Zubayr
Ibn Zuhr, Abū l-ʿAlāʾ Zuhr ibn Abī Marwān ʿAbd al-Malik ibn Muḥammad ibn Mar- wān, Andalusian physician 1.5 n.; 13.61;
AⅠⅠ.10
Ibn Zuhr, Abū Marwān ʿAbd al-Malik ibn
Muḥammad ibn Marwān, Andalusian
physician 13.60
Ibn Zuhr, Abū Marwān ibn Abī l-ʿAlāʾ ibn
Zuhr (Abū Marwān ʿAbd al-Malik ibn Abī l-ʿAlāʾ Zuhr ibn Abī Marwān ʿAbd al-Malik ibn Muḥammad ibn Marwān ibn Zuhr), Andalusian physician 1.5; 13.61.4 nos. 6, 7; 13.62; 13.63.3; 13.66.1; 13.76; 13.77; 13.80.2
Ibn Zuhr, Abū Muḥammad ibn al-Ḥafīd
Abī Bakr Muḥammad ibn Abī Marwān ʿAbd al-Malik, Andalusian physician 13.64
Ibn Zuhr, al-Ḥafīd Abū Bakr Muḥammad ibn Abī Marwān ibn Abī l-ʿAlāʾ, Andalusian physician and poet 13.62.2.3; 13.62.4
nos. 4, 7; 13.63; 13.68.2; 13.78
Ibn Zurʿah, Abū ʿAlī ʿĪsā ibn Isḥāq ibn Zurʿah,
Christian philosopher and translator (331–398/943–1008) 10.22.3; 10􏲆23; 14.25.9 no. 25
Ibrāhīm (Abraham, al-Khalīl), Hebrew Patri-
arch, Father of Muslims in Islam 15.31.2; 15.31.3
Ibrāhīm, pupil of Jūrjis ibn Jibrīl and per- sonal physician to al-Manṣūr 8.1.1; 8.1.2
Ibrāhīm ibn al-ʿAbbās ibn Ṭūmār al-Hāshimī,
a source used by ⅠAU 8.32.2; 8.32.3 Ibrāhīm ibn ʿAbd Allāh, 2nd/8th-c. Alid rebel 8.18.2
Ibrāhīm ibn ʿAbd Allāh, Christian translator 4.8.1
Ibrāhīm ibn Abī Bakr ibn ʿAlī al-Iṣfahānī,
pupil of Fakhr al-Dīn Rāzī 11.19.6.1 Ibrāhīm ibn ʿAdī (probably brother of Yaḥyā
ibn ʿAdī), disciple of al-Fārābī 15.1.5 no. 72
Ibrāhīm I ibn al-Aghlab, first Emir of the
Aghlabids in Ifrīqiyah (nd􏲉. 183–196/799– 812) 13.1.3
Ibrāhīm ibn Aḥmad al-Marwāzī, teacher
of Abū Bishr Mattā ibn Yūnus (d. 339– 341/951) 15.1.2; 15.1.3
Ibrāhīm ibn ʿAlī, physician of Aḥmad ibn
Ṭūlūn 8.26.9
Ibrāhīm ibn ʿAlī ibn al-Mahdī, grandson of
al-Mahdī 8.8, 8.9
Ibrāhīm ibn ʿAlī al-Ḥuṣrī, 10th c. litt􏲰rateur
from Qayrawān, 8.4.5
Ibrāhīm ibn Ayyūb al-Abrash, physician
under al-Mutawakkil and al-Muʿtazz 8.23
Ibrāhīm ibn Bābā al-Daylamī, contemporary of Ibn Sīnā 11.13.3.15
Ibrāhīm ibn Baks/Bakūs/Bakūsh/Bakkūsh al-ʿUshārī/al-ʿAshshārī(?), Abū Isḥāq, 4th/10th-c. Christian physician and trans- lator active in Baghdad 4.7n; 8.29.8; 9.37; 9.38; 10.23.2; 10.42; 11.8.6 no. 13 Ibrāhīm ibn Bunān, brother of the physician
Salmawayh ibn Bunān 8.20.1; 8.0.9 Ibrāhīm ibn al-Buḥturī, off􏲊cial of al-Muʿtaṣim 8.20.11
Ibrāhīm ibn Fazārūn, personal physician of
Ghassān ibn ʿAbbād 8.21
Ibrāhīm ibn Hilāl al-Ṣābiʾ `see` Abū Isḥāq
Ibrāhīm ibn Hilāl al-Ṣābiʾ
Ibrāhīm ibn ʿĪsā, Baghdadi physician and
companion of Yūḥannā ibn Māsawayh 14.2
Ibrāhīm ibn ʿĪsā ibn al-Manṣūr, known as Ibn Nazīhah, grandson of al-Manṣūr 8.21.2
Ibrāhīm ibn Jamīl, off􏲊cial during the reign of al-Nāṣir li-Dīn Allāh 10.77.3
Ibrāhīm ibn Khalaf, Samaritan physician, student of Raḍī al-Dīn al-Raḥbī 15.36.1.1
Ibrāhīm ibn al-Mahdī, Abū Isḥāq, brother of Hārūn al-Rashīd and brie􏲪􏲤y caliph in 202–203/817–818 5.1.16; 8.3.5; 8.3.6n; 8.3.11; 8.3.12; 8.3.14; 8.3.17; 8.3.18; 8.3.19; 8.4.5; 8.8.3; 8.8.4; 8.8.5; 8.8.6; 8.9; 8.13.2; 8.20.4; 8.20.5; 8.26.8n; 8.27.2; 8.27.3
Ibrāhīm ibn Muḥammad `see` Ibn al- Mudabbir
Ibrāhīm ibn Muḥammad ibn Baṭḥā, 4th/10th- c. off􏲊cial 10.4.7
Ibrāhīm ibn Muḥammad ibn Mūsā, ‘the Sec-
{424}
retary’ (a􏱌]􏲡􏱎phb), 3rd/9th-c. patron of
Greek-to-Arabic translators 9.47 Ibrāhīm ibn Mūsā ibn Maymūn, son of Mūsā
ibn Maymūn (Maimonides) 14.39.2n; 14.40
Ibrāhīm ibn al-Qāsim, probably biographer of al-Ḥajjāj ibn Yūsuf 7.9.4
Ibrāhīm ibn al-Raʾīs Mūsā `see` Ibrāhīm ibn Mūsā ibn Maymūn
Ibrāhīm ibn Ṣāliḥ ibn ʿAlī, cousin of caliphs al-Saffāḥ and al-Manṣūr 8.3.22n; 12.6
Ibrāhīm ibn al-Ṣalt, Christian translator 9.27; 9.28; 14.25.2n
Ibrāhīm ibn Sinān, mathematician (d. 355/ 946) 14.22.4.2 no. 21
Ibrāhīm ibn Sinān ibn Thābit ibn Qurrah, Abū Isḥāq (d. 330/941) 10.6
Ibrāhīm ibn al-Sindī ibn Shāhak, prefect of police under Hārūn al-Rashīd 8.10.3n Ibrāhīm ibn ʿUthmān ibn Nahīk, prefect of
police under Hārūn al-Rashīd 5.1.16.2; 8.3.22
Ibrāhīm ibn Zayn al-Dīn, Director of the al- Nūrī hospital in Damascus around the year 1045/1635–1636 15.50.4n
Ibrāhīm ibn Zahrūn `see` Abū Isḥāq Ibrāhīm ibn Zahrūn
Ibrāhīm al-Jawāliqī (active beginning 8th/14th c.), copyist of 􏳁􏳂 Sb AⅠⅠ.6n
al-Ibshīhī (d. ca. 850/1446), anthologist AⅠⅠ.2.1
Idrīs, Qurʾanic figure identified with Enoch and Hermes 2.1.3; 2.1.4; 2.1.5; 10.3.1
Idrīs ibn ʿAbd Allāh Ibn al-Yamān al- Andalusī, poet (d. 470/1077–1078) 10.51.5n
Ifrāʾīm ibn al-Zaffān, Jewish physician in
Egypt, student of Ibn Riḍwan 14.25.9 no. 25; 14.26; 14.27.1; 14.27.2
Iftikhār al-Dīn (Iftikhār al-Dīn Abū Hāshim ʿAbd al-Muṭṭalib ibn al-Faḍl al-Hāshimī), leader of the Ḥanafī kacggab in Aleppo and shaykh of the statesman Ibn al-ʿAdīm 15.18.1.3
al-Ikhshīd ibn Ṭughj `see` Muḥammad ibn
Ṭughj
Ikhwān al-Ṣafāʾ (the Brethren of Purity), 4th/10th-c. secret society of Ismāʿīlī philo- sophers 4.1.8.1n; 4.5.4n; 13.9
al-Īlāqī, Muḥammad ibn Yūsuf `or` Sharaf al- Zamān Muḥammad ibn ʿAlī al-Īlāqī of Bākharz in Persia, student of Ibn Sīnā 11.14; 15.30
Ilghāzī ibn Artuq, Najm al-Dīn, Artuqid ruler
(nd􏲉. 507–516/1115–1122) 10.75.1 Iliyyāʾ al-Qass, 5th/11th-c. Christian priest 10.59.1; 10.59.2 no. 5
ʿImād al-Dīn Abū Bakr ibn Qarā Arslān ibn
Dāwūd ibn Artuq, 12th-c. Artuqid ruler of
Kharpūt (Harpūt) 15.18.3 no. 2
ʿImād al-Dīn al-Dunaysirī, physician and lit-
erary scholar 15.58
ʿImād al-Dīn al-Iṣfahānī `see` al-Kātib al-Iṣfahānī
ʿImād al-Dīn al-Salmāsī 15.22
ʿImrān (Amram), father of Moses in Ex. 6􏲆20
and the father of Maryam/Mary in Qurʾan 11.13.7.7
ʿImrān ibn Abī ʿAmr 13.16; 13.17
ʿImrān al-Isrāʾīlī, Awḥad al-Dīn ibn Ṣadaqah,
Jewish physician student of Raḍī al-Dīn al-Raḥbī (d. 637/1240) 15.23.4.1; 15.36.1.1; 15.42
ʿImrān the Short (al-Qaṣīr), transmitter 10.2.2.1
Imruʾ al-Qays, a Bedouin (not the homonym- ous poet) 10.69.3.2n; 15.25
Iqbāl al-Dawlah ʿAlī al-ʿĀmirī (nd􏲉. 436– 468/1044–1076), petty king of Denia 13.48
al-Irbilī, ʿIzz al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn Ḥasan [=
al-Ḥasan ibn Muḥammad] al-Ghanawī al-Ḍarīr, poet (d. 660/1262) 14.48; 15.21
ʿĪsā, expert in jurisprudence, brother of Majd al-Dīn Abū Bakr ibn al-Dāyah 14.49.2; 14.49.3
ʿĪsā, a boy, subject of an epigram 15.58.7 ʿĪsā, Jesus son of Mary 15.23.4.2(p); 15.58.7(p); `see` a􏱌ol al-Masīḥ
ʿĪsā ‘the Muslim’, early 3rd/9th-c. physician 8.15.1
ʿĪsā, known as Abū Quraysh, apothecary and
personal physician to al-Mahdī 8.2; 8.8
ʿĪsā ibn Abī Khālid, early 3rd/9th-c. physi- cian, a contemporary of Sahl al-Kawsaj 8.15.1
{425}{!}
ʿĪsā ibn ʿAlī, uncle of al-Manṣūr 8.3.10 ʿĪsā ibn ʿAlī, student of Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq,
physician to al-Muʿtamid ʿalā Allāh 8.3.10n; 8.34
ʿĪsā ibn ʿAlī ibn ʿĪsā ibn Dāwūd ibn al-Jarrāḥ, Abū l-Qāsim, poet (d. 391/1001) 10.22; 14.22.4.4n
ʿĪsā ibn al-Biṭrīq, Christian physician, brother
of Saʿīd ibn al-Biṭrīq 14.11; 14.12
ʿĪsā ibn Ḥakam al-Dimashqī, known as Masīḥ 7.6; 7.8; 8.3.10n; 8.3.22n; 8.15.1
ʿĪsā ibn Ibrāhīm ibn Nūḥ ibn Abī Nūḥ, scribe
of al-Fatḥ ibn Khāqān 8.26.9 ʿĪsā ibn Isḥāq ibn Zurʿah, Abū ʿAlī 10􏲆23; 14.25.9
ʿĪsā ibn Jaʿfar ibn al-Manṣūr, cousin of Hārūn
al-Rashīd 8.3.22; 8.8.5
ʿĪsā ibn Māhān, guard commander under al-Mahdī and Hārūn al-Rashīd 8.3
ʿĪsā ibn Māsarjīs (`or` Māsarjawayh), physician
and translator 9.9
ʿĪsā ibn Māssah al-Baṣrī, medical writer (d.
ca. 275/888) 8.3.8; 8.4.10; 8.8.1; 8.12.2; 8.20.2; 8.23.1; 8.25.2; 8.26.2; 8.28
ʿĪsā ibn Mūsā, known as al-Jurjānī, son of al-Hādī 8.10.3
ʿĪsā ibn Mūsā ibn Muḥammad, nephew of
al-Saffāḥ and al-Manṣūr 8.18.1
ʿĪsā ibn Qusṭanṭīn (known as Abū Mūsā),
late-antique physician 6.5.2
ʿĪsā ibn Ṣahārbukht, Christian physician, stu-
dent of Jūrjis ibn Jibrīl ibn Bukhtīshūʿ 8.29.22 no. 16; 8.37; 9.26
ʿĪsā ibn Shahlā, student of Jūrjis ibn Jibrīl, personal physician to al-Manṣūr 8.1.1; 8.1.2
ʿĪsā ibn Usayd al-Naṣrānī, Abū Mūsā, student
of Thābit ibn Qurrah 10.3.12; 10.3.14 nos. 27, 85
ʿĪsā ibn Yaḥyā ibn Ibrāhīm, pupil of Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq 5.1.37 no. 115; 8.35; 9.5
ʿĪsā ibn Yūnus ‘the secretary and accountant’ (a􏱌]􏲡􏱎phb a􏱌]􏲛􏱎ohb), patron of translators 9.44
ʿĪsā the physician of al-Qāhir bi-Allāh, 10.26
ʿĪsā al-Raqqī `see` al-Raqqī al-Ti􏲪􏲤īsī
al-Iṣfahānī, Abū l-Faraj `see` Abū l-Faraj ʿAlī ibn
al-Ḥusayn
Isḥāq ibn ʿAlī, brother of Abū ʿAlī al-Qiyānī 8.14
Isḥāq ibn ʿAlī al-Ruhāwī, 3rd/9th-c. physician, author of Acab a􏱌]`ṭabīb` 8.3.8; 8.4.10; 8.8.1; 8.12.1; 8.12.2; 8.20.2; 8.23.1; 8.25.2; 8.26.2; 8.28n; 10.57
Isḥāq ibn Ḥunayn, translator of Greek philo-
sophy, author of Ta􏱏n􏲞􏲡g a􏱌]a􏲝hbb􏱎􏱏 (d.
ca. 298/910–911) 1.1n; 4.1.10.4n; 4.1.10.5n; 4.1.11.1n; 4.4.3; 4.5.2; 4.5.4n; 4.6.3.5; 5.1.3–4 (Galen’s dates); 5.1.12.1 (defect- ive chronology); 8.20.3; 8.29.8; 8.29.22n; 8.30; 8.31n; 9.3; 9.4; 9.44n; 10.24 no. 2
Isḥāq ibn Ibrāhīm, secretary to Ibn Ṭūlūn 14.4.1
Isḥāq ibn Ibrāhīm al-Mawṣilī, musician (d. 235/850) 15.40n
Isḥāq ibn Ibrāhīm ibn Muḥammad ibn Ismāʿīl, known as Bayḍ al-baghl, associ- ate of Yūsuf ibn Ibrāhīm (Ibn al-Dāyah) 8.26.5
Isḥāq ibn Ibrāhīm ibn Nasṭās (Abū Yaʿqūb
Isḥāq ibn Ibrāhīm ibn Nasṭās ibn Jurayj), Christian physician in service of al-Ḥākim 14.7; 14.16
Isḥāq ibn ʿImrān, physician at the court of
Ziyādat Allāh ibn al-Aghlab 13.1; 13.2.1; 14.4.1n
Isḥāq ibn al-Khaṣīy, friend of Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq 8.29.2; 8.29.3
Isḥāq ibn Mūsā, physician (d. 363/973) and son of Mūsā ibn al-ʿĀzār
Isḥāq ibn Mūsā, Abbasid prince, son of the caliph al-Hādī and his favourite concu- bine, Amat al-ʿAzīz 8.10.3
Isḥāq ibn Qasṭār, Andalusian physician 13.48
Isḥāq ibn al-Ṣabbāḥ, governor of Kufa under al-Mahdī and al-Rashīd, and father of al- Kindī 10.1.2
Isḥāq ibn Shahrām, ambassador to Basil ⅠⅠ (nd􏲉. 976–1025) 8.29.6
Isḥāq ibn Shalīṭā, physician of al-Muṭīʿ li- Allāh 10.28
Isḥāq ibn Sulaymān ibn ʿAlī al-Hāshimī, gov- ernor under Hārūn al-Rashīd and al-Amīn 12.2 no. 6n; 12.5
Isḥāq ibn Sulaymān al-Isrāʾīlī, medical writer
{426}{!}
(d. 320/932 `or` 344/955) 13.2; 13.3.1; 15.40.9 nos. 54, 55, 56
Isḥāq ibn Yūnus, student of Ibn al-Samḥ 14.22.5.2 no. 91; 14.24
Isḥāq al-Ṭabīb, physician in Cordova (active 287/900) 13.20
Isidore of Seville, encyclopaedist author of Epukl􏱌l􏲉hdo (d. 636) 5.1.15
al-Iskāfī `see` Abū Thughrah
al-Iskandar al-Afrūdīsī `see` Alexander of Aph-
rodisias
Ismāʿīl ibn Abī Sahl ibn Nawbakht, son of
Abū Sahl ibn Nawbakht 8.9
Ismāʿīl ibn Bulbul, Abū l-Ṣaqr, vizier of al- Muʿtamid (d. 278/892) 8.26.16; 10.3.6; 10.3.14 no. 113
Ismāʿīl ibn Jaʿfar, brother of al-Muʿtazz 8.23.1
Ismāʿīl ibn Mūsā, physician son of Mūsā ibn
al-ʿĀzār al-Israʾīlī 10.9; 14.9 Ismāʿīl ibn Mūsā, son of al-Hādī 8.8.4; 8.10.3
Ismāʿīl ibn al-Ṣāliḥ ibn al-Bannāʾ al-Qifṭī, jur-
ist 15.23.2.1
Ismāʿīl al-Zāhid (the Ascetic), Ḥanafī scholar
of Bukhara (d. 402/1012) 11.13.2.3 Ismāʿīl al-Ẓāfir ibn Dhī l-Nūn, emir of the
􏲝􏱎􏱏heag of Toledo 13.38.1; 13.38.2 Isrāʾīl the bishop (unidentified) 15.1.2 Isrāʾīl ibn Sahl, early 3rd/9th-c. physician 8.17
Isrāʾīl ibn Zakariyyā ibn al-Ṭayfūrī, Christian personal physician of al-Mutawakkil 8.12; 8.26.12; 9.49
Iṣṭifan ibn Basīl, translator (d. ca. 298/910) 4.1.11.1n; 8.29.9; 9.19; 13.36.2.1
Ītākh (`or` Aytākh), Turkish general 8.20.5n ʿIzz al-Dawlah, brother of Muʾayyid al-Dīn
Ibn al-Ṣūfī 15.8.6
ʿIzz al-Dawlah Bakhtiyār, Būyid Emir (d. 366– 367/977) 10.8.2; 10.29; 10.30
ʿIzz al-Dīn Abū l-Qāsim al-Khiḍr ibn Abī l-
Ghālib Naṣr al-Azdī al-Ḥimṣī 10.75.4 no. 1
ʿIzz al-Dīn Farrukh-Shāh (`or` ʿIzz al-Dīn al-Muʿaẓẓamī `or` ʿIzz al-Dīn Aybak al- Muʿaẓẓamī), Ayyubid governor of Ṣarkhad 15.23.3; 15.37.4; 15.46.3; 15.48; 15.49.1; 15.51.2
ʿIzz al-Dīn Farrukh Shāh ibn Shāhān Shāh ibn Ayyūb, Ayyubid governor of Baalbek 15.51.2
ʿIzz al-Dīn al-Ḥasan ibn Muḥammad ibn
Aḥmad al-Ghanawī al-Rāfiḍī al-Irbilī al- Ḍarīr (d. 660/1262), poet, philosopher, teacher of Ibn al-Quff 14.48.3; 15.21; 15.60.1
ʿIzz al-Dīn ibn al-Suwaydī `see` Ibn al-al-Suwaydī
al-Jabbān `see` Abū Manṣūr al-Jabbān
Jabhar, otherwise unknown Indian physician
and scholar 12.2
Jābir ibn Ḥayyān, Abū Mūsā ibn ʿAbd Allāh
al-Kūfī (Geber), alchemist (d. ca. 200/810) 1.2n; 11.5.25 no. 176; 15.40.3
Jābir ibn Manṣūr `see` al-Sukkarī, Jābir ibn Manṣūr
Jabrāʾīl (Archangel) `see` Gabriel
Jacob `see` Yaʿqūb
Jacob Baradaeus, 6th-c. bishop of Edessa 6.1.2
Jacobites (al-Yaʿqūbiyyah) 6.1.2; 6.1.3; 10.22.1.2, 14.1; 15.3.1
Jaʿdah bint al-Ashʿath ibn Qays, conspirator
under Muʿāwiyah 7.5.6
Jaʿfar ibn ʿAbd al-Raḥmān al-Ṣaqlabī, cham-
berlain of al-Ḥakam ⅠⅠ 13.30 Jaʿfar ibn Kilāb, Arab tribe 15.8.4(p); 15.8.5(p); 15.8.6(p)
Jaʿfar ibn Muḥammad, last Imam recog-
nized by both Twelver and Ismaili Shi’is
(d. 148/765) 15.51.7
Jaʿfar ibn Mūsā, son of al-Hādī 8.10.3; 8.15.1n Jaʿfar ibn Yaḥyā ibn Khālid ibn Barmak, vizier
and sponsor of Indian science (d. 187/803) 8.3.2; 8.3.16; 8.3.22; 8.10.3n; 8.15.1n; 8.20.4n; 12.6
Jaʿfar, al-Khalīfah unidentified 11.13.7.9 al-Jāḥiẓ, Abū ʿUthmān ʿAmr ibn Baḥr,
author of works of acab, theology, etc. (d. 255/868–869) 4.5.1n; 7.2.3n; 7.6n; 8.26.16; 11.5.25 nos. 40, 41; 11.16 no. 1.30; 13.63.8.2n; 15.40.9 no. 50; AⅠⅠ.2.2
Jaḥẓah, Aḥmad ibn Jaʿfar al-Barmakī, courtier, man of letters, poet (d. 324/936) 8.30.5n; 10.1.13
{427}{!}
al-Jahshiyārī, Abū ʿAbd Allāh, 4th/10th-c. man of letters, historian 8.3.16n Jalāl al-Dīn Abū l-Fatḥ Muḥammad ibn
Nubātah, al-Ṣāḥib, unidentified high off􏲊-
cial 15.46.3.9
Jalāl al-Dīn al-Baghdādī, al-Qāḍī, pupil of
Kamāl al-Dīn ibn Yūnus 10.83.3
Jalāl al-Dīn ibn Ṣadaqah, al-Ḥasan ibn ʿAlī, vizier under al-Mustarshid 10.68.2.5n
Jalāl al-Dīn Khwārazmshāh, (nd􏲉. 617– 628/1220–1231) last ruler of the Khwā- razm-shāhs 11.13
Jālīnūs `see` Galen
al-Jamāl (Jamāl al-Dīn), unidentified subject
of a love epigram by al-Dunaysirī 15.58.4 Jamāl al-Dawlah Abū l-Ghanāʾim 15.8.5 Jamāl al-Dīn (Ibn al-Jammālah), copyist
serving Ibn al-Muṭrān 15.23.4; 15.23.4.1 Jamāl al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Laṭīf, notable from
Baghdad 15.40.3
Jamāl al-Dīn al-Ḥarastānī, judge 15.53; 15.50.6
Jamāl al-Dīn ibn Abī l-Ḥawāfir `see` Ibn Abī
l-Ḥawāfir
Jamāl al-Dīn Muḥammad al-Āmidī, son of
Sayf al-Dīn Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Abī ʿAlī
al-Āmidī 15.22
Jamāl al-Dīn al-Naqqāsh al-Siʿirdī `see` al-Siʿirdī, Jamāl al-Dīn al-Naqqāsh
Jamāl al-Dīn ʿUthmān (d. 658/1258)), physi-
cian brother of Sharaf al-Dīn ibn al-Raḥbī 15.37.3
Jamāl al-Dīn ʿUthmān ibn Aḥmad, grand- son of physician Jamāl al-Dīn ibn Abī l-Ḥawāfir 14.44.1n
Jamāl al-Dīn Yaḥyā ibn Maṭrūḥ `see` Ibn Maṭrūḥ
Jamīl ibn Maʿmar, poet-lover (d. 82/701) 14.32.4(p)
Janān, slave-girl loved by Abū Nuwās 8.19.3 al-Jānis (Jābis, Ḥābis?), unidentified author
of a book on leadership (?) 14.25.9 no. 97
al-Jannābī al-Qarmaṭī, Abū Ṭāhir Sulaymān, leader of Qarmaṭians (d. 332/943–944) 11.13 Jarak `see` Caraka
Jārī, otherwise unknown Indian physician and scholar 12.2
Jarīr al-Ṭabīb 11.5.25 no. 75
al-Jarīrī, Muʿāfā ibn Zakariyyā, litt􏲰rateur
(d. 390/1000) 7.1.6n
Jarjah ibn Zakariyyā, 3rd/9th-c. Nubian chief-
tain 8.26.10
al-Jawād, Abū Jaʿfar Muḥammad ibn ʿAlī
Jamāl al-Dīn al-Iṣfahānī (d. 574/1178), viz-
ier under the Zangids 10/.81.6 no. 2 Jawād al-Ṭabīb al-Naṣrānī (the Christian
Physician) (3rd/9th c.) 13.13; 13.18 al-Jawālīqī, Abū Manṣūr Mawhūb ibn Aḥmad
ibn Muḥammad al-Khiḍr (d. 539/1144),
lexicographer and traditionalist 15.46.2 Jawdar (`or` Jawdhar), otherwise unrecorded
Indian scholar 12.4
al-Jawharī, Abū Naṣr Ismāʿīl ibn Ḥammād
(d. 393/1002 `or` 398/1007), 10th-c. lexico-
grapher 7.1.1; 7.2.4n; 14.32.2; 15.50.5 al-Jawharī, al-ʿAbbās ibn Saʿīd, astronomer
under al-Maʾmūn 12.3 no. 1
Jawzah, servant of Khwand Khātūn, wife of
Muwaffaq al-Dīn ibn al-Muṭrān 15.23.2 al-Jazūlī, Abū Mūsā ibn ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz (d.
between 606/1209 and 616/1219), gram-
marian 13.64.2.1 Jesus `see` ʿĪsā `and` al-Masīḥ
Jews 4.6.7.1; 5.1.7; 5.1.8.1; 5.1.8.2; 5.1.14; 7.2.1; 8.3.10; 8.5.3; 8.5.6 no. 7; 8.18.1; 8.19; 10.4.4.2; 10.23.3; 10.49; 10.64.2; 10.66.1; 10.66.6; 10.66.7; 10.68.2.1n, 10.68.2.2; 11.13.7.7n; 11.21; 11.21 no. 4; 13.1.2; 13.2.1n; 13.26.2.3n; 13.46; 13.47; 13.48; 13.49; 13.50; 13.57; 13.66.3; 14.18; 14.22.3.2; 14.23.3n; 14.26.1; 14.27.1; 14.27.2; 14.32.4; 14.33.1; 14.34.1; 14.34.2; 14.36.3; 14.38.1; 14.39.1; 14.39.4 no. 6; 14.41;14.42; 14.44.3; 15.8.11; 15.15; 15.16; 15.40.3; 15.40.9
 nos. 93, 94; 15.41
Jibrīl (Archangel) `see` Gabriel
Jibrīl ‘the oculist’, oculist to al-Maʾmūn 8.24 Jibrīl ibn Bukhtīshūʿ, Christian physician
serving Hārūn al-Rashīd 5.1.16; 5.1.37. no. 115; 8.3; 9.35; 9.49; 10.27; 11.5.6; 12.6
Jibrīl ibn ʿUbayd Allāh ibn Bukhtīshūʿ 8.5 al-Jīlī, Rafīʿ al-Dīn ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz `see` Rafīʿ al-Dīn al-Jīlī
al-Jilyānī, Ḥakīm al-Zamān Abū l-Faḍl ʿAbd
al-Munʿim ibn ʿUmar ibn ʿAbd Allāh ibn Ḥassān al-Ghassānī al-Andalusī,
{428}{!}
physician, ophthalmologist, and poet
(d. 600/1203–1204) 15.11; AⅠⅠ13; AⅠⅠ.14 Jinn (jinnees, demons) 10.38.3; 10.67.4.2(p); 10.69.3.12(p); 10.69.3.13n; 11.13.7.8(p); 11.19.6.2n; 15.15 no. 57; 15.10(p); 15.56.1n; 15.57.2(p)
Jirāb al-Dawlah, musician and wit under al- Muqtadir 8.26.16
Jirjis, 5th/11th-c. Christian physician in Cairo 14.27.3
Jirjis al-Faylasūf, unidentified lampoonist 14.27
Job of Edessa (Iyob of Edessa) `see` Ayyūb al- Ruhāwī al-Abrash
Joseph ibn Shimʿon, student of Maimonides 14.39.2n
John, mid 5th-c. Patriarch of Antioch 6.1.3
John the Baptist 5.1.8.1
John the Grammarian/Yaḥyā al-Naḥwī,
con􏲪􏲤ation of John Philoponus (ca. 490– 575) and one or more unidentified late-antique medical writers, alleged con- temporary of ʿAmr ibn al-ʿĀṣ 2.1.5; 3.2; 4.1.11.1n; 4.1.11.3; 5.1.3; 5.1.4; 5.1.12.1; 6.1.1; 6.1.2; 6.1.3; 6.2; 14.22.4.3 no. 11; 15.1.5 no. 43
John Philoponus, Neoplatonist Christian philosopher (ca. 490–575) 6.1.1n; 6.1.2n; 6.1.3 (imaginary biography) Joseph `see` Yūsuf
Joseph ben Judah, `see` Yūsuf al-Isrāʾīlī Jubal son of Lamech son of Methuselah
(Yūfāl ibn Lāmakh ibn Matūshālakh) 1.5
al-Jubbāʾī `see` Abū ʿAlī al-Jubbāʾī
Julian the Apostate 14.25.2n
Julius Gaius Caesar, Roman general and dic-
tator 5.1.8.1
al-Jumaḥī `see` Muḥammad ibn Sallām al-Jumaḥī
al-Junayd ibn Muḥammad, celebrated Sufi
(d. 298/910) 15.51.7; 15.51.10.1(p)
Jurayj ibn al-Ṭabbākh, unidentified physician 14.4.4
Jurhum, pre-Islamic Arabian people 14.32.4(p)
al-Jurjānī, Abū l-ʿAbbās Aḥmad ibn Muḥam-
mad (d. 482/1089), author of a􏱌]Kh􏱋􏱎u􏱎p 10.3.8
Jūrjis ibn Jibrīl, first of the Christian Bukht- īshūʿ family of physicians 5.1.16.5; 8.1; 9.1; 9.26n
Jūrjis ibn Mīkhāʾīl 8.3.16; 8.15.1; 8.15.2 al-Juwaynī, Abū ʿAlī al-Ḥasan ibn ʿAlī ibn
Ibrāhīm al-Juwaynī al-Kātib, known as Ibn al-Luʿaybah, poet (d. in Cairo 586/1190) 14.31, 14.31.8
al-Jūzjānī `see` Abū ʿUbayd al-Jūzjānī
Kaʿb ibn Zuhayr, 1st/7th-c. poet 14.31.8n; 15.40.9 no. 9
Kadbānuwayh (Persian for Lady of the House), patron of Ibn Sīnā 11.13.3.3
Kāfūr al-Ikhshīdī, Abū-l-Misk Kāfūr, Ikh- shīdid commander 14.6n; 14.8 al-Kalbī, Hishām, historian 7.1.6n
al-Kaldāniyyūn `see` Chaldaeans
Kamāl al-Dīn Abū l-Qāsim ibn Abī Turāb al-Kātib al-Baghdādī 11.5.4
Kamāl al-Dīn al-Ḥimṣī, pupil of Raḍī al-Dīn
al-Raḥbī 15.39
Kamāl al-Dīn ibn Yūnus, Abū ʿImrān (`or` Abū
l-Fatḥ) Kamāl al-Dīn Mūsā ibn Yūnus ibn Muḥammad al-Mawṣilī, mathematician and jurist (551–639/1156–1242) 10.83; 15.40.3
Kamāl al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn Mīkāʾīl, dedic-
atee of Fakhr al-Dīn al-Rāzī 11.19.7 no. 37 al-Kanbanārī `see` Abū l-ʿAbbās al-Kanbanārī Kankah (`or` Kanakah) al-Hindī, Indian
astrologer-astronomer (active ca. 775– 800) 12.1
Ka􏳃kāyana, Indian physician 12.1n Karaites, Jewish sect 14.33.1; 14.41; 14.43.1 Kasdaeans (al-Kasdāniyyūn) 1.5 `see` a􏱌ol
Chaldaeans
al-Kashkarī (or al-Kaskarī), Yaʿqūb, 4th/10th-
c. physician in Baghdad 11.5.6n al-Kātib al-Iṣfahānī, ʿImād al-Dīn, state sec-
retary of Nūr al-Dīn and Saladin, antholo-
gist (d. 597/1201) 15.13; 15.40
Kawkīn, relation of ʿAḍud al-Dawlah 8.5.2 Kay Bahman, mythical Kayanian king 4.1.5
Kaykāʾūs ibn Kaykhusraw, al-Malik al-Ghālib,
Seljuqid ruler of al-Rūm (Anatolia) (nd􏲉. 608–618/1211–1220) 10.82
Kayqubādh ibn Kaykhusraw ibn Qilij Arslān,
{429}
ruler of Erzerum in Anatolia (reg. 588– 593/1192–1197) 15.40.5
Kaysān ibn ʿUthmān ibn Kaysān, 10th-c.
physician from Egypt and brother of the
physician Sahlān 14.15
al-Kayyāl, Aḥmad ibn Zakariyyā (active 3rd/9th c.), Ismaili missionary 11.5.25 .no. 136
al-Khabūshānī, Najm al-Dīn, theologian, sup- porter of Saladin 14.36.2; 14.36.3
Khafīf al-Samarqandī, servant of al-Muʿtaḍid 10.10.5
Khalaf ibn ʿAbbās al-Zahrāwī, Andalusian physician 13.56
Khalaf ibn Khalīfah, poet (possibly Khalaf ibn Khalīfah ibn Ṣāʿid, d. 181/797–780) 15.37.2n
Khalaf al-Ṭūlūnī, Abū ʿAlī, Baghdadi physi-
cian (active 302/914) 14.5
Khālid, clan of the Jaʿfar ibn Kilāb 15.8.4(p) Khālid ibn ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz `see` Abū ʿUthmān Khālid ibn al-Muhājir ibn Khālid ibn al-Walīd, nobleman under Muʿāwiyah 7.5.3; 7.5.4; 7.5.5
Khālid ibn Ṣafwān ibn al-Ahtam al-Tamīmī, transmitter, noted for his eloquence
(d. 135/752) 8.26.13
Khālid ibn Shahriyār, Khorasanian prince (active 141/758–759) 8.10.3
Khālid ibn al-Walīd, commander (d. 21/642) 7.5.2n
Khālid ibn Yazīd `see` Ibn Rūmān al-Naṣrānī al-Khālidiyyān, the brothers Abū Bakr al-Khālidī and Abū ʿUthmān al-Khālidī known as al-Khālidiyyān, poets and men of letters (d. 380/990 and ca. 390/100) 8.26.15 al-Khalīl `see` Ibrāhīm
al-Khalīl ibn Aḥmad, Abū ʿAbd al-Raḥmān al-Farāhīdī al-Azdī, lexicographer, gram- marian (d. 175/791) 8.29.1
al-Khansāʾ, poetess (d. after 24/644) 10.51.3(p); 15.17(p)
al-Khāqānī, Abū l-Qāsim ʿAbd Allāh ibn Muḥammad (d. 314/926–927), vizier under al-Muqtadir 10.5.2
Kharijites 10.2.3.1
Kharshā, slave-girl of Hārūn al-Rashīd 8.29.2
Khaṣīb al-Naṣrānī, 2nd/8th-c. Christian phys- ician 8.7
al-Khaṣībī, Abū l-ʿAbbās Aḥmad ibn ʿUbayd Allāh ibn Aḥmad ibn al-Khaṣīb (d. 328/940), vizier 10.5.3
al-Khaṭīb al-Baghdādī, Aḥmad ibn ʿAlī ibn Thābit (d. 463/1071), author of T􏱎n􏲞􏲡g Ba􏲉gc􏱎c 8.26.17; 8.30.5n
al-Khaṭīb al-Dawlaʿī, preacher and student of law (d. 598/1202) 15.40.3
al-Khaṭīb al-Tibrīzī `see` al-Tibrīzī al-Khaṭṭābī, Ḥamd ibn Muḥammad, tradi-
tionist (d. ca. 388/998) 15.40.3; 15.40.9 no. 1
al-Khawātīmī `see` Shams al-Dīn al-Kutubī Khayrūn ibn Rābiṭah, translator 9.22 Khayyām, ʿUmar (Omar), Persian poet 11.19n
al-Khayzurān bint ʿAṭāʾ al-Jurashiyyah, wife of
al-Mahdī 8.2n; 8.8; 8.10.2
al-Khāzinī, 6th/12th-c. astronomer 4.6.13.3n Khindif, branch of North Arabian tribes 15.8.6(p)
Khudhāwayh ibn Sahl, son of Sahl al-Kawsaj 8.15.2
Khunad Khātūn `or` Khwand Khātūn, wife of
Saladin 15.23.2
al-Khūnajī, Afḍal al-Dīn Abū l-Faḍāʾil
Muḥammad ibn Nāmawar, physician,
teacher or ⅠAU (d. 646/1248) 14.48 al-Khuraymī, Abu Yaʿqūb Isḥāq ibn Ḥassān,
poet (d. 214/829) 10.5n
Khusraw `see` Kisrā
Khusrawshāh ibn Mubādir, 4th/10th-c. king
of Daylamites 8.5.3; 8.5.6 no. 4 al-Khusrawshāhī `see` Shams al-Dīn al-Khusrawshāhī
al-Khuwayyī `see` Shams al-Dīn al-Khuwayyī Khwārazmshāh Abū l-ʿAbbās Maʾmūn ibn
Maʾmūn (nd􏲍pd Muḥammad), ruler of
Khwārazm (d. 387/997) 11.8.6 no. 10 Khwārazm Shāh, Muḥammad b. Tekish ʿAlāʾ
al-Dīn (ʿAlāʾ al-Dīn ʿAlī Khwārazm Shāh `or`
Muḥammad
Khwārazm Shāh) (nd􏲉. 596–617/1200–1220) 11.19.3; 11.19.4; 11.19.5; 11.19.6; 11.19.7
nos. 4, 45; 11.24
al-Khwārazmī `see` Jalāl al-Dīn Khwārazm
Shāh
{430}{!}
al-Khwārizmī, Muḥammad ibn Mūsā, 4th/10th-c. encyclopedist 4.6.4.1n; 13.5.1
Kinānah, Arab tribe 15.46.2
al-Kindī, Yaʿqūb ibn Isḥaq, philosopher
(ca. 185–252/801–866) 1.1; 4.4.2.2n; 4.5.4n; 10.1; 10.2.1; 10.3.14 no. 27; 11.3; 11.5.25 no. 31; 13.61.4 no. 8; 14.22.5.2 no. 85n; 15.1.3.2; AⅠⅠ.2.1; AⅠⅠ.2.2; AⅠⅠ.2.3; AⅠⅠ.2.4
al-Kindī al-Naḥwī, Tāj al-Dīn Abū l-Yumn Zayd ibn al-Ḥasan, grammarian and teacher of literary sciences (d. 613/1217) 15.23.1; 15.29; 15.39; 15.40.3; 15.48; 15.50; 15.51.2
al-Kirmānī, Abū l-Ḥakam ʿAmr ibn ʿAbd al-Raḥmān ibn Aḥmad ibn ʿAlī 13.5.1; 13.9
al-Kīshī, author of a commentary on the Hip- pocratic `Aphorisms` 15.60.2n
Kisrā (Khusraw, Chosroes), generic name for pre-Islamic Persian kings 14.32.4(p); 15.11.2.1(p)
Kisrā Anūshirwān, Sasanid ruler (nd􏲉. 537– 579) 7.1.2; 7.1.3; 7.1.4; 7.1.6; 8.20.6 al-Kumayt ibn Maʿrūf al-Asadī (d. ca. 100/ 718), poet 8.29.15n
Kūmiyah, Berber tribe 13.81.1
Kunnah bint Kusayrah of Thumālah (Azd),
eponymous ancestress of the Banū Kun-
nah subtribe 7.1.6n
Kushājim, Abū l-Fatḥ Maḥmūd ibn al-Ḥusayn, poet and prose writer (d.
ca. 360/970) 13.3.3
Kutāmah, Berber tribe 13.2.2.2 Kuthayyir ibn ʿAbd al-Raḥmān, known as
Kuthayyir ʿAzzah, 1st/7th-c. poet 7.5.6; 15.8.5n

Labīd ibn Rabīʿah, pre-Islamic poet 10.51.3(p); 15.8.4(p); 15.31.1; 15.45.3(p); 15.46.2n
Laecanius Arius of Tarsus, 1st-c. A􏲬 pharma- cologist 4.1.11.2
Lajhad `see` Hermes
Lakhmids, pre-Islamic dynasty based at al-Ḥīrah 8.3.16n; 8.29.1n
Laqīṭ, traditionist (?Laqīṭ ibn Ṣabirah, one of
Muḥammad’s Companions) 7.3 Leon, pupil of Hippocrates 4.1.10.1
Luqmān, pre-Islamic sage 4.2; 15.17(p); 15.58.4n
Luʾluʾ (?Luʾluʾ al-ḥājib al-ʿĀdilī) 15.40.3 Lycus of Macedonia, 2nd-c. anatomist 4.1.10.2; 5.1.37 nos. 23, 29, 30
Maʿadd, legendary ancestor of the North Arabs 10.1.3; 15.47.2.1(p)
al-Maʿarrī, Abū l-ʿAlāʾ Aḥmad ibn ʿAbd Allāh ibn Sulaymān, Syrian poet and prose writer (d. 449/1057) 5.1.33; 11.19.7
no. 9n; 10.38.4; 10.51.3n; 11.19.7 no. 9n;
AⅠⅠ3.3
Macarius, physician of antiquity 3.6 Machaon, son of Asclepius 2.1.5n; 4.6.2.1 al-Madāʾinī, Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Muḥam-
mad, historian (d. 228/842–843) 7.5.2; 7.5.5n
Mādhava, Indian author of the Nhc􏱎􏱋 `or` Nhc] 􏱎􏱋a, also called M􏱎cgara􏱋hc􏱎􏱋a (active ca. A􏲬700) 12.2 no. 3n
Maʿdī Karib ibn Muʿāwiyah, pre-Islamic chieftain of Hadramaut 10.1.2
Magnus of Alexandria, late-antique physi- cian 5.2.1
Magnus of Emesa, physician of antiquity 4.1.10.2
al-Mahdī, third Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 158– 169/775–85) 8.2n; 8.3.11n; 8.8.1; 8.8.3; 8.8.4; 8.18.3; 8.25.8n; 12.6
Maḥmūd ibn Muḥammad Ghiyāth al-Dīn al-Ghūrī (nd􏲉. 602–609/1206–1212), Ghūrid
ruler 10.67.5 no. 2; 11.19.3; 11.19.6 Maḥmūd ibn Seb􏱮ktigin, Sultan of Ghaznah
(nd􏲉. 388–421/998–1030) 11.8.3n; 11.8.4 Maḥmūd ibn Zankī (`or` Zangī) `see` al-Malik
al-ʿĀdil Nūr al-Dīn Maḥmūd ibn Zankī Maimonides `see` Mūsā ibn Maymūn
al-Majd (Majd al-Dīn) ibn al-Ṣāḥib `see` Hibat
Allāh ibn ʿAlī Majd al-Dīn
Majd al-Dawlah, Rustam, Būyid emir of Rayy
and the Jibāl (nd􏲉. 387–420/997–1029) 11.13.3.3; 11.13.8 no. 11
Majd al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Raḥmān ibn Ibrāhīm, father of Badr al-Dīn ibn Qāḍī Baʿlabakk 15.52.1
Majd al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Wahhāb ibn Aḥmad ibn
Ṣaḥnūn al-Dimashqī 15.52.2n
Majd al-Dīn Abū Bakr ibn al-Dāyah, foster
{431}
brother of Nūr al-Dīn Maḥmūd ibn Zangī 14.49.2; 14.49.3
Majd al-Dīn al-Jīlī, scholar, teacher of Fakhr al-Dīn al-Rāzī 11.19.1; 11.19.7 no. 30 Majnūn Laylā, Qays ibn al-Mulawwaḥ, 1st/7th-c. poet 10.3
al-Majrīṭī, Abū l-Qāsim Maslamah ibn
Aḥmad, physician from Cordova
(d. 398/1007) 13.5; 13.7; 13.8; 13.10; 13.29.2; 13.38.1; 13.45
al-Majūsī `see` ʿAlī ibn al-ʿAbbās al-Majūsī Makḥūl, transmitter 10.2.2.2
al-Makīn Abū l-Qāsim ʿAlī ibn al-Ḥusayn `see`
al-Qāḍī al-Makīn Abū l-Qāsim ʿAlī ibn
al-Ḥusayn
Mākird the Daylamite, 4th/10th-c. off􏲊cial 10.5.3
Makkī ibn Abī Ṭālib al-Qayrawānī, Abū
Muḥammad, Qurʾanic scholar and dream interpreter (d. 437/1045–1046); `see` a􏱌ol ʿAlī ibn Abī Ṭālib al-Qayrawānī 1.7
al-Makkī, Aḥmad ibn Yaḥyā, poet (d. 248/ 862) 8.3.23n
al-Malik al-ʿĀdil Abū Bakr Muḥammad ibn Ayyūb, known as Sayf al-Dīn, brother and successor of Saladin (d. 615/1218) 11.19
no. 18; 13.86.2; 14.31.7; 14.32.5 no. 8; 14.38.1; 14.39.1; 14.43.2; 14.49.2–3; 14.50; 14.51.2; 14.54.3; 15.34; 15.36.1.3; 15.39; 15.40.5; 15.42; 15.45.2; 15.46.3; 15.46.4 no. 3; 15.47.1; 15.48; 15.49.2; 15.50; 15.51.3; 15.51.5; 15.51.6; 15.51.8
al-Malik al-ʿĀdil Khwārazm Shāh Abū l- ʿAbbās Maʾmūn ibn Maʾmūn = Maʾmūn ⅠⅠ ibn Maʾmūn Ⅰ, Abū l-ʿAbbās (nd􏲉. 399– 407/1009–1017) 11.12 no. 8
al-Malik al-ʿĀdil Nūr al-Dīn Maḥmūd ibn Zankī (`or` Zangī), ruler of Aleppo and Damascus, founder of al-Bīmāristān al- Nūrī (al-Nūrī hospital) 14.49.2n; 15.9; 15.12; 15.13; 15.15; 15.23.4.2; 15.24; 15.25; 15.33; 15.34; 15.35; 15.36.1; 15.37; 15.38; 15.39; 15.46.3; 15.50; 15.51; 15.52.1; 15.53
al-Malik al-ʿĀdil Sayf al-Dīn Abū Bakr ibn Ayyūb `see` al-Malik al-ʿĀdil Abū Bakr Muḥammad ibn Ayyūb
al-Malik al-Afḍal Nūr al-Dīn ʿAlī, Saladin’s eldest son 14.39.1; 14.39.4 no. 3; 15.28; 15.40.3
al-Malik al-Afḍal Shahanshāh ibn Amīr al- Juyūsh (d. 515/1121), Fatimid commander 13.58.2.1; 13.58.2.2; 13.58.4.4
al-Malik ʿAlāʾ al-Dīn Dāwūd ibn Bahrām (also
known as Dāwūd Shāh), governor of Erz-
injān (d. 624/1225) 15.40.5; 15.40.9 no. 96 al-Malik al-Amjad Majd al-Dīn Bahrām
Shāh ibn ʿIzz al-dīn Farrukh Shāh ibn Shāhinshāh ibn Ayyūb, Ayyubid ruler (d. 628/1230) 15.20 no. 1; 15.48; 15.49.1; 15.51.2; 15.51.11 nos. 1, 6
al-Malik al-Ankūr, probably = (Malik) al-Inkitār (‘(King of) l’Angleterre’), name of
Richard Ⅰ 15.50.6
al-Malik al-Ashraf Abū al-Fatḥ Mūsā, son of
al-Malik al-ʿĀdil Abū Bakr ibn Ayyūb = al-Malik al-Ashraf Ⅰ Mūsā ibn al-ʿĀdil ⅠⅠ Abū Bakr Sayf al-Dīn, Abū l-Fatḥ Muẓaffar al-Dīn, of Diyarbakr, Ayyubid ruler (nd􏲉. 626–635/1229–1237) 15.11.2; 15.35; 15.36.1.1; 15.46.3; 15.47.1; 15.50.5; 15.51; 15.52.1; 15.53
al-Malik al-Ashraf Shāh Arman Mūsā, the son
of al-Malik al-ʿĀdil Abū Bakr ibn Ayyūb (?identical with al-Malik al-Ashraf Abū al-Fatḥ Mūsā) 15.46.4 no. 3; 15.52
al-Malik al-Ashraf, the son of al-Malik al- Manṣūr, the ruler of Homs 15.56.1 al-Malik al-Awḥad Najm al-Dīn Ayyūb, son
of al-Malik al-ʿĀdil Abū Bakr ibn Ayyūb, Ayyubid ruler of the city of Khilāṭ 15.46.3
al-Malik al-ʿAzīz, Fatimid caliph (nd􏲉. 365– 386/975–96) 14.54.3n
al-Malik al-ʿAzīz Uthmān, Ayyubid ruler of
Egypt, son of Saladin 14.37; 14.44.2; 15.22 no. 17; 15.40.3; 15.40.9 no. 23; 15.51.1
al-Malik Bahāʾ al-Dawlah ibn ʿAḍud al- Dawlah = Abū Naṣr Bahāʾ al-Dawlah Fīrūz b. Fanā Khusraw ʿAḍud al-Dawlah, Būyid prince (nd􏲉. 388–403/998–1012) 11.10
al-Malik al-Fāʾiz Ibrāhīm ibn al-Malik al-ʿĀdil Ⅰ, Ayyubid prince 15.29
al-Malik al-Ḥāfiẓ Nūr al-Dīn Arslān Shāh ibn Abī bakr ibn Ayyūb, Ayyubid governor 15.32
Mālik ibn al-Hārith al-Nakhaʿī, known as al-Ashtar, supporter of ʿAlī ibn Abī Ṭālib 7.5.6
{432}
Mālik ibn Wuhayb al-Ishbīlī, Abū ʿAbd Allāh, Sevillian polymath (d. 252/1130) 13.59
.2.2
al-Malik al-Jawād Muẓaffar al-Dīn Yūnus ibn
Shams al-Dīn Mamdūd ibn al-Malik al- ʿĀdil, Ayyubid ruler of Damascus 15.50.6; 15.52.1
al-Malik al-Kāmil ibn al-Malik al-ʿĀdil
(= al-Malik al-Kāmil I Nāṣir al-Dīn = al-Malik al-Kāmil I Muḥammad ibn al-ʿĀdil I Muḥammad `or` Aḥmad Sayf al-Dīn, Abū l-Maʿālī Nāṣir al-Dīn), Ayy- ubid ruler of Egypt (nd􏲉. 615–635/1218– 1238) 14.45; 14.47.2; 14.49.2; 15.35; 15.37; 15.50.3
al-Malik al-Kāmil Muḥammad ibn Abū Bakr
ibn Ayyūb (573–635/1177–1238), fourth Ayyubid sultan in Egypt 14.22.2n; 14.40.1; 14.44.2; 14.45; 14.49.2;14.51.2; 14.53; 14.54.3; 14.54.4; 14.54.4–6; 14.54.8; 14.54.9; 14.54.10; 14.54.11; 14.56.1; 14.57.1; 14.57.3; 14.58.3; 15.37.3; 15.40.9 no. 14; 15.49.2; 15.50; 15.51.4
al-Malik al-Manṣūr Nāṣir al-Dīn Abū l-Maʿālī Muḥammad ibn al-Malik al-Muẓaffar Taqī al-Dīn ʿUmar ibn Shāhinshāh ibn Ayyūb, Ayyubid ruler of Hama 15.22; 15.24; 15.46.3; 15.54
al-Malik al-Manṣūr ʿIzz al-Dīn Taqī al-Dīn
Abū Saʿīd Farrukh Shāh Dāwūd, Ayyubid ruler of Baalbek and Damascus 15.49.1; 15.51.2
al-Malik al-Manṣūr = al-Malik al-Mujāhid
Shīrkūh ⅠⅠ ibn al-Qāhir Muḥammad Nāsir al-Dīn, Ṣalāḥ al-Dīn, lord of Homs (nd􏲉. 581–637/1186–1240) 15.31.1; 15.31 no. 22
al-Malik al-Masʿūd, Lord of Āmid 15.56.1 al-Malik al-Masʿūd Aqsīs ibn al-Malik al-Kāmil = al-Masʿūd Yusuf, son of al-Malik
al-Kāmil, emir of Yemen 14.57.1 al-Malik al-Muʾayyad Najm al-Dīn Masʿūd,
son of al-Malik al-Nāṣir Ṣalāḥ al-Dīn Yūsuf
ibn Ayyūb 15.51.11 no. 3
al-Malik al-Muʿaẓẓam Sharaf al-Dīn ʿĪsā ibn
al-Malik al-ʿĀdil Ⅰ, Ayyubid ruler of Dam- ascus (576–624/1180–1227). Ayyubid ruler of Damascus 14.50; 14.53; 14.56.1; 15.19; 15.22; 15.29; 15.36.1; 15.43.1; 15.43.3; 15.45.2; 15.45.3 no. 1; 15.50.3; 15.51
al-Malik al-Muʿaẓẓam Shihāb al-Dawlah Abū l-Fatḥ Mawdūd ibn Masʿūd ibn Mahmūd 11.15 no. 1
al-Malik al-Muʿaẓẓam Tūrānshāh, son of al-Malik al-Ṣāliḥ Najm al-Dīn Ayyūb 14.54.3
al-Malik al-Muʿizz ʿIzz al-Dīn Aybak al- Turkumānī, Mamlūk ruler of Egypt (nd􏲉.648–655/1250–1255) 15.32; 15.49.3; 15.49.4; 15.49.6
al-Malik al-Muẓaffar Quṭuz al-Muʿizzī, Sayf
al-Dīn, Baḥrī Mamlūk (nd􏲉. 657–658/1259– 1260) 11.13.7.9; 15.32
al-Malik al-Muẓaffar Taqī al-Dīn ʿUmar ibn
al-Malik al-Amjad Bahrām Shāh ibn Far- rukh Shāh ibn Shāhinshāh ibn Ayyūb 15.20; 15.24
al-Malik al-Muẓaffar I ʿUmar ibn Shāhanshāh
Nūr al-Dīn, Abū Saʿīd Taqī al-Dīn, Ayyubid ruler of Hama (nd􏲉. 574/1178–587/1191) 15.24
al-Malik al-Mujāhid Shīrkūh ⅠⅠ ibn al-Qāhir
Muḥammad Nāsir al-Dīn, Ṣalāḥ al-Dīn (nd􏲉. 581/1186–637/1240)–
al-Malik al-Nāṣir Ṣalāḥ al-Dīn Abū l-Muẓaffar Yūsuf ibn Ayyūb, Ayyubid ruler (d. 1260) 15.11.1; 15.11.2; 15.54(?)
al-Malik al-Nāṣir Ṣalāḥ al-Dīn Dāʾūd ibn al-Malik al-Muʿaẓẓam (= al-Malik al-Nāṣir ⅠⅠ Dāʾūd ibn al-Muʿaẓẓam ʿĪsā Sharaf al-Dīn, Ṣalāḥ al-Dīn), Ayyubid ruler of Damascus (nd􏲉. 624–626/1227–1229, d. 1259) 15.21; 15.35; 15.42; 15.43.3; 15.45.2; 15.51 al-Malik al-Nāṣir Ṣalāḥ al-Dīn Yūsuf ibn
Ayyūb `see` Ṣalāḥ al-Dīn (Saladin) al-Malik al-Nāṣir ⅠⅠ Yūsuf ibn al-ʿAzīz
Muḥammad Ghiyāth al-Dīn ⅠⅠ, Ṣalāḥ al-Dīn, Ayyubid ruler of Aleppo (nd􏲉. 634– 658/1236–1260) 15.32; 15.49.3; 15.51; 15.54
Malik al-Nuḥāh ‘King of Grammarians’, Abū Nizār al-Ḥasan ibn Ṣāfī (d. 568/1173) 15.8.12
al-Malik al-Qāhir Muḥammad ibn Shīrkūh I
Asad al-Dīn ibn Shādhī, Naṣīr al-Dīn (also known as Asad al-Dīn Shīrkūh), lord of Homs (nd􏲉. 574–581/1178–1186) 15.23.4.1
al-Malik al-Saʿīd Ghāzī ibn al-Malik al- Manṣūr, Artuqid ruler of Mardin 15.58.5
{433}{!}
al-Malik al-Ṣāliḥ ⅠⅠ Ayyūb ibn al-Kāmil Muḥammad Nāṣir al-Dīn, Najm al- Dīn, Ayyubid ruler of Egypt (nd􏲉. 638– 647/1240–1249) 14.32.2; 14.45; 14.54.3; 14.55.3; 14.56.1; 14.56.3; 14.56.2; 14.56.4 no. 1; 14.58.3; 14.58.4 no. 3; 15.31.1; 15.49; 15.52.1
al-Malik al-Ṣāliḥ ʿImād al-Dīn Abū l-Fidāʾ Ismāʿīl ibn al-Malik al-ʿĀdil Abū Bakr ibn Ayyūb – (nd􏲉. 635/1237–1238 and 637–643/1239–1245), Ayyubid ruler of Damascus and Egypt 15.20; 15.49.2; 15.50; 15.51
al-Malik al-Ẓāhir Ghāzī ibn Yūsuf, Ayyubid
ruler of Aleppo (d. 613/1216) 10.75.2; 15.18.1; 15.18.1.3; 15.23.2.1; 15.30; 15.40; 15.50.6
al-Malik al-Ẓāhir Rukn al-Dīn, Baybars Ⅰ al- Bunduqdārī, Baḥrī Mamlūk, fourth Mam- lūk ruler of Egypt (nd􏲉. 658–676/1260– 1277) 14.46; 14.54.3; 14.55.1; 14.55.2; 14.55.3; 15.32
al-Maʾmūn, seventh Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 198– 218/813–833) 8.3.5; 8.3.11n; 8.3.13; 8.3.15n; 8.3.17; 8.3.20; 8.3.22; 8.3.23; 8.4.2n; 8.13; 8.15.1n; 8.20.4n; 8.21.1n; 8.25.7n; 8.26.17n; 8.29.3n; 9.12; 9.32n; 9.40n; 9.41; 10.1.3; 10.1.14 no. 22; 12.3 no. 1; 14.25.1n; AⅠⅠ.2.2n
al-Maʾmūn, Yaḥyā ibn Ismāʿīl ibn Dhī l-Nūn, king of the 􏲝􏱎􏱏heag of Toledo (nd􏲉. 435– 467/1043–1074) 13.38.2; 13.39.2; 13.45
Maʾmūn ibn Maʾmūn (nd􏲍pd Muḥammad) `see` Khwārazmshāh Abū l-ʿAbbās Maʾmūn
al-Manāwī, author of a commentary on the Hippocratic Aphorisms 15.60.2n
Mani (Mānī), founder of Manicheism (d. 276) 5.1.8.2n
Manichaeans 10.1.14 nos. 114, 171 Mankah al-Hindī (Mā􏲹ikya), Indian phys-
ician and translator under Hārūn al-Rashīd 12.1n; 12.2 no. 6n; 12.3 no. 1; 12.5 al-Manṣūr, Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 136–158/754– 75) 8.1; 8.2; 8.3.4n; 8.3.10n; 8.3.17n; 8.8n; 8.181.1n; 8.25.2n; 8.29.5n; 8.29.8n; 9.1; 9.31n; 9.41n; 11.2; 12.5n; 14.1
al-Manṣūr ibn Abī ʿĀmir, chamberlain of al- Ḥakam ⅠⅠ and cd ea􏲍pl ruler of al-Andalus
between 368–392/978–1002 13.29.1; 13.35
no. 3; 13.52
Manṣūr ibn Bānās, translator 9.34
Manṣūr ibn Dubays, Bahāʾ al-Dawlah, Maz-
yadid ruler (nd􏲉. 474–479/1082–1086) 10.64.2
al-Manṣūr ibn Ismāʿīl [ibn Khāqān], ‘Gov- ernor of Khorasan and Transoxiana’ to whom ⅠAU (apparently in error) says al- Rāzī dedicated his book a􏱌]Ma􏱋􏲚􏱊n􏲞 11.5.9; 11.5.14
Manṣūr ibn Ṭalḥah ibn Ṭāhir ibn al-Ḥusayn
(active 3rd/9th c.), philosopher and
Ṭāhirid governor 11.5.25 no. 165 al-Manṣūr, Yaʿqūb Abū Yūsuf ibn ʿAbd al- Muʾmin, third Almohad ruler (r 580– 595/1184–1199) 13.63.3; 13.63.5; 13.66.3.; 13.66.4; 13.68.3; 13.72; 13.73; 13.74; 13.77; 13.79; 13.83; 13.85
Manṣūr al-Namarī, poet of the 2nd/8th c. 13.63.8.2
Mantias, physician of antiquity 4.1.10.2; 4.11.2
al-Manṭiqī `see` Abū Sulaymān Muḥammad ibn Ṭāhir
al-Maqrīzī, Taqī al-Dīn (d. 845/1442), Egyp- tian historian AⅠⅠ.16
Mar Elias `see` Elias of Nisibis
Marcian, 5th-c. emperor 6.1.3 Marcus, physician of antiquity, pupil of
Ghūrus 3.2; 4.1.10.5
al-Māridīnī, Fakhr al-Dīn Abū ʿAbd Allāh
Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd al-Salām, phys- ician and teacher of Shihāb al-Dīn al- Suhrawardī al-Maqtūl and Sadīd al-Dīn ibn Raqīqah 10.64.18; 10.75; 15.18.1; 15.29; 15.46.1; 15.46.2; 15.46.3; 15.46.3.9; 15.50
Marinus, late-antique physician 3.6; 5.2.1 Marinus of Alexandria, 2nd-c. anatomist 5.1.37 no. 22
Marinus, a king of the Greeks, perhaps to
be identified with the mythological hero
Minos 7.2.2
Marius ‘the Methodist’ `see` Thessalus Marsyas, legendary Phrygian satyr associated
with music 1.1n
Martialius, 2nd-c. anatomist at Rome 5.1.10.1; 5.1.10.2
{434}
Maʿrūf al-Karkhī, ascetic, Sufi and tradition- alist (d. 200/815–816) 15.51.7
Mārūt, one of the two angels who descended to earth in Babylon 10.68.2.2n; 15.56.1n
Marwān ibn ʿAlī ibn Salāmah al-Fanakī `see` Ḥujjat al-Dīn
Marwān ibn al-Ḥakam, Umayyad caliph (nd􏲉. 646–645/684–5) 7.5.6; 8.19.2n
Marwān ibn Janāḥ, Andalusian physician and philologist 13.47
Marwān (ⅠⅠ) ibn Muḥammad al-Jaʿdī al-Ḥimār (nd􏲉. 127–132/744–50), last Umayyad caliph 15.31.1n
Maryam bint Bukhtīshūʿ, sister of Jibrīl ibn Bukhtīshūʿ, mother of Jūrjis ibn Mīkhāʾīl 8.15
al-Maryamī, probably the 3rd/9th-c. Egyptian
poet al-Qāsim ibn Yaḥyā al-Maryamī 13.58
al-Marzubānī, Abū ʿUbayd Allāh Muḥammad ibn ʿImrān, 4th/10th-c. scholar 8.29.15n
al-Marzūqī, Abū ʿAlī Aḥmad ibn Muḥammad ibn al-Ḥasan, author of a commentary on the Ḥak􏱎oag of Abū Tammām 7.2.3n; 8.29.15n
Māsarjawayh (also Māsarjīs, Persian Mās-
arg􏲭ye), Jewish Umayyad physician and
translator 6.5.1; 8.19; 9.8
Māsarjīs `see` Māsarjawayh
Māsawayh, son of Yūḥannā ibn Māsawayh 8.26.12
Māsawayh Abū Yūḥannā, physician in the
service of Hārūn al-Rashīd 8.25 al-Maṣdūm, Abū l-Ḥusayn ibn Asdūn,
Andalusian physician 13.62.3; 13.63.6; 13.77; 13.78
Māshāʾallāh, astrologer courtier of Hārūn al-Rashīd 12.1n
al-Masīḥ, Christ, the Messiah 5.1.4; 5.1.5; 5.1.6; 5.1.7; 5.1.8; 5.1.11; 5.1.12.1–2; 5.1.13; 5.1.14; 5.1.21.2; 8.5; 8.26; 8.29; 11.13.7(p); 15.8.1(p); 15.51.3(p); 15.58.7(p); `see` a􏱌ol Christians/Christianity
Masīḥ ibn Ḥakam, physician at the court of Hārūn al-Rashīd 12.5n
al-Masīḥī `see` Abū Sahl al-Masīḥī Maslamah, transmitter 7.2.3 Maslamah ibn Aḥmad `see` al-Majrīṭī Masrūr, 􏲉gq􏱌􏱎k of al-Muʿtaḍid 10.10.2
Masrūr al-Kabīr (Masrūr al-Khādim al- Kabīr), eunuch, transmitter, fictional companion of Hārūn al-Rashīd 8.20.4n; 12.6
Masrūr Samānah, eunuch associate of al-Muʿtaṣim 8.20.4
al-Mastūr, Abū l-Faraj al-Ḥusayn ibn
Muḥammad, grammarian and poet
(d. 392/1001–1002) 10.64
Masʿūd ibn Maḥmūd ibn Seb􏱮ktegin (nd􏲉. 421–432/1030–1040), ruler of Ghaznah 11.13.3.17; 11.13.8 no. 5; 11.15 no. 13
al-Masʿūdī, Abu l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn al-Ḥusayn, author of historical and geographical works (d. 345/956) 4.6.1; 4.6.3.3; 5.1.6; 7.5.5n; 7.5.6n; 7.6n; 8.3.7n; 8.3.16n; 8.29.11n; 8.29.22n; 11.5.25 no. 201 Maternus, Triarius Maternus Lasciuius,
Roman consul 5.1.12.2
Mattā ibn Yūnān (or Yūnus) `see` Abū Bishr
Mattā
Matthaeus the Elder, physician of antiquity,
pupil of M􏱭nas 3.3
Matthaeus the Younger, physician of
antiquity 3.4
al-Māwardī, Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Muḥammad
ibn Ḥabīb, Shāfiʿite jurist (d. 450/1058) 10.38.4
Maximinus, physician of antiquity 3.6 al-Maydānī, Abū l-Faḍl Aḥmad ibn Muḥam-
mad, philologist (d. 518/1124) 7.1.6n; 7.5.5n
al-Maymandī, Shams al-Kufāh Aḥmad ibn al-Ḥasan, Ghaznavid vizier (d. 424/1032) 11.13
Maymūn ibn Hārūn, 􏲡􏱎phb (d. 297/909–910) 8.3.13
Maymūn ibn Qays ibn Thaʿlabah al-Aʿshā,
poet (d. after 3/625) 10.1.2; 11.9.2.5n Maymūn al-Qaṣrī, Fāris al-Dīn, Ayyubid ruler
of Sidon and Nablus (d. 611/1214) 15.23.2.2
al-Māzyār ibn Qārin (d. 225/840), last of the Qārinid rulers of Tabaristan 11.4
Melissus, Empiricist physician of antiquity 3.5; 4.1.11.3
Melkites (al-Malakiyyah) 14.1; 14.6n; 14.10n; 14.15; 14.54.1n; 15.23.1n; 15.43.1
Menalcus, disciple of Hippocrates 4.1.10.1n
{435}{!}
M􏱭nas, legendary Greek physician 3.2; 3.3
Menelaus, Greek author on spherics 14.22.3.2n; 15.31.6n
Menemachus, Methodist physician of antiquity 3.5
Menodotus, 2nd-c. empiricist physician 5.1.37 no. 110
Methodists, school of ancient Greek physi- cians 1.1; 4.1.10.1
Miʾat Alf, the mother of Abū l-ʿAshāʾir (probably Abū l-ʿAshāʾir [Jaysh] ibn Khu- mārawayh, third ruler of the Tulunid dynasty) 14.4.4
Michael the Syncellus, brother of Theodore at Mar Saba 9.23n
Mihrawayh ibn Shahriyār, Khorasanian prince 8.10.3
Mihyār al-Daylamī, poet (d. 428/1036–1037) 10.38.4
Mīkhāʾīl, son-in-law of Jibrīl ibn Bukhtīshūʿ 8.3.5; 8.3.16; 8.3.20
Mīkhāʾīl ibn Māsawayh, personal physician to al-Maʾmūn, brother of Yūḥannā ibn Māsawayh 8.25.1; 8.27; 8.29.3n
Milo of Agrigento, physician of antiquity 3.6
Milo of Croton, Greek athlete 4.3.4.3; 5.1.35n
Milon the Second, physician of antiquity 4.1.10.2
al-Minfākh `see` Muwaffaq al-Dīn al-Minfākh Miskawayh, Abū ʿAlī Aḥmad ibn Muḥam-
mad, philosopher and historian (d. 421/ 1030) 10.45; 10.64.20 no. 5
al-Mismaʿī al-Mutakallim 11.5.25 no. 73 Mithridates, king of Pontus 4.1.10.2; 8.20.11n al-Miṭwāʿ `see` Shams al-Dīn Abū l-Faḍl ibn
Abī l-Faraj
Mnaseas, Methodist physician of antiquity 3.5
Mnesarchus, pupil of Hippocrates and father
of Pythagoras 4.1.10.1; 4.3.4.1 Mnesitheus, Athenian Dogmatist physician 4.1.10.4
Modestus, physician of antiquity, pupil of
Ghūrus 3.2 Mongols `see` al-Tatar Moses `see` Mūsā
the Mouse 􏲽a􏱌]Fa􏱏n, a􏱌]F􏱎n, perhaps = Alvar), Andalusī physician 13.62.2.3
Muʿāwiyah ibn Abī Sufyān, founder of Umayyad dynasty (nd􏲉. 41–60/661–680) 7.1.1; 7.5.1; 7.5.2; 7.5.3
Muʿāwiyah ibn al-Ḥārith al-Akbar, pre-
Islamic chieftain in Hadramaut, ancestor
of al-Kindī 10.1
Muʿāwiyah ibn Jabalah, pre-Islamic chieftain
of the Banū l-Ḥārith al-Aṣghar in Had-
ramaut, ancestor of al-Kindī 10.1.3 Muʿāwiyah ibn Yaḥyā, transmitter 10.2.2.1 Muʾayyid al-Dīn, the son of Ibn al-Ṣāʾigh al-ʿAntarī 10.69.3.1
Muʾayyid al-Dīn Abū Ismāʿīl al-Ḥusayn ibn
Muḥammad ibn al-Ḥasan ibn ʿAlī, vizier 11.21 no. 1
Muʾayyid al-Dīn Abū l-Fawāris al-Musayyab ibn ʿAlī al-Ḥusayn, also known as Ibn al-Ṣūfī, vizier in Damascus under Muʿīn al-Dīn Unur 15.8.4
Muʾayyid al-Dīn al-ʿUrḍī (ca. 596–664/ ca. 1200–1266), teacher of Ibn al-Quff 15.60.1
Mubārak ibn Abī l-Khayr Salāmah ibn
Mubārak ibn Raḥmūn `see` Mubārak ibn
Salāmah ibn Raḥmūn
Mubārak ibn Salāmah ibn Raḥmūn, physi-
cian in Egypt 14.28
al-Mubarrad, Abū l-ʿAbbās Muḥammad ibn
Yazīd al-Azdī, philologist, grammarian
(d. 285/898) 15.40.2
al-Mubashshir ibn Fātik, Maḥmūd al-Dawlah
Abū l-Wafāʾ (5th/11th c.), author of Mq􏲡gp􏱎n a􏱌]􏲛h􏲡ak 1.4; 2.1.3; 2.1.7; 4.1.5n; 4.1.7; 4.1.8.1n; 4.1.10.2n; 4.3.3n; 4.3.4.1; 4.3.4.2n; 4.3.5; 4.4.2.1; 4.4.24n; 4.4.2.5; 4.4.4; 4.5.1n; 4.5.3; 4.6.2.1n; 4.6.3.1; 4.6.3.2; 4.6.3.4; 4.6.8n; 4.6.11; 5.1.21.1; 5.1.23; 5.1.35; 10.22.3; 14.23; 14.27.1
Muḍar ibn Nizār ibn Maʿadd ibn ʿAdnān, ancestor of one of the main branches of the ‘Northern Arabs’ 8.10.4n; 15.33(p); 15.46.2(p)
al-Mufaḍḍal ibn Zimām, `mawlā` (client) of
al-Mahdī 10.5.2
al-Mufashkil, unidentified Jewish physician
lampooned by Abū l-Ḥakam al-Maghribī 15.8.11
{436}
al-Mufīd, Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad ibn Muḥammad ibn al-Nuʿmān al-Ḥārithī al-ʿUkbarī, Imāmī Shiite theologian (d. 413/1032) 14.25.9 no. 40n
al-Muhadhdhab Abū Saʿīd ibn Abi Sulayman `see` Abū Saʿīd ibn Abi Sulayman
Muhadhdhab al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Raḥīm ibn ʿAlī (known as al-Dakhwār), high-ranking Syr- ian physician teacher of ⅠAU, Ibn al-Nafīs and Ibn Qāḍī Baʿlabakk (d. 628/1230) 10.64.4; 10.66.3; 10.68.1.3; 10.68.2.1; 10.75.2; 11.12; 14.54.2; 14.56.1; 15.3.1.1; 15.3.1.4; 15.23.4.1; 15.23.4.2; 15.31.1; 15.32; 15.37.1; 15.42; 15.43.1; 15.50; 15.51; 15.52.1; 15.53; 15.54; 15.56.1; 15.56.2 no. 2; 15.57.1; AⅠ.2
Muhadhdhab al-Dīn Abū Naṣr Muḥammad ibn Muḥammad ibn Ibrāhīm ibn al- Khaḍir (or al-Khiḍr) al-Ḥalabī `see` Ibn al-Khaḍir al-Ḥalabī
Muhadhdhab al-Dīn Abū Saʿīd Muḥammad ibn Abī Ḥulayqah, Egyptian physician b. 620/1223 14.54.14; 14.55
Muhadhdhab al-Dīn Aḥmad `see` Ibn al- Ḥājib
Muhadhdhab al-Dīn ibn Habal `see` Ibn Habal
Muhadhdhab al-Dīn ibn al-Naqqāsh (Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Abī ʿAbd Allāh ʿĪsā ibn Hibat Allāh al-Naqqāsh al-Baghdādī), Damascus physician 10.64.19.1n; 14.31.5; 14.44.2; 15.13; 15.14; 15.23.1; 15.24; 15.36.1; 15.48
Muhadhdhab al-Dīn Yūsuf ibn Abī
Saʿīd al-Sāmirī, Samaritan philosopher and physician (d. 624/1227) 15.48; 15.49.1
al-Muhājir ibn Khālid ibn al-Walīd, son of
the celebrated commander Khālid ibn
al-Walīd 7.5.2; 7.5.3
Muḥammad, Prophet, Messenger of God 7.1.5; 10.1.2; 10.2.2.1; 10.2.2.2; 10.68.2.4(p) (‘Aḥmad’); 10.81.3; 11.19.6.2(p); 11.19.7 no. 11; 14.22.5.1 no. 7; 14.25.9 no. 80; 14.31.8n; 15.1.5 no. 62; 15.18.2(p); 15.31.2(p); 15.31.4(p); 15.46.2; 15.46.3 .10(p); 15.51.7
Muḥammad, son of the caliph al-Mutawakkil 8.20.5n
Muḥammad, son of caliph al-Nāṣir li-Dīn Allāh 10.76.2
Muḥammad I al-Awṣat, fifth Umayyad emir of al-Andalus (nd􏲉. 238–272/852–86) 13.12; 13.13; 13.18
Muḥammad al-Amīn `see` al-Amīn Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd Allāh ibn Ḥasan (`or` al-Ḥasan), known as ‘The Pure Soul’ (a􏱌]Naeo a􏱌]Za􏲡huuag), 2nd/8th-c. ʿAlid rebel 8.18.1
Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd Allāh ibn Masarrah
al-Jabalī `see` Ibn Masarrah
Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd Allāh ibn al-Muqaffaʿ,
son of Ibn al-Muqaffaʿ and secretary to
al-Manṣūr 11.2n
Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd Allāh ibn Ṭāhir, head of
police under al-Mutawakkil (d. 253/876) 8.4.10; 8.29.15n
Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd al-Bāqī al-Bazzār, poet 15.51.5n
Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd al-Malik ibn al-Zayyāt `see` Ibn al-Zayyāt
Muḥammad ibn ʿAbdūn al-Jabalī al-ʿIdwī, Andalusian physician (active 350/960) 13.29.2; 13.34; 13.37; 13.38.1 Muḥammad ibn Abī l-ʿAbbās `see` al-Saffāḥ Muḥammad ibn Abī Ayyūb ibn al-Rashīd,
grandson of Hārūn al-Rashīd; and patient
of Yuhanna ibn Masawayh 8.26.11 Muḥammad ibn Abī Bakr, governor of Egypt
in the caliphate of ʿAlī ibn Abī Ṭālib 7.5.6
Muḥammad ibn Abī l-Faḍl al-Ṭūsī, governor of Ṭūs 10.8.4
Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad ibn Abī l-Ashʿath, son of Aḥmad ibn Abī l-Ashʿath 10.46.3
Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad ibn Ṣāliḥ al-ʿAbdī, unidentified westerner physician 13.61.3.1
Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad al-Tamīmī al-Maqdisī, author of M􏱎ccap a􏱌]bam􏱎􏱏 4.5.1n; 15.40.9 no. 35
Muḥammad ibn ʿAlī, al-Bāqir, fifth Imam of theTwelver Shi’is 15.51.7
Muḥammad ibn ʿAlī ibn al-Khallāl al-Baṣrī, Abū l-Ḥusayn, source of al-Tanūkhī 11.5.11
Muḥammad ibn Hārūn ibn Makhlad ‘Kubbah
al-Kātib’, 3rd/9th-c. poet 13.58
{437}{!}
Muḥammad ibn al-Ḥajjāj ibn Yūsuf 7.9.4 Muḥammad ibn al-Ḥasan al-Warrāq, source
quoted by Ibn al-Nadīm 11.5.9 Muḥammad ibn Ḥusayn ibn ʿAbbādah, 5th/11th-c. Andalusian grammarian 8.29.8n
Muḥammad ibn Isḥāq, transmitter 7.2.3 Muḥammad ibn al-Jahm (active 3rd/8th c.),
Muʿtazilite philosoper and off􏲊cial 10.1.14 no. 190
Muḥammad ibn Jarīr al-Ṭabarī `see` al-Ṭabarī, Abū Jaʿfar Muḥammad
Muḥammad ibn Khalaf al-Marzubān, 3rd/9th-c. scholar and translator 7.10 Muḥammad ibn Maḥmūd Khwārazmshāh,
Sejljūq sultan (d. 554/1159) 10.63.3 Muḥammad ibn Malik-Shāh Abū Shujāʿ
Ghiyāth al-Dunyā wa-l-Dīn, Seljuq ruler (nd􏲉. 498–511/1105–1118) 10.64.19.16(p); 10.66.9 no. 2
Muḥammad ibn Marwān Ibn Zuhr al-Iyādī,
father of Abū Marwān ibn Zuhr 13.60.1 Muḥammad ibn Maymūn Markūsh, Andalus-
ian grammarian and poet 13.29.2 Muḥammad ibn Muḥammad al-Ḥasanī `see`
al-Sharīf Muḥammad ibn Muḥammad
al-Ḥasanī
Muḥammad ibn Mūsā, Abū Jaʿfar al-Munajjim (‘the astrologer’), son of Mūsā ibn Shākir, patron of Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq 8.29.22 no. 29; 9.19n; 9.40; 9.47n; 10.3.2.3; 10.3.14 no. 95
Muḥammad ibn Mūsā ibn ʿAbd al-Malik,
patron of translators, perhaps = Abū ʿImrān Mūsā ibn ʿAbd al-Malik ibn Hishām al-Iṣbahānī, high off􏲊cial under al-Mutawakkil (d. 246/860–861) 9.43
Muḥammad ibn Saʿd, uncle of Saʿīd ibn al- Umawī, a source for Ibn Juljul 7.1.6 Muḥammad ibn Saʿīd ibn Hishām al-Ḥajarī
`see` Ibn Mulsāqah
Muḥammad ibn Saʿīd al-Ṭabīb, one of the
Andalusī translators of Dd Mapdnha Mdch􏲍a 13.36.2.3
Muḥammad ibn Ṣāliḥ, 3rd/9th-c. Abbasid prince 8.8.4
Muḥammad ibn Sallām al-Jumaḥī, tradition- ist and author of Ṭabam􏱎p a􏱌]ogq􏱉an􏱎􏱏 (d. ca. 231–232/845–6) 8.7; 8.26.17
Muḥammad ibn Sulaymān ibn al-Hādī, known as Ibn Mashghūf, grandson of al-Hādī (nd􏲉. 785–786) 8.26.12
Muḥammad ibn Ṣāliḥ ibn ʿAbd Allāh al- ʿAlawī (d. 252/866–867 or 255/868–869)
AⅠⅠ.2.1
Muḥammad ibn Ṭāhir ibn al-Ḥusayn 8.19.3
Muḥammad ibn Tamlīkh, 4th/10th-c.
Andalusian physician and judge 13.27 Muḥammad ibn Thawāb, known as Abū l- Thallāj (?Abū l-Falāḥ), Iraqi physician,
disciple of Ibn Abī l-Ashʿath 10.46.2; 10.46.4 nos. 1, 4; 10.47; 15.4
Muḥammad ibn Tawwāb al-Mawṣilī 15.4n Muḥammad ibn Ṭughj `see` Ibn Ṭughj Muḥammad ibn ʿUmar ibn Yaḥyā, Abū l-
Ḥasan, al-Sharīf 10.8.5; 10.8.7 Muḥammad ibn Yaḥyā, unidentified 14.36.2
Muḥammad ibn Yasīr, poet 8.29.22n Muḥammad al-Sāʿātī, clockmaker and chro-
nometrist, father of Fakhr al-Dīn Riḍwān
al-Sāʿātī 15.29
Muḥammad al-Shajjār, one of the Andalusī
translators of Dd Mapdnha Mdch􏲍a 13.36.2.3
al-Muḥassin ibn Ibrāhīm al-Ṣābiʾ (d. 410/ 1010), father of Hilāl al-al-Ṣābiʾ 10.4.9; 10.8.8; 10.8.9
al-Muhtadī bi-Allāh, Abū ʿAbd Allāh
Muḥammad ibn al-Wāthiq, son and suc- cessor to al-Wāthiq (nd􏲉. 255–256/869–70) 8.4.4; 8.16; 8.23.3n
Muḥyī l-Dīn, Abū l-Maʿālī Muḥammad ibn
al-qāḍīʿAlī Zakī al-Dīn (d. 598/1202), chief
judge of Damascus 15.50; 15.33
Muḥyī l-Dīn, judge of Marand 11.19.2 Muḥyī l-Dīn ibn (al-)ʿArabī `see` Ibn ʿArabī Muʿīn al-Dīn ibn Raqīqah, brother of Sadīd
ibn Raqīqah 15.46.1
Muʿīn al-Dīn, Father of Khunad `or` Khwand
Khātūn, the wife of Saladin 15.23.2 Muʿīn al-Dīn ibn Shaykh al-Shuyūkh, Ayyu-
bid emir 15.49.2
Muʿīn al-Dīn Unur 15.8.4n al-Muʿizz li-Dīn Allāh, Maʿadd, fourth
Fāṭimid caliph (nd􏲉. 341–364/953–75) 14.14.3; 14.9; 14.15n; 14.22.3.1n
{438}{!}
Muʿizz al-Dawlah, founder of Būyid rule in Baghdad (d. 356/967) 8.5.2; 10.27
Muʿizz al-Dawlah Thimāl ibn Ṣāliḥ, Mirdāsid ruler of Aleppo (nd􏲉. 442–449/1050–1057– 8) 10.38.2
Mujāhid al-ʿĀmirī, ruler of the 􏲝􏱎􏱏heag of Denia (nd􏲉. 405–436/1014–1044/45) 13.7; 13.48; 13.60.2
Mujāhid al-Dīn Qaymāz 10.81.2 al-Muktafī, Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 288– 295/902–908) 8.30.1n; 9.26n; 14.5n Mumahhid al-Dawlah, Abū Manṣūr, ruler
from the Marwānid dynasty at Mayyāfār-
iqīn 8.5.4; 8.5.5; 10.27
Munaḥḥim ibn al-Fawwāl, Andalusian physi-
cian 13.46
al-Munayḥī, Abū l-Ghawth ibn Niḥrīr, 4th/10th-c. poet 10.64
Muʾnis al-Faḥl, chief of police under al-Muʿtaḍid 10.2.3.1
Muʾnis al-Khādim, servant of al-Muʿtaḍid 10.10.5
Munkar, Islamic angel 15.8.11(p) al-Muntaṣir bi-Allāh, eleventh Abbasid
caliph (nd􏲉. 247–248/861–62) – 8.4.3al- Muqtadir bi-Allāh (Abū l-Faḍl Jaʿfar ibn Aḥmad al-Muʿtaḍid), Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 295–320/908–932) 8.5.2; 8.26.16n; 8.33; 9.36n; 14.5n; 15.1.3; 15.1.3.2
al-Muqbilī, Abū Naṣr Muḥammad ibn Yūsuf,
Iraqi physician 10.55
al-Muqtadī bi-amr Allāh, Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 476–478/1075–1094) 10.58.1; 10.58.5 no. 1; 10.59.1; 10.59.2 nos. 1, 2, 3
al-Muqtadir bi-Allāh, Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 295–320/908–932) 10.4.1; 10.4.4.1; 10.4.6; 10.4.7; 10.5.1; 10.44.1
al-Muqtafī li-amr Allāh (Abū ʿAbd Allāh
Muḥammad ibn al-Mustaẓhir), Abbasid
caliph (nd􏲉. 530–555/1136–1160) 10.68.1.4; 10.72
Murshid, unidentified 10.62.3(p)
Mūsā ‘the blind’, Abbasid prince
Mūsā, Moses 10.51.2(p); 13.50; 15.17(p); 15.46; 15.40.3; 15.46.3.6(p); 15.56.1n Mūsā al-Hādī `see` al-Hādī
Mūsā ibn ʿAbd al-Malik, secretary to the caliph al-Mutawakkil (nd􏲉. 232–247/847– 61) 8.12; 9.43n
Mūsā ibn Abī l-ʿAbbās al-Shāshī, governor of al-Shāsh (Tashkent) 8.10.4
Mūsā ibn Abī l-Faraj ibn al-Daḥḥāk AⅠⅠ.2.2n Mūsā ibn al-ʿAyzār `see` Mūsā ibn al-ʿĀzār al-Isrāʾīlī
Mūsā ibn al-ʿĀzār al-Isrāʾīlī, physician in the
service of al-Muʿizz li-Dīn Allāh 14.9 Mūsā ibn Isrāʾīl al-Kūfī (129–222/746–747– 837), personal physician of Ibrāhīm ibn
al-Mahdī 8.18
Mūsā ibn Jaʿfar, al-Kāẓim, seventh Imam of
the Twelver Shi’is 15.51.7
Mūsā ibn Khālid ‘the Translator’ (a􏱌]
pqn􏲳qk􏱎􏱋), pupil of Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq 8.29.8; 9.20
Mūsā ibn Maymūn, Moses Maimonides, Abū ʿImrān al-Qurṭubī (527–606/1135–1208) Jewish theologian, philosopher and physi- cian 14.38.1n; 14.39; 14.40.1n; 15.40.3; 15.51.1
Mūsā ibn Muḥammad ibn Saʿīd ibn Mūsā ibn
Ḥudayr, vizier under ʿAbd al-Raḥmān ⅠⅠⅠ 13.21.2.1
Mūsā ibn Yūsuf ibn Sayyār, Abū Māhir, physi- cian 10.24; 10.25
Muslim ibn al-Ḥajjāj, compiler of a canonical collection of hadiths (d. 261/875) 7.1.5n
Muslim ibn al-Walīd, poet (d. 207/823) 10.64.19.5n, 13.63.8.2n
al-Mustaḍīʾ bi-amr Allāh, Abū Muḥammad
al-Ḥasan ibn al-Mustanjid, Abbasid caliph
(nd􏲉. 566–575/1170–1180) 10.63.2; 10.64.5 al-Mustaʿīn, Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 248– 252/862–66) 8.4.3; 8.4.8n; 8.23.1n; 10.1.6 al-Mustaʿīn bi-Allāh, Abū Jaʿfar Aḥmad ibn
Hūd, ruler of the p􏱎􏱏heag of Saragossa (nd􏲉. 478–503/1085–1110) 13.57 al-Mustakfī bi-Allāh, Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 333–334/944–46) 10.5.1
al-Mustanjid bi-Allāh, Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 555–566/1160–1170) 10.63.2; 10.64.5; 10.66.1
al-Mustanṣir (Abū Tamīm Maʿadd al- Mustanṣir bi-Allāh), Fatimid caliph (420–487/1029–1094) 10.38; 14.25.3n; 14.25.5; 14.26.3 no. 2n al-Mustanṣir bi-Allāh (Abū Jaʿfar al-Mustanṣir al-Manṣūr ibn al-Ẓāhir),
{439}
Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 623–640/1226–1242) 8.4.3n; 10.38.3; 5.35; 15.40.7
al-Mustarshid bi-Allāh, Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 512–529/1118–1135) 10.62.1
al-Mustaẓhir bi-Allāh, Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 487–512/1094–1118) 10.58.1; 10.61
al-Muʿtaḍid bi-Allāh, Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 279–289/892–902) 10.2.3.1; 10.2.3.2; 10.2.3.3; 10.2.4 no. 20; 10.3.2.3; 10.3.6; 10.3.14 no. 139; 10.10.1; 10.10.4; 10.10.5; 10.11; 10.12.2; 10.15; 14.5n; 14.11
al-Muʿtaḍid bi-Allāh Abī ʿAmr ʿAbbād ibn ʿAbbād, ruler of the p􏱎􏱏heag of Seville (nd􏲉. 433–460/1042–1069) 13.61.1
al-Muʿtamar ibn al-ʿAssāl, theologian 8.29.22n
al-Muʿtamid, governor of Damascus 15.40.3
al-Muʿtamid ʿalā Allāh, Aḥmad ibn al- Mutawakkil, Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 256– 279/870–92) 8.26.16n; 8.34; 8.32.1n; 10.14.1; 10.14.2.1; 14.5n
Mutammim ibn Nuwayrah, 1st/7th-c. poet 14.32.4(p); 15.37.4(p)
al-Mutanabbī, Abū l-Ṭayyib Aḥmad ibn al-Ḥusayn al-Juʿfī, poet (d. 354/965) 14.27.2n; 15.8.2n; 15.8.15n; 15.17n; 15.31.1n; 15.37.4n; 15.40.2; 15.40.4n; 15.46.3.6n; 15.49n (􏳁􏳂 B); 15.52.1.2n; 15.54n
al-Muṭarriz, Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad ibn ʿAlī al-Sulamī al-Dimashqī, grammarian, lexicographer and `adīb` (d. 456/1064) 15.31.6 no. 18
al-Muʿtaṣim bi-Allāh, Muḥammad Abū Isḥāq,
Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 218–227/833–42) 7.1.5n; 7.8.3n; 8.3.5n; 8.4.2n; 8.4.5n; 8.4.7n; 8.4.10n; 8.11n; 8.12.1n; 8.20.1; 8.20.2; 8.20.3; 8.20.4; 8.20.5; 8.20.6; 8.20.7; 8.20.11; 8.26.4; 8.26.17; 8.27.3; 9.49n; 10.1.3; 10.68.1.4; 11.4
al-Muʿtaṣim bi-Allāh, Ibn Ṣumādiḥ, emir of Almeria 13.40
al-Mutawakkil ʿalā Allāh, Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 232–247/847–61) 8.4.1; 8.4.2; 8.4.3; 8.4.4; 8.4.7; 8.4.8; 8.4.9; 8.12.1; 8.1.2.2; 8.16; 8.20.5; 8.23.1; 8.23.2; 8.26.3; 8.26.4; 8.26.9; 8.26.12; 8.26.15; 8.26.16; 8.26.18; 8.29.7n; 8.29.9; 8.29.11; 8.29.12; 8.29.13; 8.29.16; 8.29.17; 8.29.18; 8.29.19; 8.29.20; 8.29.22; 9.43n; 9.46n; 9.49n; 10.1.7; 10.4.5; 10.10.1; 10.14.2.1; 10.68.1.4; 11.4; 13.36.2.1
Mutayyam, musician 8.3.23
Muʿtazilites, al-Muʿtazilah, ‘rationalist’ theo-
logians 11.5.25 nos. 53, 144; 13.4; 14.22.4.3 nos. 20, 36; 14.22.5.1 nos. 11, 12
al-Muʿtazz bi-Allāh, Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 252– 255/866–69) 5.1.37 no. 101; 8.4.3n; 8.4.8; 8.23.1; 8.23.2; 8.23.3
al-Muṭīʿ li-Allāh, Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 334– 363/946–74) 10.5.1; 10.28; 10.29 al-Muttaqī, Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 329– 333/940–44) 10.5.1
al-Muwaffaq Abū l-Barakāt ibn al-Quḍāʿī `see`
Abū l-Barakāt ibn al-Quḍāʿī al-Muwaffaq bi-Allāh, Ṭalḥah ibn Jaʿfar
al-Mutawakkil (nd􏲉. 256–278/870–91), Abbasid prince 8.32.1; 8.32.2; 8.32.3; 10.3.6; 10.10.1; 10.10.2; 10.10.3; 10.10.4 Muwaffaq al-Dīn ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz al-Sulamī,
pupil of Ilyās ibn al-Muṭrān 15.24; 15.34; 15.45.1; 15.50.1; 15.50.6
Muwaffaq al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Salām, physician and philosopher 15.54
Muwaffaq al-Dīn Abū l-Khayr, brother of Muhadhdhab al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn Abī Ḥulayqah, oculist 14.55.3
Muwaffaq al-Dīn Abū Naṣr ʿAdnān ibn Manṣūr `see` Ibn al-ʿAynzarbī
Muwaffaq al-Dīn Abū Shākir ibn Abī Sulay- mān Dāwūd `see` Abū Shākir ibn Abī Sulaymān Dāwūd
Muwaffaq al-Dīn Abū Ṭāhir al-Ḥusayn ibn Muḥammad, unidentified 10.64.19.19
Muwaffaq al-Dīn Hibat Allāh `see` Ibn al- Naḥḥās
Muwaffaq al-Dīn ibn al-Muṭrān `see` Ibn al- Muṭrān, Muwaffaq al-Dīn
Muwaffaq al-Dīn ibn al-Quff, philologist and litt􏲰rateur, father of the physician Ibn al- Quff 15.60.1
Muwaffaq al-Dīn al-Minfākh, Abū l-Faḍl Asʿad ibn Ḥulwān, physician 15.55
Muwaffaq al-Dīn ibn al-Ṣaraf, physician at the al-Nūrī hospital 15.51.2
Muwaffaq al-Dīn Yaʿqūb Ibn Siqlāb `see` Ibn Siqlāb
{440}
Muwaffaq al-Dīn Yaʿqūb al-Sāmirī (Abū Yūsuf Yaʿqūb ibn Ghanāʾim), Samaritan physi- cian and philosopher 15.59; 15.60.1
al-Muwaffaq ibn Shūʿah, Jewish physician serving Saladin 14.31.2n; 14.36; 14.47.2
al-Muẓaffar, ʿAbd al-Malik ibn Abī ʿĀmir, chamberlain of al-Ḥakam ⅠⅠ and cd ea􏲍pl ruler of al-Andalus in 392–399/1002– 1008 13.19.1
Muẓaffar ibn al-Dawātī, 5th/11th-c. off􏲊cial 10.61
Myrmex, servant of Aristotle 4.6.6.2
Nabataeans (al-Nabaṭ) 1.1n; 1.5 (of Iraq and Syria); 8.29.6n
Nabataeans of Iraq `see` Chaldaeans al-Nābighah al-Dhubyānī, pre-Islamic poet 15.58.4n; 10.64.19.18n
al-Nābulusī, surveyor of Fayyum 9.45n al-Naḍr ibn al-Ḥārith ibn Kaladah al-Thaqafī,
opponent of the Prophet Muḥammad 7.2; 7.5.2n
al-Nadrūmī `see` Abū ʿAbd Allāh al-Nadrūmī Nāfashal `see` Nūfashal
Nāfiʿ, transmitter 10.81.3
Nāfiʿ, servant of Khālid ibn al-Muhājir ibn
Khālid ibn al-Walīd 7.5.3
Nāfiʿ ibn al-Ḥārith ibn Kaladah, son of the
slave-girl Sumayyah and, probably, the
physician al-Ḥārith ibn Kaladah 7.1.1 Nafīs al-Dīn ibn al-Zubayr, al-Qāḍī, pupil of Ibn Shūʿah and al-Shaykh al-Sadīd Raʿīs
al-Ṭibb (b. 555 `or` 556/1160) 14.31.2; 14.31.4; 14.31.7; 14.36.3; 14.47; 15.51.1 Najāḥ al-Sharābī, Najm al-Dawlah Abū l-
Yumn (d. 615/1218), off􏲊cial at the caliphal
court 10.76.2; 10.77.2
al-Najāshī al-Ḥārithī, 1st/7th-c. poet 7.5.6n Najīb al-Dīn Abū Ḥāmid Muḥammad al-Samarqandī `see` al-Samarqandī, Najīb
al-Dīn Abū Ḥāmid
Najm al-Dīn Abū l-Fatḥ Shāh Ghāzī Malik
Shāh, son of Ṭughril Beg 11.21 no. 3 Najm al-Dīn Abū l-Ghanāʾim Muḥammad
ibn ʿAlī ibn al-Muʿallim al-Hurthī, poet of
Wāsiṭ 10.62.3
Najīb al-Dīn Asʿad al-Hamadānī (`or` al-Hamadhānī), philosopher from Persia 15.30
Najm al-Dīn Ayyūb, father of Ṣalāḥ al-Dīn (Saladin) 14.36.2; 15.23.5 no. 3
Najm al-Dīn Ayyūb al-Malik al-Ṣāliḥ `see` al- Malik al-Ṣāliḥ ⅠⅠ Ayyūb
Najm al-Dīn Ḥamzah ibn ʿĀbid al-Ṣarkhadī, transmitter 10.83.4
Najm al-Dīn ibn al-Lubūdī, physician son of Shams al-Dīn ibn al-Lubūdī 15.31
Najm al-Dīn ibn al-Minfākh, Abū l-ʿAbbās Aḥmad ibn Abī l-Fāḍl Asʿad ibn Ḥulwān nicknamed ‘the son of the singer’, physi- cian teacher of Ibn al-Quff 15.56; 15.59
no. 2; 15.60.1
Najm al-Dīn ibn al-Ṣalāḥ `see` Ibn al-Ṣalāḥ Najm al-Dīn Ilghāzī ibn Artuq `see` Ilghāzī ibn
Artuq
Najm al-Dīn al-Qamrāwī, Abū l-Faḍāʾil Mūsā
ibn Muḥammad ibn Mūsā ibn Aḥmad ibn ʿĪsā al-Kinānī (d. 651/1253), student of Kamāl al-Dīn ibn Yūnus 10.83.4
Najm al-Dīn ʿUmar ibn Muḥammad ibn al- Kuraydī, al-Qāḍī 1.9; 10.66.7; 10.83
Najm al-Dīn Yūsuf ibn Sharaf al-Dīn ʿAlī ibn Muḥammad al-Asfizārī 11.19.4
Najm ibn Ṭarafah, master falconer 13.25 al-Najm al-Khabūshānī `see` al-Khabūshānī Nakīr, Islamic angel 15.8.11n
Namrūd ibn Kūsh `see` Nimrod, son of Cush Nāqil al-Hindī 12.2 no. 13
Narses the Roman, late-antique physician 5.2.1
al-Nāshiʾ al-Akbar, Abū l-ʿAbbās ʿAbd Allāh ibn Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd Allāh ibn Mālik al-Anbārī, also known as Ibn Shirshīr
(d. 293/906), poet and Muʿtazilite theo- logian 11.5.25 no. 19
Nasīm, servant of Aḥmad ibn Ṭūlūn 14.4.1; 14.4.2
Nasīm, al-Sitt (Lady), a woman of Baghdad writing letters on behalf of al-Nāṣir li-Dīn Allāh 10.77.3
al-Nāṣir, unidentified ruler 11.13.7.9(p) al-Nāṣir Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad (nd􏲉. 595–610/1199–1213), fourth Almohad ruler 13.63.3; 13.64.1; 13.64.2.1; 13.66.5; 13.67; 13.68.2; 13.68.3; 13.70; 13.71; 13.76; 13.79; 13.81.2; 13.82; 13.84; 13.85
Naṣīr al-Dawlah Abū ʿAlī al-Ḥusayn ibn Abū
{441}{!}
ʿAlī al-Ḥasan ibn Ḥamdān `see` Ibn Ḥam-
dān
Naṣīr al-Dawlah, perhaps = Naṣr al-Dawlah
Abū Naṣr Aḥmad ibn Marwān, prince of the Marwānid dynasty of Diyarbakr (d. 463/1061) 8.6 no. 10; 10.39; 10.41
Nāṣir al-Dawlah, Abū Muḥammad al-Ḥasan ibn ʿAbd Allāh, prince of the Ḥamdānid dynasty (d. 357/968?) 10.46.2
Naṣīr al-Dawlah ibn Marwān, Marwānid ruler of Diyār Bakr (d. 489/1096) 10.39
Naṣīr al-Dīn, unidentified 10.64.2(p); 10.75
Nāṣir al-Dīn ibn Yaghmūr, head of the house- hold of the Ayyubid ruler al-Malik al-Ṣāliḥ Ismāʿīl 15.49.4
Naṣīr al-Dīn Nāṣir ibn Mahdī al-ʿAlawī al-Rāzī (d. 617/1220), vizier 10.76.2
Nāṣir al-Dīn Zikrī `or` Zakarī, Ayyubid emir also known as Ibn ʿUlaymah, companion to al-Malik al-Ṣāliḥ Najm al-Dīn Ayyūb 15.49.5
Naṣīr al-Ḥalabī `see` Nuṣayr al-Ḥalabī Nāṣir ibn Ismāʿīl, al-Sharīf Abū Ṭālib 10.22.4
no.7
al-Nāṣir li-Dīn Allāh, Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 575–622/1180–1223) 15.40; 10.76.2; 10.76.3
Naṣr al-Dawlah Aḥmad ibn Marwān, Mar- wānid ruler of Mayyāfāriqīn and Diyār Bakr (nd􏲉. 401–453/1010–1060–1) 10.38.6
no. 10; 10.41; 10.54.1; 10.54.2; 10.70 mo. 1
(`see` a􏱌ol Naṣīr al-Dawlah)
Naṣr ibn Manṣūr ibn Bassām, grandfather of 3rd/9th-c. poet Ibn Bassām 8.20.5 Nasṭās ibn Jurayj – Christian physician prac-
tised during the reign of al-Ikhshīd ibn
Ṭughj 13.14; 14.6; 14.7
al-Nātilī `see` Abū ʿAbd Allāh al-Nātilī Nawbakht, Banū 11.3
al-Nawbakhtī, Abū Muḥammad al-Ḥasan (d.
between 300/912 and 310/922), Imamite
scholar and translator 10.3.8.7 Naẓīf al-Qass al-Rūmī 10.33; 11.5.6 Nazīn Bālī `see` Ninus, son of Belus al-Naẓẓām, Muʿtazilite theologian, (d.
between 220/835 and 230/845) 10.64
.19.1n; AⅠⅠ.2.2n
Nebrus, ancestor of Hippocrates 4.4.1
Nebuchadnezzar, king of Babylon 4.1.5 Nemesius, 4th-c. author confused with
Gregory of Nyssa 6.5.2
Nero, 1st-c. Roman emperor 5.1.8.1; 5.1.8.2
Nerva, 1st-c. Roman emperor 5.1.8.2 Nicanor of Stagira, commander under Alex-
ander the Great 4.6.6.1; 4.6.13.3 no. 114
Nicolaus, late-antique physician 4.1.11.3n; 5.2.1
Nicolaus Damascenus 13.66.6 no. 9 Nicomachus, father of Aristotle (wrongly
identified as Nicomachus of Gerasa) 4.6.1
Nicomachus of Gerasa, mathematician (d. A􏲬120) 10.3.14 no. 103
Nicus, nicknamed ‘the One-eyed’, fabricator of works supposedly by Pythagoras 4.3.6.2
Nifṭawayh, Abū ʿAbd Allāh Ibrāhīm ibn
Muḥammad, grammarian (244–323/858– 935) 10.1.9
al-Nīlī, Abū Sahl Saʿīd ibn ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz, physi-
cian and man of letters (d. 420/1020) 10.56
Nimrod, son of Cush 2.1.4
Ninus, son of Belus, mythical founder of
Nineveh 2.1.4
Niqūlā, Byzantine monk collaborator in
the Andalusī translation of Dd Mapdnha
Mdch􏲍a 13.36.2.3; 13.36.2.4
Nitaforas, fictional Greek prince, son of King
Rufistanes 4.6.7.2
(al-)Niẓām, possibly the famous Seljuq
statesman Niẓām al-Mulk (d. 485/1092) 10.58.5 no. 4
al-Niẓām, unidentified (6th/12th c.) 10.81.2 Nizār ibn Maʿadd ibn ʿAdnān, legendary
ancestor of one of the main branches
of the ‘Northern Arabs’ 8.10.4n; 15.8.5(p) Nuʿaym, perhaps Abū ʿAbd Allāh Nuʿaym ibn
Hammad ibn Muʿāwiyah al-Khuzāʿī al- Marwazī, 3rd/10th-c. Hadith scholar 7.3
Nūfashal (`or` Nāfashal or T]s]m]og]p]􏱌 or
Tūqashtal or Tugashtal or Fūfasal), unidentified Indian medical author 12.2
no. 10
{442}{!}
Nūḥ ibn Manṣūr (nd􏲉. 366–387/977–97), Samanid emir of Transoxiana 11.13.2.1,9
Numenius, 2nd-c. A􏲬 Platonist philosopher 4.3.1n
Nūr al-Dīn ibn Jamāl al-Dīn ibn Artaq `or` Artuq, ruler of Ḥīnī 15.46.3
Nūr al-Dīn ibn Zankī (`or` Zangī) `see` al-Malik al-ʿĀdil Nūr al-Dīn Maḥmūd ibn Zankī
Nuṣayr (`or` Naṣīr) al-Ḥalabī, unidentified 15.8.11
Nuṣrat al-Dīn ibn Jahān Pahlawān ibn Shams al-Dīn Eldig􏱮z, ruler of Azerbaijan (d. 582/1186) 11.21n
Olympiodorus, 5th-c. philosopher 4.5.4n Olympius, slave belonging to Aristotle 4.6.6.2
Oribasius, 4th-c. physician to Julian the
Apostate 1.5; 9.19n; 4.1.10.1n; 5.1.32; 5.2.1 (Oribasius the Obstetrician); 5.2.1 (works); 14.25.2
Orosius, late 4th/early 5th-c. author of Hho]
plnhad acrdnoqk 􏲤a􏲉a􏱋lo 2.1.1n; 2.1.2; 2.1.4n; 13.36.2.1
Otho, 1st-c. Roman emperor 5.1.8.2

Palladius, late-antique physician 5.2.1n; 6.1.1
Pamphilianus, dedicatee of Galen 5.1.37
no. 82
Panaetius of Rhodes, 2nd-c. BC Stoic philo- sopher 4.1.11.3n
Pantacles, Empiricist physician of antiquity 3.5
Parmenides, Presocratic philosopher 3.2; 3.4
Patrophilus, dedicatee of Galen 5.1.37
no. 117n
Paul, apostle 5.1.5 (nephew of Galen); 5.1.8.1; 5.1.25n
Paul of Aegina, 7th-c. physician and author of Cl􏱌􏱌d􏲍phl􏱋do kdch􏲍ad 4.1.11.3; 5.2.1
(works); 14.25.2
Paulus, physician of antiquity, pupil of
Ghūrus 3.2; 3.4; 4.1.10.5 Pedanius `see` Dioscorides ‘Pell-Mell’ `see` (al-)Ḥayṣ Bayṣ Pelops, Dogmatist teacher of Galen 5.1.25; 5.1.37 nos. 36, 101
Perdiccas, 5th-c. BC king of Macedonia 4.1.5 Perennis, Tigidius, 2nd-c. praetorian prefect 5.1.12.2
Perictione, pen-name of an author who
wrote in the style of Pythagoras 4.3.6.2n Peripatetics (a􏱌]Maogog􏱎􏱏􏱊􏱋), followers of a
school of philosophy founded by Aristotle 2.1.6.4; 5.1.25; 13.66.6 no. 32
Persius, late-antique physician 5.2.1n; 6.1.1n Peter, apostle 5.1.8.1
Peter ⅠⅠ, king of Aragon 13.71n
Pethion the Translator, author of a lost eccle-
siastical history (active 2nd half 9th c.) 8.1.1; 8.2.1; 8.3.2; 8.3.3n; 8.3.4; 9.16 Petrus, physician of antiquity 4.1.11.2
Phaedo, friend of Socrates 4.4.2.3 Phaenarete, father of Praxitela and grand-
father of Hippocrates 4.1.1 Phaestis, mother of Aristotle 4.6.2.1 Phalaris, 6th-c. BC tyrant of Akragas (the
modern Agrigento) in Sicily 4.3.6.2n Phanias, physician of antiquity, pupil of Plato
the Physician 3.5
Pherecydes of Syrus, early cosmologist,
teacher of Pythagoras 4.3.4.1; 4.3.4.2; 4.3.6.2n
Philadelphus, Ptolemy ⅠⅠ Philadelphus, ruler of Egypt 283–46BC 5.1.5–5.1.8.1 (transla-
tion of Torah)
Philagrius, 3rd–4th-c. medical author 3.6; 5.1.37 no. 80; 5.2.2 (works); 6.5.2; 10.8.12n; 14.25.9 no. 34
Philinus of Kos, founder of Empiricist sect
(active 260BC) 1.1; 3.5
Philip, king of Macedon, father of Alexander
the Great 4.6.2.3
Philip Arrhidaeus, half-brother of Alexander
the Great 5.1.8.1n (era of)
Philo, slave belonging to Aristotle 4.6.6.2 Philo (or Philon) of Tarsus, 1st-c. pharmaco-
logist 1.9; 4.1.11.2; 11.5.2
Philocles, 5th-c. BC tragedian 4.1.11.3n Philotimus, Dogmatist physician of antiquity 3.5
Phlegyas, father of Coronis, the mother of
Asclepius 2.1.6.1n
Piso, dedicatee of Galen 5.1.37 no. 83 Plato, 4th-c. BC philosopher 1.2; 4.1.11.3; 4.1.11.4; 4.4.3; 4.5; 5.1.12.3; 5.1.26; 5.1.32;
{443}{!} 5.1.37 nos. 45, 46, 123 (summaries
of his works); 10.1.14 no. 36; 10.3.14
no. 143; 10.4.9 no. 16; 11.5.25 nos. 80, 130; 14.22.4.3 no. 44.7; 14.25.2; 14.25.5n; 14.25.9 nos. 76, 95; 15.1.3.2; 15.1.5 nos. 31, 53, 107; 15.40.9 no. 124; AⅠⅠ.2.2n
Plato the Physician, legendary ancient Greek physician 3.2; 3.5
Pliny the Younger, 1st/2nd-c. courtier 5.1.8.2n
Plotinus 4.6.13.3n; 9.13n
Plutarch of Athens, Neoplatonist philosopher 4.1.11.3; 4.5.1n
Plutarch of Chaeronea (ca. 45–120) 11.5.25
nos. 130, 138
Podalirus, son of Asclepius 2.1.5n Polemon, 2nd-c. Greek nobleman 4.1.6
Poliarcho, disciple of Hippocrates 4.1.10.1n
Politianus (Balīṭīyān), patriarch of Alexan-
dria and physician 14.1
Polybus, son-in-law of Hippocrates 4.1.2; 4.1.10.1
Polycrates, tyrant of Samos 4.3.4.2 Porphyry, philosopher author of Ioa􏲉l􏲉d (d.
ca. 305) 4.1.10.5; 4.1.11.3; 4.3.2n; 4.3.3; 4.3.6.1; 4.3.6.2; 8.29.22n; 10.1.14 no. 23; 10.2.4 no. 1; 10.21 no. 3; 10.23.3 no. 3; 10.37.5 no. 33; 11.2; 11.5.25 no. 76; 11.8.6 no. 15n; 11.13.2.4n; 15.1.5 no. 13; 14.22.4.3 nos. 1, 2; 14.25.9 no. 96
Posidonius, 4th-c. BC physician 14.25.9
no. 33 14.25.9
Posidonius, 2nd-c. BC philosopher no. 33 14.25.9
Praxagoras, late 4th-c. Hippocratic physician 4.1.10.1; 5.1.38 no. 153
Praxitela, mother of Hippocrates 4.1.1 Priscianus Lydus, 6th-c. Neoplatonist 4.1.11.3n
Proclus, Neoplatonist (d. 485) 4.1.11.3; 4.6.13.3n; 4.8.2n; 5.1.37 no. 45; 6.1.2; 6.1.3n; 6.2 (Diadochus son of Mulus); 11.5.13.no. 129
Protas of Pelusium, physician of antiquity 4.1.10.5n
Proxenus, executor of Nichomachus 4.6.2.1 (Pseudo-)Elias the Neoplatonist, (ca. 6th c.), commentator on Porphyry and Aristotle 11.8.6 no. 15
Ptolemy, later 2nd-c. A􏲬 astronomer 4.1.105; 4.6.2.1; 4.6.6.1; 4.6.13.1; 8.3.6n; 8.15.1n; 10.1.14 nos. 28, 119; 10.3.14
no. 101; 10.38.4; 11.3; 11.13.3.16; 11.15 nos. 7, 14; 11.19; 14.22.5.2 nos. 27, 64
works
A􏱌ka􏲉dop 11.12n; 11.13.2.5; 11.13.3.1,10; 11.13.3.16; 13.5.1; 14.22.2; 14.22.3.2; 14.22.4.2 nos. 3, 5); 14.22.5.1 nos. 18, 19; 14.22.5.2 no. 38; 14.22.5.2 no. 86n; 15.1.5
no. 1
Tdpnabhb􏱌lo 9.31n; 14.25.2; 14.25.9n;
O􏲤ph􏲍o􏲆 14.22.5.1 no. 18
Ptolemy al-Gharīb, author of the Vhpa Anho]
plpd􏱌ho 4.6.2.1, 4.6.6.1; 4.6.13.1–3 Ptolemy Philopator, 3rd-c. BC pharaoh 4.1.10.2n
Ptolemy the Physician 4.1.10.5 Pulcheria, sister of Theodosius ⅠⅠ 6.1.3n Pythagoras 2.1.4; 4.1.11.3; 4.1.11.4; 4.3; 4.3.2
(teaching and diet); 4.3.4.1–2 (travels and settlement in Italy); 4.3.4.3 (opposition of Cylon and death);4.4.1; 4.4.2.2; 4.5.1n; 4.6.3.1; 10.2.4 no. 34; 14.25.9 no. 24
Pythagoras ‘the physician’ 3.6
Pythais, mother of Pythagoras 4.3.4.1 Pythias, niece of Hermias, wife of Aristotle 4.6.2.1n
Qabīḥah, concubine mother of al-Muʿtazz
(nd􏲉. 252–255/866–869) 8.23.1 al-Qāḍī al-Ajall al-Sadīd Abū l-Manṣūr
ʿAbd Allāh ibn al-Shaykh al-Sadīd Abī l- Ḥasan ʿAlī `see` al-Shaykh al-Sadīd Raʾīs al-Ṭibb
al-Qāḍī al-Fāḍil ʿAbd al-Raḥīm ibn ʿAlī, 􏲡􏱎phb to Saladin (d. 596/1200) 14.33.3; 14.39.4
no. 4n; 15.18.1; 15.23.2.1; 15.24; 15.25; 15.40.3
al-Qāḍī al-Jalīs Abū l-Maʿālī ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz ibn
al-Ḥusayn ibn al-Jabbāb (`or` al-Ḥabbāb),
poet (d. 561/1166) 15.47n
al-Qāḍī Nafīs al-Dīn ibn al-Zubayr `see` Nafīs
al-Dīn ibn al-Zubayr
al-Qāḍī al-Makīn Abū l-Qāsim ʿAlī ibn al-Ḥusayn, unidentified 14.32.5 no. 4 al-Qāḍī al-Nuʿmān (d. 363/ 974), theologian
{444}
and qadi of the Fatimid caliph Muʿizz li-
Dīn Allāh 13.3.2.2; 13.3.2.3
al-Qāḍī al-Saʿīd `see` Ibn Sanāʾ al-Mulk al-Qaḥātībah, an important Arab family
settled in Khorasan 8.18.2n
al-Qāhir, Abū Manṣūr Muḥammad al-Qāhir
bi-Allāh, 19th Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 320– 322/932–34) 10.4.1; 10.4.2; 10.8.8; 10.26; 14.11
Qaḥṭān, legendary ancestor of the South
Arabs 15.47.2.1(p)
al-Qamarī `see` al-Qumrī
al-Qamrāwī `see` Najm al-Dīn al-Qamrāwī Qanbar, servant of Amīn al-Dawlah Ibn al-Tilmīdh 10.64.7
al-Qārah, Arab tribe famous for archery 10.68.2.2(p)
Qarāṭīs, head wife or concubine of the physi-
cian Yūḥannā ibn Māsawayh 8.26.8 Qasānjas `see` Ibn Fasānjas
al-Qāsim ibn ʿUbayd Allāh (d. 291/903–904),
vizier under al-Muʿtaḍid and al-Muktafī 8.14; 8.30.1; 8.30.5; 10.2.3.1; 10.2.3.2; 10.10.5
Qaṣīr, counsellor of Jadhīmah, pre-Islamic king of al-Ḥīrah 15.49.6.1(p)
Qayḍā al-Ruhāwī, translator associate of Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq 9.33
Qaymāz, Mujāhid al-Dīn `see` Mujāhid al-Dīn Qaymāz
Qāymāz, Quṭb al-Dīn al-Mustanjidī, Armenian Mamlūk of al-Mustanjid bi- Allāh 10.63.2
Qays ʿAylān, legendary ancestor of an import- ant branch of the ‘North Arabs’ 15.8.4(p); 15.8.6(p)
Qays ibn ʿĀṣim, famous tribal leader, contem-
porary of Muḥammad 15.52.1.1
Qays ibn Maʿdī Karib, pre-Islamic chieftain of
clan Kindah, ancestor of al-Kindī 10.1.2
Qays ibn al-Mulawwaḥ `see` Majnūn Laylā Qayṣar ibn Abī l-Qāsim ibn ʿAbd al-Ghanī ibn Musāfir al-Ḥanafī, ʿAlam al-Dīn, known as
Qayṣar and as al-Taʿāsīf, mathematician and architect (d. 649/1251) 13.63.8.1; 14.22.2; 15.51.6
al-Qaysarānī `see` Ibn al-Qaysarānī al-Qazwīnī, Raḍī, scholar 15.40.3
al-Qazwīnī, Abū Yaḥyā Zakariyyā ibn Muḥammad, physician, astronomer and geographer (d. 682/1283) 4.4.2.1n
Qiwām al-Dīn Ṣāʿid al-Muhannā 11.21 no. 5n; 11.22
Qubād, 5th–6th-c. Sasanian king 4.6.11n Qudāmah ibn Jaʿfar, author of Namc a􏱌]ogh􏱉n
(d. ca. 337/948) 15.40.9 nos. 20, 21 Quintus, 2nd-c. physician at Rome 4.1.11.2n; 5.1.25; 5.1.37 nos. 23n, 105
al-Qummī, Muʾayyid al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn
Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd al-Karīm, vizier
(d. 629/1231 or 630) 10.77.3 al-Qumrī (or al-Qamarī), Abū Manṣūr al-Ḥasan ibn Nūḥ al-Qumrī (or al-Qamarī),
Persian physician 11.11
Quraysh, Muḥammad’s tribe 7.1.5n; 7.2.1; 7.2.3; 7.5.3
Quss ibn Sāʿidah al-Iyādī, legendary pre-
Islamic orator 10.64.17.1(p); 10.68.1.4(p); 14.55.2(p); 15.31.2; 15.52.1.1
Qusṭā ibn Lūqā al-Baʿlabakkī 4.5.4n; 4.7n; 9.6; 10.44; 15.17(p)
Qutaylah bint al-Ḥārith, sister (or possibly daughter) of al-Naḍr ibn al-Ḥārith ibn Kaladah al-Thaqafī 7.2.3
Quṭb al-Dīn Qāymāz `see` Qāymāz
al-Quṭb (Quṭb al-Dīn) al-Miṣrī, physician and
philosopher 11.19.2; 11.20; 15.59 no. 1 Quṭb al-Dīn al-Shīrāzī (d. 710/1311) 14.48.4
no. 1n
Qutham ibn ʿAbbās ibn ʿAbd al-Muṭṭalib
al-Hāshimī, cousin and Companion of
Muḥammad 7.5.6
Quṭuz `see` al-Malik al-Muẓaffar Quṭuz Quwayrī (sometimes spelled Fūthirī `or`
Fūtirī), Abū Isḥāq Ibrāhīm, teacher of philosophy in Baghdad 10.18; 10.21; 15.1.2
Rabban al-Ṭabarī, physician and astrologer 11.3
al-Rabʿī, Taqī al-Dīn ʿAbbās ibn Aḥmad ibn ʿUbayd, father of ʿImād al-Dīn al- Dunaysirī 15.58.1
al-Rabīʿ ibn Yūnus ibn ʿAbd Allāh ibn Abī Farwah, chamberlain to al-Mansūr 8.1; 8.2; 8.3.4n; 8.3.22n; 8.25.2n
Rabīʿ ibn Zayd al-Ushquf (Recemundus),
Mozarabic bishop of Elvira 13.29.2
{445}
Rabīʿah, Arab clan of the tribe of Jaʿfar ibn Kilāb 15.8.4(p)
Rabīʿah al-Raqqī, poet under Hārūn al-Rashīd 8.3.18
Rabʿīn, Khorasanian chieftain and rebel in 141/758–759 8.10.3
al-Raḍī (al-Riḍā?), unidentified vizier of al- Jazīrah 10.69.3.11
al-Rāḍī bi-Allāh, Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉, 322– 329/934–40) 9.33; 10.4.1; 10.4.8; 10.5.3; 10.5.4; 15.1
Raḍī al-Dawlah Abū Naṣr `see` Ibn al-Tilmīdh,
Raḍī al-Dawlah
Raḍī al-Dīn al-Raḥbī `see` al-Raḥbī, Raḍī al-Dīn al-Raḍī al-Qazwīnī (?= Raḍī al-Dīn Abū al-Khayr Aḥmad ibn Ismāʿīl al-Ṭāliqānī) (d. 590/1194), teacher of dialectic and exegesis 15.40.3
Rafīʿ al-Dīn al-Jīlī, Abū Ḥāmid ʿAbd al- ʿAzīz ibn ʿAbd al-Wāḥid ibn Ismaʿīl ibn ʿAbd al-Hādī, chief justice of Damascus (d. 641/1243) 15.20; 15.49.2; 15.49.6
al-Rāghib al-Iṣfahānī, Abū l-Qāsim al-Ḥusayn ibn Muḥammad, 5th/11th-c. author of Mq􏲛􏱎􏳀an􏱎p a􏱌]qcab􏱎􏱏 10.64.19.15
Rāḥah (Rājah?), otherwise unknown Indian physician and scholar 12.2
al-Raḥbī, Jamāl al-Dīn ibn, physician (d. 658/1259) 15.36.1.4; 15.37.3; 15.38
al-Raḥbī, Raḍī al-Dīn, Syrian physician (d. 631/1233) 10.64.12; 14.31.5; 14.44.2; 15.29; 15.36; 15.42; 15.50.1; 15.50.4; 15.51.2; AⅠⅠ.15(p)
al-Raḥbī, Sharaf al-Dīn ibn, student of ʿAbd
al-Laṭīf al-Baghdādī (583–667/1187–1268) 15.36.1.4; 15.37; 15.50.6
al-Raʾīs Hibat Allāh, Jewish Egyptian physi- cian (d. 580s/1184–1193) 14.35; 14.43.2
al-Raʾīs Mūsā `see` Mūsā ibn Maymūn
Rajāʾ the physician of Khorasan 10.37.4 al-Raqqī, Abū Bakr Muḥammad `see` Abū Bakr
Muḥammad ibn al-Khalīl al-Raqqī al-Raqqī, Abū l-Qāsim ʿAlī ibn ʿUbayd Allāh,
transmitter 15.46.2
al-Raqqī al-Ti􏲪􏲤īsī, Abū l-Qāsim ʿĪsā, physician
and astronomer under Sayf al-Dawla Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn ʿAbd Allāh ibn Ḥamdān al-Taghlibī (nd􏲉. 333–356/944–67) 15.2
Rashīd, a servant of al-Muwaffaq bi-Allāh 8.32.3
Rashīd al-Dīn Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Khalīfah, physician and uncle of ʿAbd al-Laṭīf al- Baghdādī 10.83.5; 14.42.2; 14.44.4; 14.56.1; 15.1.3; 15.40.9 no. 85; 15.50.6; 15.51 Rashīd al-Dīn Abū Ḥulayqah ibn al-Fāris
(Rashīd al-Dīn Abū l-Waḥsh ibn al-Fāris Abī l-Khayr ibn Abī Sulaymān Dāwūd ibn Abī l-Manā ibn Abī Fānah), Egyptian physician known as Abū Ḥulayqah 14.49.2; 14.51.1n; 14.54; 14.55.2(p);14.55.3; 14.56.2
Rashīd al-Dīn Abū Saʿīd ibn Muwaffaq al-Dīn
Yaʿqūb, Christian physician of Jerusalem
(d. 646/1249) 14.56
Rashīd al-Dīn Abū l-Thanāʾ Ḥammād ibn
Hibat Allāh ibn Ḥammād ibn al-Fuḍayl
al-Ḥarrānī, teacher of Hadith 15.33 Rashīd al-Dīn ibn al-Ṣūrī, physician, botan- ist and pharmacologist, student of ʿAbd
al-Laṭīf al-Baghdādi (573–639/1177–1242) 15.45; 15.50
Rashīq, servant of Ibn al-Jazzār 13.3.2.1 Ravigupta, author of Shccgao􏱎na (`K.` Sh􏱋c]
gaog􏱎n) (active 650) 12.2 no. 4n al-Rāwandī `see` Ibn al-Rāwandī
Ray, Indian scholar 12.1
Raymond of Tripoli, regent of Baldwin 􏲫 of
Jerusalem 14.49.3n
al-Rāzī, Abū Bakr Muḥammad ibn Zakariyyā,
physician and philosopher (ca. 250– 313/854–925) 1.10; 4.1.10.5n; 5.1.32; 6.5.2
(source on late-antique medicine); 7.9.1n; 8.15.1n; 8.19.1; 8.19.6n; 9.15n; 10.56 no. 2; 11.4; 11.5; 11.8.4; 11.17 no. 6; 12.2; 13.59.4 no. 22; 13.61.4 no. 4; 14.21n; 14.22.5.1 no. 4; 14.25.2; 14.25.5; 14.25.9 nos. 51, 91; 14.56.4 no. 2; 15.1.5 no. 44; 15.36.1.1; 15.36.1.2; 15.60.1
Works
a􏱌]Khp􏱎b a􏱌]Ḥ􏱎s􏲞 e􏲞 􏱌]􏲝hbb 10.64.20 no. 4; 12.2; 14.21 no. 1; 15.39 no. 4; 15.50.7 no. 1 Dlqbpo l􏱋 Ga􏱌d􏱋 15.40.9 no. 101
Ta􏱉􏱎􏱌􏲞m 􏱉a􏱌􏱎 `K.` a􏱌]Ḥ􏱎s􏲞􏲆 14.56.4 no. 4
al-Rāzī, Ḍiyāʾ al-Dīn, eldest son of Fakhr al- Dīn al-Rāzī 11.19.5
al-Rāzī, Fakhr al-Dīn `see` Fakhr al-Dīn al- Rāzī
{446}{!}
al-Rāzī, Shams al-Dīn also known as Fakhr al- Dīn, youngest son of Fakhr al-Dīn al-Rāzī 11.19.5
Richard Ⅰ ‘Coeur de Lion’ `see` al-Malik al-Ankūr
al-Riḍā (al-Raḍī?), vizier of al-Jazīrah 10.69 Riḍwān, guardian angel of Paradise; name of
unidentified person 10.64.19.11(p) Risālah, a slave-girl of Slavic origin 8.25.8; 8.26.9; 8.29.3
Romanos, Byzantine Emperor 13.36.2.1; 13.36.2.2; 13.36.2.3
Rūfīl (`or` Rūbīl), apparently teacher of Abū
Bishr Mattā ibn Yūnus 10.21; 15.1.3.1 Rufistanes, fictional Greek king 4.6.7.2 Rufus of Ephesus, Greek physician (active 100) 4.1.10.2 (‘the Great’; his works); 4.3.2n; 5.1.26; 5.1.38 (confusion with Galen); 11.8.6 no. 12; 14.25.2
al-Ruhāwī `see` Isḥāq ibn ʿAlī
Rukn al-Dawlah, Abū ʿAlī al-Ḥasan ibn Būyah
(d. 366/976), Buyid emir 11.6
al-Rukn al-Dīn al-Rāzī, brother of Fakhr al-Dīn al-Rāzī 11.19.4
al-Rumaylī, 5th/11th-c. Andalusian physician 13.40
Rūsā (`or` Rūshī `or` Zūsī), female Indian med- ical author 12.2 no. 11

Ṣāb, or Ṭāṭ, son of Idrīs and reputed ancestor of the Sabians 10.3.1
al-Ṣābiʾ `see` Abū Isḥāq Ibrāhīm ibn Hilāl al- Ṣābiʾ `and` `see` Aḥmad ibn Waṣīf `and` `see` Hilāl ibn al-Muḥassin ibn Ibrāhīm al-Ṣābiʾ `and` `see` al-Muḥassin ibn Ibrāhīm al-Ṣābiʾ
Ṣābiʾans/Sabians, a polytheistic community in Ḥarrān (northern Mesopotamia) 1.5; 4.6.7.1; 8.29.6; 10.1.14 no. 207; 10.2.4 no. 29; 10.3.1; 10.3.2.3; 10.3.14 nos. 55, 147; 10.4.9 nos. 10, 15
Sabrishoʿ ibn Quṭrub (written Shīrshūʿ `or` Shīrīshūʿ), physician from Gond􏱭shāpūr 9.39
Sābūr, Arabic form of Shapur, name of sev- eral Sasanian emperors 11.19.6.2
Sābūr Dhū l-Aktāf, Shāpūr ⅠⅠ (nd􏲉. 309–379), Persian King of Kings 11.1
Sābūr ibn Sahl, early 3rd/9th-c. Christian physician 8.15.1; 8.16; 8.26.6n
Saʿd al-Dīn Abū Saʿīd ibn Abī Sahl al- Baghdādī al-ʿAwwād, transmitter 10.64.9; 10.66.6
Saʿd al-Dīn ibn ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz AⅠⅠ.16
Saʿd al-Dīn ibn Muwaffaq al-Dīn ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz
al-Sulamī, Damascus physician 15.35; 15.50.6
Saʿd ibn Abī Waqqāṣ, Companion of Muḥammad 7.1.1
Saʿd ibn Muʿādh, Companion of Muḥammad 15.57.1
Saʿd ibn ʿUbādah, Companion of Muḥammad 15.51.1
Saʿd al-Mulk Naṣīr al-Dīn Abū l-Maḥāsin Saʿd al-Mulk, vizier of Muḥammad ibn Malik-Shāh (496/1103) and of Malik-Shāh ⅠⅠ (498/1105) 10.64.19.16
Saʿdān the Shoemaker (Saʿdān al-Iskāf ) 15.17
Ṣadaqah ibn Manjā ibn Ṣadaqah al-Sāmirī 14.42.3 no. 4; 15.46.3; 15.47
Ṣadaqah ibn Manṣūr ibn Dubays al-Asadī, Sayf al-Dawlah, Mazyadid ruler of al- Ḥillah (nd􏲉. 479–501/1086–1108) 10.64
.19.13; 10.65.2(p); 10.65.3
Ṣadaqah al-Sāmirī `see` Ṣadaqah ibn Manjā al-Sadīd Abū l-Manṣūr ʿAbd Allāh `see` al-Shaykh al-Sadīd Raʾīs al-Ṭibb
Sadīd al-Dīn, father of ⅠAU 14.26.2n; 14.29.2; 14.34.2; 15.49.6
Sadīd al-Dīn Abū l-Faḍl Dāwūd ibn Abī l-
Bayān Sulaymān ibn Abī l-Faraj Isrāʾīl ibn Abī l-Ṭayyib Sulaymān ibn Mubārak `see` Ibn Abī l-Bayān
Sadīd al-Dīn Abū Manṣūr, son of Muwaffaq al-Dīn Yaʿqūb ibn Siqlāb 15.44
Sadīd al-Dīn ibn Raqīqah `see` Ibn Raqīqah Sadīd al-Dīn Maḥmūd ibn ʿUmar ibn
Muḥammad al-Ṭabīb al-Ḥanawī, `see` Ibn
Raqīqah
Sadīd al-Dīn al-Manṭiqī, probably to be iden-
tified with Sadīd al-Dīn ibn Raqīqah 13.58.2.1; 14.23.2; 14.30; 15.49.6; 15.51.1
al-Sadīd Raʿīs al-Ṭibb, al-Shaykh `see` al- Shaykh al-Sadīd Raʿīs al-Ṭibb
Saʿdūn, son-in-law of Ghālib the physician 10.10.5
al-Ṣafadī, Khalīl ibn Aybak, historian (d. 763/1363) 7.1.5n; 7.2.3n; 8.4.3n;
{447} 8.2.11n; 8.26.11n; 8.26.13n; 8.26.16n; 8.29.8n; 8.30.5n
al-Saffāḥ, first Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 132– 136/749–54) 8.7; 8.18.1n
Ṣafī al-Dīn ibn Shukr, al-Ṣāḥib Abū Muḥam-
mad ʿAbd Allāh ibn ʿAlī, Ayyubid vizier (548–622/1154–1225) 14.31.7; 15.36.1.3; 15.48; 15.50.1
Ṣafī al-Dīn Ibrāhīm ibn Marzūq, vizier of al-Malik al-Ashraf ibn al-Malik al-ʿĀdil 15.36.1.2
Ṣafī al-Dīn Khalīl ibn Abī l-Faḍl ibn Manṣūr al-Tanūkhī, 􏲡􏱎phb of Latakiyah 15.15; 15.18.1.3
Saḥbān, legendary orator and poet of the
tribe of Wāʾil 15.31.1; 15.37.4(p); 15.47 .2.1(p); 15.52.1.1(p)
al-Ṣāḥib Ibn ʿAbbād `see` Ibn ʿAbbād
al-Ṣāḥib Ṣafī al-Dīn ibn Shukr `see` Ṣafī al-Dīn
ibn Shukr
al-Sāhir `see` Yūsuf known as al-Sāhir
Sahl al-Kawsaj (Sahl the Beardless), early 3rd/9th-c. p􏲸ysician 8.15
Sahl ibn Jubayr, early 3rd/9th-c. p􏲸ysician 8.15.1
Sahlān ibn ʿUthmān ibn Kaysān, Abū l-
Ḥasan, Christian physician (d. 380/991) 14.15; 14.43.3 no. 1n
Saḥnūn ibn Saʿīd ibn Ḥabīb al-Tanūkhī (d. 240/855), Mālikī scholar 13.63.2 Saʿīd, grandfather of al-Tamīmī 14.14.3
Ṣāʿid al-Andalusī (al-Qāḍī Ṣāʿid), Abū l-Qāsim Ṣāʿid ibn Aḥmad ibn ʿAbd al-Raḥmān al- Taghlibī al-Andalusī, author of Ṭabam􏱎p a􏱌]qkak (d. 462/1070) 4.1.11.4; 4.2; 4.4.1; 4.4.2.1n; 4.6.3.2n; 4.6.4.1; 10.1.8; 11.5.8; 13.4; 13.5.1; 13.6.1.1; 13.6.1.2; 13.9; 13.27.2; 13.29.2; 13.34.2; 13.37; 13.38.1; 13.39.2; 13.60.2; 15.1.3n; 15.1.3.2
Saʿīd al-Dawlah Abū l-Fakhr, Egyptian physi- cian, son of Abū l-Barakāt ibn Shaʿyā 14.41
Saʿīd ibn ʿAbd Rabbih, Abū ʿUthmān ibn ʿAbd
al-Raḥmān ibn Muḥammad 13.24
Ṣāʿid ibn ʿAbdūs, Abū Manṣūr, physician con-
temporary with Ibn al-Ṭayyib 10.37.4 Ṣāʿid ibn Bishr ibn ʿAbdūs 10.13; 10.23.2; 10.38.4
Saʿīd ibn al-Biṭrīq (Eutychius), physician, pat-
riarch of Alexandria, historian author of `K.` a􏱌]p􏱎n􏲞􏲡g a􏱌]ka􏲳k􏱊􏱉 a􏱌􏱎]􏱌]pa􏲛m􏲞m sa]􏱌]pa􏲚c􏲞m (Na􏲟k a􏱌]􏲳asgan) (263– 328/877–940) 14.1; 14.10n; 14.11; 14.12
Saʿīd ibn Fatḥūn al-Saraqusṭī, contemporary of Ibn al-Kattānī 13.29.2; 13.36.2.3n
Saʿīd ibn Ghālib, son of Ghālib the physician 10.10.5; 10.11
Ṣāʿid ibn al-Ḥasan `see` Abū l-ʿAlāʾ Ṣāʿid ibn al-Ḥasan
Ṣāʿid ibn al-Ḥasan al-Rabaʿī al-Baghdādī (d. 417/1026), philologist AⅠ.1n
Saʿīd ibn Hibat Allāh ibn al-Ḥusayn, Abū l- Ḥasan, 5th/11th-c. physician 10.58; 10.59.1; 10.60; 10.66.1
Ṣāʿid ibn Hibat Allāh ibn al-Muʾammil `see` Ibn
al-Muʾammil
Ṣāʿid ibn Hibat Allāh ibn Tūmā `see` Abū l-
Faraj Ṣāʿid ibn Hibat Allāh
Saʿīd ibn Isḥāq al-Naṣrānī, chronicler under
Hārūn al-Rashīd 8.3.13
Saʿīd ibn Jubayr, 1st/7th-c. legal scholar from
Kufah 7.9.4
Ṣāʿid ibn Makhlad, Abū l-ʿAlāʾ, Dhū l-
Wizāratayn, 􏲡􏱎phb to al-Muwaffaq and vizier to al-Muʿtamid (d. 276/889) 8.32.3; 10.10.3
Saʿīd ibn Ṣāliḥ, chamberlain of al-Mutawakkil 8.12.2
Saʿīd ibn Salm ibn Qutaybah ibn Muslim,
chieftain of Zāʾidah clan 8.10.3 Saʿīd ibn Tawfīl, Abū ʿUthmān, Christian
physician in the service of Aḥmad ibn
Ṭūlūn 14.3; 14.4; 13.1.3 no. 4
Saʿīd ibn al-Umawī, a source for Ibn Juljul 7.1.6
Saʿīd ibn Yaʿqūb al-Dimashqī `see` Abū ʿUth-
mān Saʿīd ibn Yaʿqūb al-Dimashqī al-Sakhāwī, ʿAlam al-Dīn, grammarian and
kqmnh􏱏 15.37.1
Ṣakih, otherwise unknown Indian physician
and scholar 12.2
Ṣakhr, brother of al-Khansāʾ 10.51.3n; 15.17(p)
Saladin `see` Ṣalāḥ al-Dīn (Saladin)
Ṣalāḥ al-Dīn ibn Muḥammad Yāghī Siyān, 13th-c. emir of Hama 15.46.3; 15.46.3.8 Ṣalāḥ al-Dīn/Saladin, Yūsuf ibn Ayyūb,
al-Malik al-Nāṣir, Ayyubid monarch (532–
{448} 589/1138–1193) 10.63.2; 13.79n; 14.31.6; 14.32.1; 14.32.5n; 14.32.5 no. 8n; 14.33.1; 14.33.3; 14.34.2n; 14.36.1; 14.36.2n; 14.37n; 14.38.1; 14.39.1; 14.39.4 no. 3; 14.40.1n; 14.43.2n; 14.44.2n; 14.47.2n; 14.49.2–4; 14.50; 14.54.15; 14.55.2n; 15.11.1; 15.11.2; 15.11.3 nos. 7, 11; 15.13; 15.14; 15.16; 15.18.1; 15.23.1; 15.23.1.1; 15.23.1.2; 15.23.2; 15.23.2.2; 15.24; 15.25; 15.26; 15.27; 15.28; 15.36; 15.40; 15.48; 15.51
Salāmah ibn Muʿattib, one of the ancestors of the Banū Kunnah subtribe 7.1.6n
Salāmah ibn Raḥmūn (Abū l-Khayr Salāmah ibn Mubārak ibn Raḥmūn), Jewish Egyp- tian physician 14.23.3; 14.27
Ṣāliḥ ibn Bahlah al-Hindī, Indian physician in household of Hārūn al-Rashīd, perhaps descendant of Bhela author of the Sa􏲶] ghp􏱎 8.20.11n; 12.6
Ṣāliḥ ibn al-Rashīd, son of Hārūn al-Rashīd, governor of al-Baṣrah 8.3.15
Ṣāliḥ ibn Shaykh ibn ʿAmīrah ibn Ḥayyān ibn Surāqah al-Asadī, patient of Ibn Mās- awayh (217/832) 8.26.13
Ṣāliḥ ibn Waṣīf, Turkish military captain and ruler in Samarra in the reign of al- Muhtadī (255–256/869–70) 8.23.3
Sālim, eunuch `mawlā` of Hārūn al-Rashīd 8.1.2
Sallām al-Abrash, Abū Salamah, early trans- lator and member of Hārūn al-Rashīd’s household 8.15.1; 8.29.2; 12.6
Salm, superintendent of the Bayt al-Ḥikmah in Baghdad 5.29.5
Salmā, intellectual under al-Maʾmūn 8.29 al-Salmāsī, ʿImād al-Dīn ʿUthmān ibn Ismāʿīl
ibn Khalīl 15.22
Salmawayh ibn Bunān, Christian physician of
al-Muʿtaṣim, collaborator of Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq (d. 225/840) 7.8.3; 8.20; 8.26.10; 8.27.3; 9.49; 10.1.9
Samāʾ al-Dawlah, Abū l-Ḥasan ibn Shams al-Dawlah, Būyid emir of Hamadan (nd􏲉. 412–414/1020–1023) 11.13.3.7–8 Samānah, chief steward of the caliph al-Wāthiq 8.26.2
al-Samʿānī, Abū Saʿd (incorrectly Saʿīd) ʿAbd
al-Karīm ibn Abī Bakr Muḥammad ibn Abī l-Muẓaffar (al-)Manṣūr al-Tamīmī
al-Marwazī al-Shafiʿī, Tāj al-Islām (al- Dīn) Qiwām al-Dīn, also known as Ibn al-Samʿānī, biographer (506–562/1113– 1166) 15.13
Samaritans, Israelite sect 15.36.1.1; 15.47.1; 15.48(p); 15.49.1; 15.60.1
al-Samarqandī, Badr al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn Bahrām ibn Muḥammad al-Qalānisī, physician 11.22
al-Samarqandī, Najīb al-Dīn Abū Ḥāmid Muḥammad ibn ʿAlī ibn ʿUmar, physician in Herat 11.23
al-Samawʾal, pre-Islamic Jewish poet 15.8.11(p)
al-Samawʾal ibn Yaḥyā ibn ʿAbbās al- Maghribī, mathematician (d. 570/1174) 11.21
Sāmīn (or Binyāmīn) `see` Binyāmīn al-Sāmirī `see` Ṣadaqah al-Sāmirī `and` `see`
Muwaffaq al-Dīn Yaʿqūb `and` `see` Muhadh-
dhab al-Dīn Yūsuf
al-Ṣanawbarī, Abū Bakr Aḥmad ibn Muḥam-
mad, poet (d. 334/945) 15.8n; 8.30.5n Sancho 􏲫ⅠⅠ, King of Navarre 13.71n Sanḥārīb, Armenian ruler and patron of
Qusṭā ibn Lūqā (active late 9th–early 10th-c.) 10. 44.4
al-Sanī al-Baʿlabakkī, Christian physician at
Damascus 10.64.13; 15.3.1; 15.3.1.2 Ṣanjahal, Indian physician and astrologer 12.2
Sanjar, Aḥmad ibn Malikshāh, Seljuq ruler (nd􏲉. 490–552/1118–1157) 10.68.2.1(p)
al-Sanjārī, ʿAzīz al-Dīn, judge 15.50.6 al-Sarakhsī, Aḥmad ibn al-Ṭayyib 8.29.11; 10.1.9; 10.2; 10.3.14 no. 50; 11.5.25 no. 72 al-Sarakhsī, Thiqat al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Raḥmān
ibn ʿAbd al-Karīm, physician 11.19.7 no. 62
Sarī al-Saqaṭī, famous Sufi (d. 253/867) 15.51.7
Ṣārim al-Dīn al-Tabnīnī, Ayyubid emir 15.42
Ṣaʿṣaʿah, Arab tribe 11.13; 15.8.4(p) Satyrus, teacher of Galen 5.1.25; 5.1.37
no. 23n
Sawārtakīn al-Farghānī, servant of al-Muʿtaṣim 8.20.5
Sawwār ibn ʿAbd Allāh 15.37.2n
{449}{!}
Sayf al-Dawlah Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn ʿAbd Allāh ibn Ḥamdān al-Taghlibī, Ḥamdānid emir (nd􏲉. 333–356/944–67) 8.29.6; 10.31; 15.1.1.1; 15.1.3
Sayf al-Dawlah Ṣadaqah ibn Manṣūr `see`
Ṣadaqah ibn Manṣūr ibn Dubays
Sayf al-Dīn ʿAlī ibn Qīlīj (or Fulayḥ), emir 10.64.19.4n; 15.52.1
Sayf al-Dīn al-Āmidī `see` al-Āmidī, Sayf al-Dīn Sayf al-Dīn al-Kurdī, emir under ruler al-Malik al-Ṣāliḥ Ismāʿīl 15.49.4
Sayf al-Dīn al-Mushidd Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn
ʿUmar ibn Qizil, emir and poet 15.49.4; 15.52.2 no. 2
Sayf ibn Dhī Yazan, legendary hero 15.8.5n
Sayf al-Islām, Sayf al-Islām Abū l-Fawāris al- Malik al-ʿAzīz Ẓahīr al-Dīn Ṭughtukīn ibn
Ayyūb, brother of Saladin (d. 593/1197) 14.54.15
al-Sayyid al-Naqīb al-Kāmil Ibn al-Sharīf al- Jalīl, poet 10.64.17.1
al-Sayyidah (d. 419/1028), regent and mother of Majd al-Dawlah 11.13.3.3
Sejanus, 1st-c. A􏲬 Roman off􏲊cial 4.1.11.2n Seleucus, founder of the Seleucid empire 5.1.8.1n (era of); 8.29.11n
Seljuqs 10.68.1.4; 13.58.4.4n; 15.18.1.1n; 15.40.5; 15.40.9 nos. 85, 130; AⅠⅠ.5
Serapis, Greco-Egyptian god of healing 1.5
Serenus, Methodist predecessor of Galen 3.3
Sergius of R􏱭sh ʿAynā/Raʾs al-ʿAyn, Syriac
physician and translator (d. 536) 5.1.37 no. 101; 6.5.2; 8.29.3; 9.24; 9.27
Sergius, physician of antiquity, pupil of Plato the Physician 3.5
Sergius, pupil of Jūrjis ibn Jibrīl, later served Hārūn al-Rashīd 8.1.1
Sergius Paullus, prefect of Rome ca. 168 5.1.25
Seth `see` Shīth
Severus, anti-Chalcedonian patriarch of
Antioch 512–518 6.1.2 Severus, physician of antiquity 3.4; 4.1.10.5n
Shaʿbān, lampooned physician 13.58.4.9
al-Shabānsī, Qāsim ibn Muḥammad al-Qurashī al-Marwānī, Cordovan physician and poet 13.36.2.3
al-Shaʿbī, ʿĀmir ibn Sharāḥīl, famous trans- mitter (d. between 103/721 and 110/728) 7.2.4
al-Shābushtī, 4th/10th-c. man of letters 8.3.16n; 8.25.7n
Shādhān, Abū Saʿīd Shādhān ibn Baḥr, stu-
dent of Abū Maʿshar 10.1.5 al-Shadhūnī `see` Abū Muḥammad al-Shadhūnī
al-Shāfiʿī, Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad ibn
Idrīs, al-Imām, famous legal scholar, eponym of al-Shāfiʿite school (d. 204/820) 11.19.7 no. 12; 15.21 no. 1; 15.58 al-Shāfiʿī, Abū Bakr Muḥammad ʿAbd Allāh,
traditionist 15.46.2
Shaftar, nickname of poet Abū l-Maʿālī al-Sulamī 15.8.10
Shaghab, mother of al-Muqtadir 10.4.6 al-Shāghūrī, Shihāb al-Dīn Fityān ibn ʿAlī,
poet (d. 615/1218) 15.48; 15.50.6 Shāhak, Khorasanian mother of al-Sindi ibn
Shāhak 8.10.3
Shahdā al-Karkhī, Syriac translator 9.10 al-Shahrastānī, Tāj al-Dīn Abū l-Fatḥ
Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd al-Karīm, 6th/12th- c. historian of religions 4.1.8.1n; 4.1.8.3n; 4.1.8.4n; 4.4.2.1n; AⅠⅠ.8.1
al-Shahrazūrī, 7th/13th-c. physician, historian
and philosopher 4.3.2n; 4.4.2.1n; 4.4.2.5n
Shahriyār, Khorasanian prince and rebel (d. 141/758–759) 8.10.3
Shams al-ʿArab al-Baghdādī ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz ibn al-Nafīs ibn Hibat Allāh ibn Wahbān, poet and `muḥaddith` (d. 622/1225) 15.51.3
Shams al-Dawlah, Būyid emir of Hamadān (nd􏲉. 387–412/997–1021) 11.13.3.3; 11.13.3.4; 11.13.3.6; 11.13.3.7; 11.13.3.8
Shams al-Dīn Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad
ibn al-Ḥasan ibn Muḥammad al-Kātib al-Baghdādī ibn al-Karīm, author of `K.` a􏱌]Ṭab􏲞􏲡g 7.2.3; 7.5.2; 10.62.2; 10.63.3; 10.76.2; 10.77.2; 10.79
Shams al-Dīn Abū l-Faḍl ibn Abī l-Faraj,
oculist from Damascus known al-Miṭwāʿ 15.8.4; 15.9; 15.33
Shams al-Dīn ibn al-Lubūdī, physician at the Bīmāristān al-Nūrī 15.30; 15.31.1
Shams al-Dīn al-Khusrawshāhī, ʿAbd al-{450}
Ḥamīd ibn ʿĪsā, physician, student of Fakhr al-Dīn al-Rāzī, 11.11; 15.44; 15.21; 15.60.1
Shams al-Dīn ibn al-Miṭwāʿ `see` Shams al-Dīn Abū l-Faḍl ibn Abī l-Faraj
Shams al-Dīn al-Khuwayyī, Abū l-ʿAbbās Aḥmad ibn al-Khalīl ibn Saʿādah ibn Jaʿfar ibn ʿĪsā, jurist under al-Malik al- Muʿaẓẓam ʿĪsā ibn al-Malik al-ʿĀdil Ⅰ 11.19.1; 15.19; 15.20; 15.50.6
Shams al-Dīn al-Kutubī, transmitter known
as al-Khawātīmī 15.37.1
Shams al-Dīn Mawdūḍ. Son of al-Malik al-ʿĀdil 15.52.1
Shams al-Dīn Muḥammad al-Ḥusaynī,
copyist working for family of ⅠAU 15.49.6
Shams al-Dīn Muḥammad al-Kullī, Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad ibn Ibrāhīm ibn Abī l-Maḥāsin, physician 15.53
Shams al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn Shihāb al- Dīn Fityān, son of Shaykh Shihāb al-Dīn Fityān al-Shāghūrī 15.48
Shams al-Dīn Muḥammad al-Wattār al- Mawṣilī 11.19.3
Shams al-Dīn al-Rāzī, youngest son of Fakhr al-Dīn al-Rāzī 11.19.5
Shams al-Khawāṣṣ Ṣawāb, vizier under al- Malik al-ʿĀdil 15.50.2
Shānāq, legendary Indian sage Cā􏲹akya (also referred to as Kauṭilya) and minister of Candragupta Maurya (nd􏲉. 321–298BC) 12.3; 12.5 Shapur `see` Sābūr
Shāpūr ⅠⅠ `see` Sābūr Dhū l-Aktāf
al-Shāqānī, unidentified Ṣūfī 15.40.3 al-Sharābī, Aḥmad ibn Hārūn 8.26.9 Sharaf al-Dīn ibn al-Baladī `see` Ibn al-Baladī Sharaf al-Dīn Ismāʿīl, al-Sharīf `see` al-Sharīf
Sharaf al-Dīn Ismāʿīl
Sharaf al-Dīn Ismāʿīl ibn ʿAbd Allāh ibn
ʿUmar, 7th/13th-c. 􏲡􏱎phb and poet 15.49.6.2
Sharaf al-Dīn al-Mutānī, Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd Allāh ibn Mūsā al-Ḥawrānī al-Mutānī (d. 659/1260–1261), student of Kamāl al-Dīn ibn Yūnus 10.83.3
Sharaf al-Dīn al-Muẓaffar ibn Muḥammad
ibn al-Muẓaffar al-Ṭūsī, mathematician and astronomer (d. 610/1213) 15.24; 15.33
Sharaf al-Dīn ʿUmar, preacher, father of
Burhān al-Dīn 15.49.6.2
Sharaf al-Dīn Yūsuf al-Baghdādī, son of
Muwaffaq al-Dīn Yūsuf al-Baghdādī 15.40.9 no. 60
Sharaf al-Kuttāb Abū l-Faraj Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad ibn Ḥamzah ibn Jiyā (or Jiyāʾ) (d. 579/1183), teacher of Ibn al-Muʾammil 10.78
Sharaf al-Zamān al-Mābarsāmī 11.22 Sharāḥīl ibn Maʿn ibn Zāʾidah, chieftain of
the Zāʾidah clan 8.10.3
Sharak `see` Caraka
al-Sharīf, Aleppan dedicatee of al-Samawʾal 11.21 no. 6 al-Sharīf al-Bakrī 15.35
al-Sharīf al-Kaḥḥāl, Burhān al-Dīn Abū l-Faḍl Sulaymān, oculist in Syria 15.25
al-Sharīf Muḥammad ibn Muḥammad al- Ḥasanī, Abū ʿAbd Allāh, Andalusian physician 13.55
al-Sharīf al-Murtaḍā `see` al-Ajall al-Murtaḍā al-Sharīf Sharaf al-Dīn Ismāʿīl, physician
in service of ʿAlāʾ al-Dīn Muḥammad
Khwārazm Shāh 11.24
al-Sharīf ʿUmar ibn Ḥamzah `see` ʿUmar ibn
Ḥamzah
al-Shaybanī, Najīb al-Dīn Abū l-Fatḥ Naṣr
Allāh ibn al-Muẓaffar ibn ʿUqayl 15.25 al-Shaykh al-Sadīd Raʾīs al-Ṭibb (al-Qāḍī
al-Ajall al-Sadīd Abū l-Manṣūr ʿAbd Allāh ibn al-Shaykh al-Sadīd Abī l-Ḥasan ʿAlī, Sharaf al-Dīn), Egyptian physician (d. 592/1195) 14.31; 14.47.2
al-Shaykh al-Sadīd ibn Abī-l-Bayān `see` Ibn Abī-l-Bayān
Shibl al-Dawlah Abū l-Hayjāʾ Muqātil ibn ʿAṭiyyah, poet (d. 505/1111) 15.18n
Shihāb al-Dīn Atābekī, governor of Damas- cus 15.40
Shihāb al-Dīn also known as al-Sharīf al- Marāghī 15.22
Shihāb al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Ḥaqq al-Ṣiqillī, gram- marian 8.29.8
Shihāb al-Dīn Abū Shāmah, authority on Qurʾan 15.52.1
{451}
Shihāb al-Dīn Fityān ibn ʿAlī al-Shāghūrī `see` al-Shāghūrī
Shihāb al-Dīn al-Ghūrī (Muḥammad ibn Sām Ⅰ, Shihāb al-Dīn, Muʿizz al-Dīn al- Ghūrī), sultan of Ghūrid empire with his brother Ghiyāth al-Dīn Muḥammad (569–599/1173–1203), sole ruler (599– 602/1203–1206) 11.19.3
Shihāb al-Dīn ibn al-ʿĀlimah, judge, half- brother of Najm al-Dīn ibn al-Minfākh 15.56.1
Shihāb al-Dīn ibn Fatḥ al-Dīn ibn Abī l-
Ḥawāfir, Egyptian physician 14.44.1n; 14.46
Shihāb al-Dīn al-Naqjawānī, musician 15.51.1
Shihāb al-Dīn al-Nīsābūrī, disciple of Fakhr al-Dīn al-Rāzī 11.19.2
Shihāb al-Dīn Ṭughrīl, early 7th/13th-c. Atabeg of Aleppo 15.40.6; 15.40.7
Shiklah, mother of Ibrāhīm ibn al-Mahdī 8.8.3; 8.27.3
al-Shīrāzī, Abū Isḥāq Ibtrāhīm ibn ʿAlī, Shāfiʿite jurisprudent (d. 476/1083) 10.83.7 no. 2n; 15.21 no. 1
Shīrkūh, vizier under the Fatimids, uncle of
Saladin (d. 564/1169) 14.36.2
Shīrshūʿ (`or` Shīrīshūʿ) ibn Quṭrub `see` Sab-
rishoʿ ibn Quṭrub
Shīrzīl ibn Rukn al-Dawlah, emir (?of Iṣfa-
hān) 11.16 no. 1.36
Shīth, Seth, prophet according to Islam 15.17(p)
Shuʿayb, Jewish astrologer 8.3.10 Shuʿayb ibn Abī Ḥamzah, transmitter 10.81.3
Shuhdah bint Aḥmad ibn al-Faraj ibn ʿAmr
al-Ibarī, grammarian (d. 574/1178) 15.40.2
Shujāʿ, mother of al-Mutawakkil ʿalā Allāh 10.4.5
Shujāʿ al-Dīn ibn al-Ḥasan al-Baghdādī, musi- cian 15.51.1
Shukr ibn Abī l-Futūḥ al-ʿAlawī al-Ḥasanī, emir of Mecca, poet (d. 453/1061) 11.9n
al-Shumays, chief steward under al-Malik
al-ʿĀdil 15.50.2
Sībawayh, Abū Bishr ʿAmr ibn ʿUthmān,
grammarian (d. between 177/793 and 180/796–797) 8.29.8; 15.40.2
Sibṭ ibn al-Jawzī, historian 15.40.3n Sibṭ ibn al-Taʿāwīdhī, poet (d. 584/1188) 15.58.6n
Sibylla, brother of King Baldwin Ⅰ􏲫 of Jerus-
alem 14.49.3n
Siculus, Dogmatist physician of antiquity 3.5
Siennesius, disciple of Hippocrates 4.1.10.1n al-Siʿirdī, Jamāl al-Dīn al-Naqqāsh, contem-
porary of ⅠAU 1.2
al-Sijistānī, Abū Sulaymān `see` Abū Sulaymān
Muḥammad
al-Silafī `see` Abū Ṭāhir Aḥmad ibn Muḥam-
mad
Sīmā al-Dimashqī (Sīmā al-Turkī), servant of
al-Muʿtaṣim 8.7
Simeon of Taybūthā, physician 6.5.1 Simichus, tyrant of Centuripae, Sicily 4.3.4.2
Simmias, friend of Socrates 4.4.2.3 Simon, member of Aristotle’s household 4.6.6.2
Simplicius, physician of antiquity 4.1.10.2; 4.1.11.3
Simus, physician of antiquity 3.4
Sinān ibn Thābit, physician and scientist, son
of Thābit ibn Qurrah 10.3.14 nos. 49, 94; 10.23.2; 10.4; 10.31; 11.5.6
Sind (Sanad) ibn ʿAlī, astrologer to al- Maʾmūn 10.1.7; 10.3.14 no. 142
al-Sindī ibn Shāhak, ?ex-slave from Sind holding important off􏲊ces 8.10.3
al-Sinjārī, Ṭāhir ibn Ibrāhīm, physician 11.18; 15.60.2n
al-Ṣiqillī, Abū Bakr, director of a kacnaoag 15.57.1
Ṣiqlāb, servant of al-Mutawakkil 8.12.2 al-Sīrāfī, Abū Saʿīd Ḥasan (`or` al-Ḥasan) ibn
ʿAbd Allāh ibn al-Marzubān, grammarian
(290–368/903–979) 15.40.2
Sirjis al-Raʾsī `see` Sergius of R􏱭sh ʿAynā
Sīrk `see` Caraka
Sīsin al-Mannānī (Sissinios the Manichaean) 11.5.25 no. 13
Sitt al-Shām, sister of al-Malik al-ʿĀdil Abū
Bakr ibn Ayyūb 15.48; 15.51.6
Socrates, Greek philosopher 4.1.10.5; 4.1.11.3;
{452}{!} 4.1.11.4; 4.4; 5.1.32; 10.1.14 nos. 203– 206
Solomon `see` Sulaymān Solon, Athenian lawgiver 4.5.2
Sophists (a􏱌]S􏱊􏲌􏲻o􏲝􏱎􏱏huuag) 10.1.14 nos. 29, 173; 10.3.14 no. 12
Sophocles, legendary physician of antiquity 3.3
Sophroniscus, father of Socrates 4.4.2.1 Sophus, Dogmatic physician of antiquity 3.5
Soranus, 2nd-c. Methodist physician 4.1.11.2; 5.1.37 no. 101
Sostratus, ancestor of Hippocrates 4.1.1
Stephanus, Athenian admirer of Aristotle 4.6.2.2
Stephanus, late-antique physician 3.4; 4.1.11.3; 5.2.1; 6.1.1
Stephanus of Ḥarrān, late-antique physician 5.2.1; 6.1.1
Stoics (A􏲚􏲛􏱎b a􏱌]kh􏲟a􏱌􏱌ag), school of philo-
sophy founded by Zeno of Citium 2.1.6.4
al-Subkī, Tāj al-Dīn (d. 771/1370), Shāfiʿī jurist and historian AⅠ.1; AⅠ.2
Sufyān ibn Saʿīd al-Thawrī, 8th-c. Hadith scholar 7.4
Sufyān ibn ʿUyaynah ibn Maymūn al-Hilālī al-Kūfī, traditionalist 7.3n
al-Suhrawardī, Shihāb al-Dīn, philosopher and mystic 15.18; 15.20; 15.40.3
al-Suhrawardī `see` a􏱌ol Abū l-Najīb al- Suhrawardī
al-Sukkarī, Jābir ibn Manṣūr, pupil of Ibn Abī l-Ashʿath and Muḥammad ibn Thawwāb 15.4
al-Sukkarī, Jābir ibn Mawhūb, physician son of Mawhūb ibn Ẓāfir 15.7
al-Sukkarī, Mawhūb ibn Ẓāfir ibn Jābir, Abū l-Faḍl, physician son of Ẓāfir ibn Jābir 15.6
al-Sukkarī, Ẓāfir ibn Jābir, Abū Ḥakīm, physi- cian son of Jābir ibn Manṣūr 10.37.5
no. 40; 15.5
Sukkarah al-Ḥalabī, Jewish physician under
al-Malik al-ʿĀdil 15.15
al-Sulamī, `see` Muwaffaq al-Dīn ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz
al-Sulamī
Sulaym, Arab tribe 15.8.4(p); 15.8.5(p)
Sulaymān, Solomon son of David 1.4; 10.4.4.2n; 11.19; 15.46.3.2(p) Sulaymān, oculist of Baghdad 11.5.25.
no. 93
Sulaymān, `mawlā` of Hārūn al-Rashīd 8.3.7; 8.4.4
Sulaymān Abū Bakr ibn Tāj, physician in al-Andalus (active 310/922) 13.22 Sulaymān ibn ʿAbd Allāh ibn Ṭāhir, Baghdadi
off􏲊cial under al-Muhtadī 8.4.4 Sulaymān ibn ʿAbd al-Malik ibn Marwān,
seventh Umayyad caliph (nd􏲉. 96–99/715– 717) 8.13.2
Sulaymān ibn Ayyūb al-Faqīh (d. 377/987– 988), Cordovan jurist 13.24.2 Sulaymān ibn Dāwūd ibn Bābān, physician
accompanying Abū Dulaf 8.20.11 Sulaymān ibn al-Ḥakam ibn Nāṣir li-Dīn
Allāh, Umayyad ruler of al-Andalus (nd􏲉. 400/1009–1010 and 403–407/1013–1016) 13.45
Sulaymān ibn Ḥassān `see` Ibn Juljul Sulaymān ibn Mihrān al-Asadī, known as al-Aʿmash, Hadith scholar of the Tābiʿūn 7.4
Sulaymān ibn Muḥammad ibn ʿĪsā ibn al- Nāshī, Andalusī mathematician 13.6.1.2
Sulaymān ibn ʿUbayd Allāh, transmitter 10.2.2.1
Sulaymān ibn Wahb, vizier of al-Muhtadī 8.4.4
Sulayṭah, eunuch of al-Malik al-ʿĀdil Abū Bakr ibn Ayyūb 15.51.3
al-Ṣūlī, Abū Bakr Muḥammad ibn Yaḥyā, court companion of caliphs, expert on poetry and chess, author of `K.` a􏱌]Asn􏱎m (d. 335/947) 8.3.5; 8.21.10n; 8.26.11n; 8.26.17
Sumayyah, mother (possibly by Abū Sufyān,
father of Muʿāwiyah) of Ziyād ibn Abīhī,
governor of Iraq 7.1.1
Sunqār, rebel in Khorasan in the time of al-Manṣūr 8.10.2
Surkhāb (al-Kiswah), chief servant of al-Muʿtaḍid 10.10.5
Su􏳧ruta, 6 c. BC Indian author of the Sq􏳨nqpa]
Sa􏲶ghp􏱎 12.2 no. 2
Suwārtigīn al-Farghānī, an associate of al-Muʿtaṣim 8.20
{453}{!}
al-Suyūṭī, Jalāl al-Dīn (d. 911/1505), Egyptian polymath AⅠ.3
Syennesis of Cyprus, physician of antiquity 4.1.10.1n
Symmachus, physician of antiquity 3.4

al-Ṭabarī `see` Abū l-Ḥasan Aḥmad ibn
Muḥammad al-Ṭabarī
al-Ṭabarī, Abū Jaʿfar Muḥammad ibn Jarīr- Ṭabarī, polymath historian and Qurʾanic commentator (d. 310/923) 8.3.7n; 8.10.3n; 10.12.2; 10.22.2
al-Ṭabarī, Rabban `see` Rabban al-Ṭabarī al-Ṭabarī `see` ʿAlī ibn Sahl Rabban al-Ṭabarī al-Ṭabarī, astrologer favoured by Ghaḍīḍ 7.8.2
Tadrus al-Sanqal `see` Theodore the Syncellus Tādurā al-Usquf (Tādurī the Bishop),
Theodore of Karkh Guddan, patron of letters, associate of Sergius of R􏱭sh ʿAynā 9.42
Ṭāhir ibn al-Ḥusayn, Abū l-Ṭayyib, com- mander under al-Maʾmūn, founder of the Ṭāhirid dynasty of governors of Khorasan 7.7.2n; 8.10.4; 8.27.4
Ṭāhir ibn al-Ḥusayn ibn Yaḥyā al-Makhzūmī
al-Baṣrī, Abū Muḥammad, late 4th/10th or
early 5th/11th-c. poet 10.64n
Ṭāhir ibn Ibrāhīm `see` al-Sinjārī
Ṭāhir ibn Muḥammad ibn Yaḥyā al-Makh-
zūmī 10.64.19.4n
al-Ṭāʾiʿ li-Allāh, Abbasid caliph (nd􏲉. 363– 381/974–91) 10.5.1; 10.29
Tāj al-Dīn ibn Yūnus al-Bulghārī, writer on
simple drugs 15.45.4 no. 2
Tāj al-Dīn al-Kindī `see` al-Kindī, Tāj al-Dīn Tāj al-Dīn Muḥammad al-Urmawī, teacher of
ⅠAU 11.19.7 no. 37
Tāj al-Dīn Rashīq, eunuch (􏲡g􏱎chk) at the
court of al-Nāṣir li-Dīn Allāh 10.77.3 Tāj al-Mulk [al-Qūhī], general of Samāʾ al-Dawlah’s armies at Hamadan 11.13.3.7; 11.13.3.8
Ṭalāʾiʿ ibn Ruzzīk, vizier who held power dur- ing the reign of the Fatimid caliph al-Fāʾiz bi-Naṣr Allāh 14.31.6n
Ṭalḥah ibn ʿUbayd Allāh, opponent of ʿAlī ibn Abī Ṭālib at the Battle of the Camel 7.5.5n
al-Tamīmī, Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad ibn Saʿīd, 10th-c. physician 14.14; 14.25.9 no. 32
al-Tanūkhī `see` Ṣafī al-Dīn Khalīl ibn Abī l-
Faḍl ibn Manṣūr al-Tanūkhī
al-Tanūkhī, Abū ʿAlī al-Muḥassin ibn ʿAlī al-Tanūkhī (d. 384/994), judge and prose writer 8.29.6n; 8.30.5n; 10.62 3; 11.5.11, 11.5.12
Taqī l-Dīn Khazʿal ibn ʿAskar ibn Khalīl (Abū
l-Majd Taqī al-Dīn Khazʿal ibn ʿAskar ibn Khalīl), grammarian (d. 623/1226) 14.56.1
Ṭarafah, pre-Islamic poet 15.8
Tarmirah, physician of al-Muqtadir 8.5.2 Tāsh Farrāsh, commander in chief of the
Ghaznavid troops 11.13.3.18 Ṭāṭ `see` Ṣāb
al-Tatār (`or` al-Tatar), the Tatars or Mongols 10.13.6; 11.13.7.9; 11.19.5; 11.20; 11.23; 15.32; 15.38; 15.54
al-Tawḥīdī, Abū Ḥayyān, 4th/10th-c. intellec- tual and author 7.1.2n; 8.3.16n; 8.26.9n
Tayādhūq 7.9; 8.18.4
Tayādūrus (Theodorus), court physician to
Shāpūr ⅠⅠ 11.1
Ṭayfūr, ?father of the literary man and his-
torian, Abū l-Faḍl Aḥmad ibn Abī Ṭāhir Ṭayfūr, claimed to be the brother of al- Khayzurān, wife of al-Mahdī 8.10.2; 8.10.3
al-Ṭayfūrī, father-in-law of the physician
Yūḥannā ibn Māsawayh 8.26.8 Teucros, presumed author of the Ta􏱋􏲡a􏱌􏱊og􏱎 11.19.7 no. 53
Teuthras, dedicatee of Galen 5.1.37 no. 5 al-Thaʿālibī, Abū Manṣūr ʿAbd al-Malik
ibn Muḥammad, anthologist and poet (d. 429/1038) 4.6.10n; 4.6.11n; 7.9.2n; 8.29.22n; 11.9.1
Thābit the Translator `see` Thābit ibn Qurrah
al-Ḥarrānī
Thābit ibn Ibrāhīm ibn Zahrūn `see` Abū l-
Ḥasan Thābit ibn Ibrāhīm ibn Zahrūn Thābit ibn Ibrāhīm, Abū l-Ḥusayn, transmit-
ter 10.3.8
Thābit ibn Qurrah al-Ḥarrānī, mathem-
atician and scientist 1.5n; 2.1.5; 8.29.5; 8.29.22n; 9.12; 9.28; 10.1.5; 10.2.4 no. 25;
{454}{!} 10.3; 10.19; no. 1; 11.3; 14.22.4.3 no. 44n; 14.25.9 no. 45n
Thābit ibn Sinān ibn Thābit ibn Qurrah,
physician and historian 8.4.9; 8.23.2; 10.3.9; 10.4.4.1; 10.4.5; 10.4.6; 10.4.7; 10.4.8; 10.5; 10.10.5; 10.16; 10.26; 10.28; 13.19.1
Thaʿlab, Abū l-ʿAbbās Aḥmad ibn Yaḥyā ibn Zayd, grammarian (200–291/815–904) 15.40; 15.40.9 no. 10
Thales, member of Aristotle’s household 4.6.6.2
al-Thamānīnī, Abū l-Qāsim ʿUmar ibn Thābit,
grammarian (d. 442/1050) 15.40.2 Thamūd, legendary Arabian tribe 11.13.7.9 Thaqīf, an ancient Arabian tribe of the al-Ṭāʾif district 7.1.1n; 7.1.6; 7.2.1
Thawr ibn Murtiʿ ibn Kindah, pre-Islamic
Arabian chieftain 10.1.3
Theodosius, 2nd-/1st-c. BC Greek mathem-
atician and astronomer 10.1.14 no. 223; 14.22.3.2n; 14.25.2n; 15.31.6n (Treatise on S􏲤gdnh􏲍o)
Theon (d. A􏲬405), Greek mathematician 10.3.14 no. 117
Theano, king of Pytho 4.3.4.3
Themison of Laodicea, founder of the Meth-
odist school of medicine 4.1.10.4n; 4.1.11.2n
Themistius, philosopher and courtier (ca. 317–388) 14.25.2; 15.40
Themistius ‘the physician’, physician of antiquity 3.6; 4.1.11.3; 8.29.22n Theocritus of Anazarbus, physician of
antiquity 4.1.11.2
Theodore at Mar Saba, brother of Michael
the Syncellus 9.23n
Theodore of Karkh Guddan `see` Tādurā al-Usquf
Theodore the Bishop (a􏱌]qomqe ) `see` Tādurā
al-Usquf
Theodore the Syncellus (Tadharus, or Tadrus,
al-Sunqal), translator 9.23 Theodoretos, physician of antiquity 4.1.10.5
Theodorus, ancestor of Hippocrates 4.1.1
Theodorus of Athens, Greek philosopher 4.1.11.3
Theodorus `see` Tayādūrus
Theodosius, late-antique physician 6.1.1; 10.1.14 no. 223; 14.25.2n; 15.31.6n (Treat-
ise on S􏲤gdnh􏲍o􏳡
Theodosius ⅠⅠ, 5th-c. emperor 6.1.3n Theodosius, catholicos in the time of al-Mutawakkil 8.29.17
Theodotus, physician of antiquity 4.1.10.4 Theomnestus of Nicopolis, Byzantine writer
on veterinary medicine 8.29.22n Theon, 2nd-c. A􏲬 mathematician and philo-
sopher 4.1.11.3; 4.5.2n
Theophrastus of Eresos, philosopher and
successor to Aristotle (d. ca. 287BC) 4.1.11.3; 4.6.3.4; 4.6.3.5; 4.6.6.1; 4.6.13.1n; 4.7; 14.25.5 no. 7; 15.1.2
Treatises􏲆 9.37n (`Causes` le P􏱌a􏱋po and `On` Sd􏱋od Pdn􏲍d􏲤phl􏱋)
Thessalus, eldest son of Hippocrates 4.1.2; 4.1.10.1n
Thessalus of Tralles, 1st-c. Greek Methodist physician 1.1; 3.4; 3.5; 5.1.37 no. 20
Thomas of Edessa (Tūmā al-Ruhāwī), con- temporary of Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq 9.33; 9.34
Thrasybulus, dedicatee of Galen 5.1.37
no. 85
Thrasyllus of Mendes, 1st-c. A􏲬 grammarian
and literary commentator 4.5.1n; 4.5.4n Thuʿal, Arab tribe famous as archers 10.68.2.2(p)
Thumāmah al-ʿAbsī al-Qaʿqāʿī, brother-in-law
of ʿAbd al-Malik ibn Marwān 8.13 Tiberius, 1st-c. Roman emperor 5.1.8.1; 5.1.11
al-Tibrīzī, Abū Zakariyyā Yaḥyā ibn ʿAlī,
called al-Khaṭīb al-Tibrīzī, philologist
(d. 502/1108–1109) 15.40.2; 15.46.2 Timaeus, disciple of Plato 4.5.1 Timaeus of Locri, pseudonymous Neopy-
thagorean forger 4.5.2n
Timaeus of Tarsus, late-antique physician 5.2.1
Timaeus ‘the Palestinian’, commentator on
the works of Hippocrates 4.1.10.4 Timarchus, friend of Aristotle 4.6.6.1 Timbreus, disciple of Hippocrates 4.1.10.1n Timotheus, Greek philosopher, teacher of
Socrates 4.1.11.3; 4.4.2.1
Timothy Ⅰ, patriarch of the Church of the
East, 780–823 8.25.8
{455}{!}
Timurtāsh ibn Najm al-Dīn Il-Ghāzī, Ḥuṣām al-Dīn (reg. 516–548/1122–1154), Artuqid ruler 10.75.1; 10.75.3; 15.17
al-Tirmidhī, 3rd/9th-c. collector of hadiths 8.19.3; 8.19.4; 8.19.5
Titus, 1st-c. Roman emperor 5.1.8.2 Titus Ṭamīdiyūs, alleged 1st-c. Roman
emperor 5.1.8.2
Trajan, 2nd-c. Roman emperor 5.1.8.2; 5.1.11
Trallianus `see` Alexander of Tralles Tubbaʿ, rulers of pre-Islamic Yemen 14.32.4(p); 15.11.2.1(p); 15.37.2(p) al-Ṭufayl, father of ʿĀmir ibn al-Ṭufayl, tribal
hero and poet (d. ca. 10/632) 15.8.4(p) Tugashtal, `see` Nūfashal
al-Ṭughrāʾī Abū Ismāʿīl al-Ḥusayn b. ʿAlī, poet
(d. 515/1121) 10.64.17.3; 11.13n
Ṭughril Beg, founder of the Seljuq Empire
(nd􏲉. 1037–1063) 11.21 no. 3 Tullius of Alexandria, physician of late
antiquity 4.1.11.2
Tūmā al-Ruhāwī `see` Thomas of Edessa
Tumulicus, disciple of Hippocrates 4.1.10.1n
Tūqashtal `see` Nūfashal
al-Turjālī `see` Abū Jaʿfar ibn Hārūn Turkmen 15.18.1.2; 15.32; 15.49.3
Turks 8.4.10; 8.26.10; 10.69.3.9(p); 11.13
.7.9(p); 13.63.8.1(p); 14.54.3; 15.1.1; 15.11.2.1(p); 15.23.1.3; 15.50.2 al-Ṭurṭūshī, Abū Bakr Muḥammad ibn al-Walīd, jurist (451–520/1059–1127) 15.3.1.5
al-Ṭūsī, Sharaf al-Dīn al-Muẓaffar ibn Muḥammad ibn al-Muẓaffar, mathem- atician and astronomer (d. 610/1213) 15.24
Tycho, slave belonging to Aristotle 4.6.6.2
Tyrrhenus, brother of Pythagoras 4.3.4.1
ʿUbayd Allāh ibn Bukhtīshūʿ 8.4.13; 8.5.2
ʿUbayd Allāh ibn Jibrīl (or Jabrāʾīl) ibn ʿUbayd Allāh ibn Bukhtīshūʿ, physician and source for ⅠAU (d. after 1058) 5.1.7–5.1.13
(Galen’s dates); 5.1.8.1–5.1.9 (dates
of Roman emperors); 6.1.3 (on John the Grammarian); 8.4.10; 8.5.2; 8.5.4; 8.29.7; 8.29.8n; 8.6; 8.39; 10.8.3; 10.8.4; 10.8.5; 10.8.6; 10.17; 10.27; 10.29; 10.30; 10.44.4; 10.46.2; 11.5.6; 11.5.22; 11.12; 14.20; 15.2
ʿUbayd Allāh ibn al-Mahdī, governor of Egypt under Hārūn al-Rashīd 14.1
ʿUbayd Allāh ibn al-Muẓaffar `see` Abū l- Ḥakam ʿUbayd Allāh
ʿUbayd Allāh ibn Sulaymān, Abū l-Qāsim, vizier (d. 288/901) 10.3.14 no. 81
ʿUbayd Allāh ibn Yaḥyā ibn Khāqān, vizier to al-Mutawakkil 8.4.3n; 8.4.10n; 8.12.2n
ʿUdhrah, Arab tribe 14.32.4n
ʿUlayyān al-ʿUkkāz al-Ḥalabī, unidentified 15.8.12
ʿUmar, servant of Ibn al-Muṭrān 15.23.2.1;
AⅠⅠ.15
ʿUmar ibn ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz, eighth Umayyad
caliph (nd􏲉. 99–101/717–720) 7.1.5n; 7.4; 8.19.2
ʿUmar ibn Ḥafs ibn Barīq, Andalusian physi- cian 13.25
ʿUmar ibn Ḥamzah, al-Sharīf, grammarian 15.40.2
ʿUmar ibn al-Khaṭṭāb, second caliph (reg. 13–23/634–644) after Muḥammad’s death 7.1.5
ʿUmar ibn al-Farrūkhān al-Ṭabarī, astro-
nomer (active 762–812) 7.8.2; 8.3.10; 9.31n; 10.1.5
ʿUmar ibn Maʿadd, contemporary of Ibn al- Jazzār 13.3.2.1
ʿUmar ibn al-Qurashī, judge, pupil of Mu- hadhdhab al-Dīn ibn al-Naqqāsh 15.13
ʿUmar ibn Ṣakhr, companion of Saʿīd ibn Tawfīl 14.4.4
ʿUmar ibn Yūnus ibn Aḥmad al-Ḥarrānī 13.19; 13.29.2
Umayyah Abū l-Ṣalt `see` Abū l-Ṣalt Umayyah Umm Asmāʾ, concubine of al-Mahdī 8.8.3
Umm ʿĪsā, daughter of al-Hādī and wife of
al-Maʾmūn 8.10.3
Umm Jaʿfar Zubaydah `see` Ghaḍīḍ Umm Muḥammad, daughter of al-Hādī 8.10.3
Umm Muḥammad, daughter of Ghaḍīḍ 7.8.2
ʿUqbah ibn Abī Muʿayṭ, adversary of
Muḥammad 7.2.3
{456}{!}
Ūqlīdis, Uqlīdis `see` Euclid
ʿUrwah ibn al-Zubayr, late 7th-c. Medinan
jurist 7.5.3; 7.5.4; 7.5.5
Usāmah ibn Munqidh, Muʾayyid al-Dawlah
Abū l-Muẓaffar Usāmah ibn Murshid ibn ʿAlī ibn Muqallad ibn Naṣr ibn Munqidh, poet and anthologist (488–584/1095– 1188) 15.13; 15.43.3n
Usṭāth (Eustathius), circle of al-Kindī (active first half of 3rd/9th c.) 8.29.8; 9.21
ʿUthmān, unidentified subject of a riddle epigram 15.58.5
ʿUthmān ibn ʿAffān, third caliph following Muḥammad’s death, successor to ʿUmar ibn al-Khaṭṭāb 7.1.1
ʿUthmān ibn Thumāmah, son of Thumāmah al-ʿAbsī al-Qaʿqāʿī 8.13
al-Uṭrūsh, al-Ḥasan (d. 304/917), Shiite mis- sionary (Dāʿī) 11.5.25 no. 194
Vāgbhaṭa, author c. 600A􏲬 of A􏲚􏲝􏱎􏲴􏲉ag􏲵] caua]Sa􏲶ghp􏱎 (`K.` Aop􏱎􏱋􏲡an/Aop􏱎􏱋􏲉an a􏱌]􏲳􏱎kh􏱉) 12.2 no. 7n
Verus, Lucius, 2nd-c. Roman emperor 5.1.9
Vespasian, 1st-c. Roman emperor 5.1.8.2
Vitellius, 1st-c. Roman emperor 5.1.8.2

Wahb ibn Muḥammad al-Kalwadhānī, Abū Ṣaqr, 4th/10th-c. off􏲊cial 10.4.5
Wajīh al-Dīn al-Wāsiṭī, Abū Bakr al-Mubārak ibn Abī Ṭālib al-Mubārak ibn Abī l-Azhar Saʿīd Ibn al-Dahhān al-Ḍarīr, grammarian, teacher of ʿAbd al-Laṭīf al-Baghdādī (532– 612/1137–1215) 15.40.2
al-Walīd, poet (probably al-Walīd ibn ʿUbayd Allāh al-Buḥturī, d. 284/897) 15.23.4.2(p)
al-Walīd ibn ʿAbd al-Malik ibn Marwān, sixth Umayyad caliph (nd􏲉. 86–96/705–715) 7.6; 7.9.1n; 8.13.2
Wallādah bint al-ʿAbbās ibn Jazʾ, sister of
Thumāmah al-ʿAbsī al-Qaʿqāʿī, wife of
ʿAbd al-Malik ibn Marwān 8.13.2n al-Wāqidī, Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad ibn ʿUmar, historian (d. 207/822) 7.5.6 al-Warrāq, Maḥmūd ibn Ḥasan (d. ca. 230/ 845), poet AⅠⅠ.3.2
al-Washshā, Abū l-Ṭayyib Muḥammad ibn
Aḥmad, man of letters, grammarian and
lexicographer (d. 325/937) 7.9.2n Waṣīf the Turk, commander under al-Muʿtaṣim 8.4.10
(al-)Wathay 11.16 no. 1.17
al-Wāthiq bi-Allāh, ninth Abbasid caliph
(nd􏲉. 227–232/842–47) 7.1.5; 8.4.2; 8.4.5n; 8.4.10n; 8.20.5; 8.20.6; 8.21.4n; 8.26.2; 8.26.4; 8.26.17n; 9.46n; 9.49n
Wuḥaysh `see` Abū l-Waḥsh Wuḥaysh al-Asadī Sabʿ ibn Khalaf
Xenocrates, master of the Athens Academy 4.5.2
Xenocrates of Aphrodisias, 1st-c. A􏲬 pharma- cologist 4.1.10.5; 4.1.11.2
al-Yabrūdī, Abū l-Faraj Jirjīs [Jūrjis] ibn Yuḥannā ibn Sahl ibn Ibrahīm, Chris- tian physician from Damascus (d.
ca. 450/1058) 15.3
Yabūlūs, unidentified Roman king 1.8 Yāghī Siyān `see` Ṣalāḥ al-Dīn ibn Muḥammad Yahūdā ibn Saʿādah `see` Ibn Saʿādah
Yaḥyā ibn Abī Ḥakīm al-Ḥallājī, personal
physician of the caliph al-Muʿtaḍid 8.36
Yaḥyā ibn Abī Manṣūr, astronomer (d. 216/ 832) 14.25.1
Yaḥyā ibn ʿAdī, Christian philosopher and theologian (d. 363/974) 1.4; 1.5; 4.5.4n; 4.7n; 4.8.1; 8.29.5; 10.22; 10.23.1; 11.7; 11.8.2; 11.8.6 no. 13; 14.25.9 no. 78; 15.1.3.1
Yaḥyā ibn al-Biṭrīq, translator of philo- sophical works and medical author (d. ca. 200/815) 9.32
Yaḥyā ibn Isḥāq, physician in al-Andalus (act- ive 300/912) 13.21
Yaḥyā ibn Khālid ibn Barmak, member of the Barmakid family (d. 190/806) 8.2; 8.3.9; 8.8.1n; 8.8.2n; 8.29.22n; 12.2 no. 2; 12.3
no. 1; 15.1 no. 43
Yaḥyā ibn Māsawayh, 11th-c. writer on phar-
macology 8.30.4(p)
Yaḥyā ibn Saʿīd ibn Yaḥyā (also known as Abū
l-Faraj al-Anṭākī), Christian physician and historian continuator of Saʿīd ibn al-Biṭrīq (ca. 369/980) 14.10; 14.11
{457}{!}
Yaḥyā ibn Yaḥyā, known as Ibn al-Samīnah, physician from Cordova (d. 315/927) 13.4
Yaḥyā al-Marwazī (? = Abū Yaḥyā al- Marwazī), teacher of Abū Bishr Mattā 10.21
Yaḥyā al-Naḥwī `see` John the Grammarian Yandūn, servant of al-Hādī 8.10.3
Yaʿqūb (Jacob) 15.31.5(p)
Yaʿqūb, superintendent of Baghdad hospital 8.15.1
Yaʿqūb ibn Isḥāq ibn Mūsā ibn al-ʿĀzār
al-Israʾīlī, physician in the service of al-Muʿizz li-Dīn Allāh 14.9
Yaʿqūb ibn Killis `see` Ibn Killis
Yaʿqūb ibn Siqlāb `see` Ibn Siqlāb
Yaʿqūb al-Sīrāfī Ibn Māhān, physician and
author of a work on medical matters 8.38
Yaʿqūb of Edessa `see` Ayyūb al-Ruhāwī (Ayyūb
of Edessa)
al-Yaʿqūbī, geographer and historian 7.5.3n; 8.3.16n
al-Yaʿqūbiyyah `see` Jacobites Yāqūt al-Ḥamawī, geographer and
biographer 7.2.3n; 8.3.16n; 8.4.7n; 8.20.5n
al-Yasaʿ, Elisha, patron of translators 9.49 7.5.3n;
Yāsīn al-Sīmiyāʾī, magician
Yāsir, servant of al-Maʾmūn
Yazīd ibn Khālid ibn Rūmān, son of Ibn
Rūmān 13.14
Yazīd ibn Mazyad, chieftain of Zāʾidah clan 8.10.3
Yazīd ibn Muʿāwiyah ibn Abī Sufyān, the
second Umayyad caliph (nd􏲉. 64/684– 685) 7.5.2; 7.6
Yazīd ibn Muqbil, a rider in the courier ser-
vice of Iraq in the time of the caliph
al-Maʾmūn 8.26.17
Yazīd ibn Rūmān, Abū Rawḥ al-Madanī,
transmitter 7.2.3
Yazīd ibn Rūmān al-Naṣrānī al-Andalusī,
Christian physician 13.14; 14.6 no. 2 Yazīd ibn Yūḥannā ibn Abī Khālid, known
as Yazīd Būr, personal physician to al- Maʾmūn and then Abū Isḥāq Ibrāhīm ibn al-Mahdī 8.13
Yūfāl ibn Lāmakh ibn Matūshālakh `see` Jubal son of Lamech son of Methuselah
Yūḥannā ibn ʿAbd al-Masīḥ, Abū ʿAlī, friend of al-Faḍl ibn Jarīr al-Takrītī 10.39 Yūḥannā ibn al-Biṭrīq `see` Yaḥyā ibn al-Biṭrīq
Yūḥannā ibn Bukhtīshūʿ, Christian physi-
cian, collaborator of Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq (d.
ca. 912) 8.32; 9.30
Yūḥannā ibn Fātilah 9.37n
Yūḥannā ibn Ḥaylān, Christian philosopher
(d. during caliphate of al-Muqtadir) 15.1.2; 15.1.3; 15.1.3.2
Yūḥannā ibn Māsawayh, Christian physician 8.3.5; 8.3.8; 8.8.1; 8.15.1; 8.15.2; 8.20.2; 8.20.3; 8.20.8; 8.25.7; 8.26; 8.27.1; 8.29.2; 8.29.3n; 8.29.4; 9.49; 10.1.14 no. 272; 13.3.3(p); 14.2
Yūḥannā ibn Sahl, son of Sahl al-Kawsaj 8.15.1
Yūḥannā ibn Sarābiyūn, medical author probably later 3rd/9th c. (ⅠAU wrongly making him brother of Dāwūd ibn Sar- ābiyūn, q.v.) 6.5.1; 9.37n (a􏱌]Kq􏱋􏱋􏱎og
a􏱌]􏲚a􏲉g􏲞n); 9.49n; 10.8.12 no. 1; 11.5.25
no. 93
Yūnus ibn Ḥabīb, poet and critic (d. 182/798) 7.5.5n
Yūsuf, Joseph 15.31.5(p)
Yūsuf Ⅰ, Abū Yaʿqūb Yūsuf 13.63.3; 13.65; 13.72
Yūsuf known as al-Sāhir, physician in the time of the caliph al-Muktafī 8.39
Yūsuf al-Baṣrī, known as ‘the Short’, physician accompanying Abū Dulaf 8.20.11
Yūsuf ⅠⅠ, Abū Yaʿqūb Yūsuf al-Mustanṣir, Almohad ruler (nd􏲉. 610–621/1213– 1224) 13.65; 13.68.3; 13.71; 13.72; 13.75; 13.76; 13.78; 13.80.2; 13.82
Yūsuf al-Fāsī al-Isrāʾīlī `see` Yūsuf al-Isrāʾīlī Yūsuf ibn Aḥmad ibn Ḥasdāy, Abū Jaʿfar,
Andalusian physician 13.51; 13.59.4 no. 17
Yūsuf ibn Hibat Allāh ibn Muslim, unidenti- fied poet 14.32.4
Yūsuf ibn Ibrāhīm ibn al-Dāyah `see` Ibn al- Dāyah, Yūsuf ibn Ibrāhīm
Yūsuf ibn Ibrāhīm, `mawlā` of Ibrāhīm ibn al- Mahdī 8.27
{458}{!}
Yūsuf ibn Iṣṭifan, physician 11.16 no. 1.39 Yūsuf ibn Ṣalībā, physician accompanying
Abū Dulaf 8.20.11
Yūsuf ibn Tāshufīn `see` Ibn Tāshufīn Yūsuf ibn Yaḥyā al-Nāshī `see` Yūsuf al-Isrāʾīlī
Yūsuf ibn Yaʿqūb, student of al-Rāzī 11.5.25
no. 212
Yūsuf ibn Yazdād, physician 11.16 no. 1.34 Yūsuf al-Isrāʾīlī, Abū al-Ḥajjāj Yūsuf ibn Yaḥyā
ibn Isḥāq al-Sabtī al-Maghribī, Jewish physician often known as Ibn Shamʿūn (d. 1227) 14.22.3.2 (quoted as source
under name Yūsuf al-Fāsī al-Isrāʾīlī); 15.40.7n; 15.41, 15.50.7 no. 7
Yūsuf al-Khūrī `or` al-Qass (the priest), Abū
Yaʿqūb ibn Yūsuf ibn ʿĪsā known as Yūsuf the Translator, the Physician, and the Sleepless, physician under al-Muktafī 9.26
Yūsuf Laqwah, alchemist associate of al- Maʾmūn 8.11
Yūsuf al-Naṣrānī, Christian physician and patriarch of Jerusalem 981–983 14.10
Yūsuf the Translator `see` Yūsuf al-Khūrī `or` al-Qass (the priest)
Yūsuf al-Wāsiṭī, 4th/10th-c. Baghdadi physi- cian 8.5.2
al-Ẓāfir bi-Amr Allāh (Abū Manṣūr Ismāʿīl ibn al-Ḥāfiẓ al-Dīn Allāh), twelfth Fatimid caliph (nd􏲉. 544–549/1149–1154) 14.29.3; 14.31.6
Ẓāfir al-Ḥaddād al-Iskandarī, poet (d. 529/ 1135) 13.58.4.2
Ẓāfir ibn Jābir al-Sukkarī `see` al-Sukkarī, Ẓāfir
ibn Jābir
Ẓāfir ibn Tamīm, physician, presumably of
Ibn al-ʿAynzarbī 14.29.4 no. 4
Zāhid al-ʿUlamāʾ, Abū Saʿīd Manṣūr ibn ʿĪsā, physician of Naṣr al-Dawlah and brother
of Elias of Nisibis 10.54; 11.5.2 al-Ẓāhir li-Iʿzāz Dīn Allāh, seventh Fatimid
caliph (nd􏲉. 413–427/1023–1036) 14.21 al-Zahrāwī, Abū l-Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn Sulaymān 13.5.1; 13.8
al-Zahrāwī, Khalaf ibn ʿAbbās `see` Khalaf ibn
ʿAbbās al-Zahrāwī
Zahrūn, contemporary of Ibn al-Ṭayyib 10.37.4
al-Zajjāj, Abū Isḥāq Ibrāhīm ibn Muḥam- mad al-Sarī, grammarian (d. 310/922) 15.40.2
Zakariyyā ibn al-Ṭayfūrī, p􏲸ysician on cam-
paign with al-Afshīn in 222/837 8.11; 8.15.1; 9.49
Zakhariyyā ibn Thawābah `see` Anbā Zakhar- iyyā ibn Thawābah
al-Zamakhsharī, Abū l-Qāsim Maḥmūd ibn ʿUmar, grammarian (467–538/1075– 1144) 7.5.6n; 11.19.7 no. 8; 15.40.9
no. 12
Zangī ibn Āq Sunqur, ʿImād al-Dīn (nd􏲉. 521– 541/1127–1146), founder of the Zangid dynasty of Mosul and Aleppo 10.69.4
no. 5
Zankal, Indian physician 12.2
Zankī `see` Zangī
Zarāfah, majordomo to al-Mutawakkil 8.29.11
Zarathustra (Zarādusht) 1.5; 4.3.4.1 Zarayāyal, late-antique physician 5.2.1 Zarnab, pupil of al-Kindī 10.1.14 no. 79 Zarūbā `see` Zarūyā
Zarūyā (Zarūbā?) ibn Mānaḥūh (Mājūh?)
al-Nāʿimī al-Ḥimṣī, translator 9.14 al-Zawzanī, ʿAbd Allāh ibn Muḥammad ibn
Yūsuf al-ʿAbdalakānī (d. 431/1040), poet 15.1n
Zayd ibn Rāfiʿ, `mawlā` of al-Muhājir ibn Khālid ibn al-Walīd 7.5.2
Zayn al-Dīn, the blind, philosopher 15.52.1 Zayn al-Dīn al-Ḥāfiẓī, Sulaymān, physician
in Aleppo and Damascus under the Ayyu-
bids 15.32
Zayn al-Dīn al-Kashshī, disciple of Fakhr al-Dīn al-Rāzī in Marand 11.19.2
Zayn al-Dīn ibn Muʿṭī, grammarian (d. 628/ 1231) 15.51.2
Zayn al-Ḥassāb, unidentified 6th/12th-c.
pupil of Abū l-Bayān ibn al-Mudawwar
in Egypt 14.33.4
Zayn al-Mulk Abū Ṭālib `see` Ibn al-Khayyāṭ,
Zayn al-Mulk Abū Ṭālib
Zaynab, female physician of the Banū Awd 7.10
Zengi `see` Zangī
{459}
Zeno the Elder, i.e. Zeno of Elea, Presocratic Greek philosopher 4.1.11.3
Zeno the Younger, i.e. Zeno of Citium, Hel- lenistic philosopher 4.1.11.3
Zeno of Cyprus, 4th-c. A􏲬 Greek physician 4.1.10.2n
Ziyād, traditionist (?Ziyād ibn Labīd, a Com- panion of Muḥammad) 7.3
Ziyād ibn Abīhi (also known as Ziyād ibn Abī Sufyān), governor of Iraq and the eastern provinces under Muʿāwiyah 7.1.1
Ziyādat Allāh ibn al-Aghlab al-Tamīmī, last
Aghlabid emir in Ifrīqiyah (nd􏲉. 290– 296/903–907) 13.1.2; 13.2.2.1 Zoroaster `see` Zarathustra
Zoroastrians 1.5; 4.6.7.1
Zubaydah Umm Jaʿfar, wife of Hārūn al-Rashīd 8.3.22; 8.4.11; 8.25.7n
al-Zubayr ibn al-ʿAwwām, fought on ʿĀʾishah’s
side at the Battle of the Camel, killed by
Ibn Jurmūz 7.5.4; 7.5.5 Zūsī `see` Rūsā
